<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Labs on Brian O&#39;Meara Lab</title>
    <link>/lab/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Labs on Brian O&#39;Meara Lab</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en_US</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 04 Aug 2017 14:01:49 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/lab/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>DDIG</title>
      <link>/lab/ddig/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 04 Aug 2017 14:01:49 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/lab/ddig/</guid>
      <description>The Doctoral Dissertation Improvement Grant was a beloved NSF program that gave small amounts of money (up to $19K) for projects to enhance the dissertations of PhD candidates. Its cancellation was motivated by programmatic needs at NSF. Each DDIG grant requires as much diligence and work by NSF as a regular grant of hundreds of thousands of dollars; in an environment where NSF had to cut its workload, cutting this program dramatically decreased the number of grants NSF had to handle without impacting overall funding to biology as much as other programs.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Better letter</title>
      <link>/lab/better-letter/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 20 Oct 2016 22:30:33 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/lab/better-letter/</guid>
      <description>[advanced_iframe src=“https://bomeara.github.io/sentimood/index.html” width=“100%” height=“3000”]</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Funding</title>
      <link>/lab/funding/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 18 Jul 2015 01:09:48 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/lab/funding/</guid>
      <description>This is a list of successful grant applications from our lab (over $2.2 million since the lab started 6 years ago). The list of unsuccessful ones is rather longer.
 2015: NSF: CAREER Reducing barriers for comparative methods (5 year grant)
 2015: NSF: Co-PI on Collaborative Research: ABI Development: An open infrastructure to disseminate phylogenetic knowledge (3 year grant)
 2013: NSF: PI on Population genetics-based codon models (3 year grant).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Guidelines &amp; Recommendations</title>
      <link>/lab/guidelines/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 18 Jul 2015 01:05:44 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/lab/guidelines/</guid>
      <description>Lab members should review these; we are all expected to follow the guidelines. The University official policies are here; in the case of any conflicts, University policies apply. My goal here is to highlight the most relevant parts for the lab, but we are subject to all of them.
Getting help Depending on the severity of an issue, you could report it to me (directly or using the anonymous feedback form), to the EEB Department Head, or other resources on campus or elsewhere: see below.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>