<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Tutorials on Brian O&#39;Meara Lab</title>
    <link>/tutorials/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Tutorials on Brian O&#39;Meara Lab</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en_US</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 28 Jul 2015 03:42:22 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/tutorials/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Phylogenetics</title>
      <link>/tutorials/phylogenetics/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Jul 2015 03:42:22 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/tutorials/phylogenetics/</guid>
      <description>Phylogenetic analysis
Each item includes PAUP batch files or commands where appropriate. I wrote this page for the Farrell Lab website, but have included it here as well, where I continue to update it (occasionally). This page is mostly useful for the batch files which are on it. Some useful references which provide broader overviews of phylogenetics are Phylogenetic Trees Made Easy by Barry Hall, chapters 11 and 12 of the somewhat dated (1996) Molecular Systematics, 2nd Edition, edited by David Hillis, Craig Moritz, and Barbara Mable, and the recently updated Molecular Systematics website.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Model Selection Using the Akaike Information Criterion (AIC)</title>
      <link>/tutorials/aic/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Jul 2015 03:39:07 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/tutorials/aic/</guid>
      <description>This web page basically summarizes information from Burnham and Anderson (2002). Go there for more information. The Akaike Information Criterion (AIC) is a way of selecting a model from a set of models. The chosen model is the one that minimizes the Kullback-Leibler distance between the model and the truth. It’s based on information theory, but a heuristic way to think about it is as a criterion that seeks a model that has a good fit to the truth but few parameters.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>