<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss  xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" 
      xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" 
      xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" 
      xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" 
      version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>Brian O&#39;Meara</title>
<link>https://brianomeara.info/blog.html</link>
<atom:link href="https://brianomeara.info/blog.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
<description></description>
<generator>quarto-1.6.40</generator>
<lastBuildDate>Fri, 07 Nov 2025 05:00:00 GMT</lastBuildDate>
<item>
  <title>AI optimization</title>
  <dc:creator>Brian O&#39;Meara</dc:creator>
  <link>https://brianomeara.info/posts/ai_optimization/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>A colleague recently pointed out a preprint on arXiv, <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.02824">Mitchener et al.&nbsp;2025</a>, “Kosmos: An AI Scientist for Autonomous Discovery”. Part of its abstract, emphasis mine:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>Here we present Kosmos, an AI scientist that automates data-driven discovery. Given an open-ended objective and a dataset, Kosmos runs for up to 12 hours performing cycles of parallel data analysis, literature search, and hypothesis generation before synthesizing discoveries into scientific reports. Unlike prior systems, Kosmos uses a structured world model to share information between a data analysis agent and a literature search agent. The world model enables Kosmos to coherently pursue the specified objective over 200 agent rollouts, collectively executing an average of 42,000 lines of code and <strong>reading 1,500 papers per run</strong>. Kosmos <strong>cites all statements</strong> in its reports with code or primary literature, ensuring its reasoning is traceable. Independent scientists found <strong>79.4% of statements in Kosmos reports to be accurate</strong>, and collaborators reported that <strong>a single 20-cycle Kosmos run performed the equivalent of 6 months of their own research time</strong> on average.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>I’m not planning to use this (my accuracy is better than a C+, I’d hope), but I imagine colleagues will, and this is just its first generation. And researchers and others are using ChatGPT and related approaches to help with papers already, despite the known issues with made up citations. Popular app Grammarly now offers a <a href="https://www.grammarly.com/citations">service</a> that lets users write scientific statements (their example is from geology) and then it automatically finds and cites relevant papers – no need to actually read the literature, just decorate your text with the funny names and numbers in parentheses that make it look credible. Grammarly claims it is both a “partner for better grades” and will help you “turn claims into supported arguments.”</p>
<p>There’s a whole discussion to have about the ethics of using such services and the wisdom of the many colleges paying for their communities to have access to them. But I want to talk about something different: <strong><em>which papers these services will choose</em></strong>.</p>
<p>Search Engine Optimization (SEO) has long been a concern for website owners: how do we make it so that when people search “vacation in Aruba” my hotel site is the top hit? That matters for people in science, too (people on the job market, make sure you have a good website!), but it’s less of an emphasis. For writing papers, there’s some optimization (like the endless debate over the wisdom of including colons in titles), but it’s a messy, human process. And journals have various tactics for bumping up their impact factor (“Hey, want to publish version 1.2.1 of your popular software package in our journal?”; “Has there been a really good review of this popular subject published this week? Let’s commission one and get those citations!”). But <strong>increasingly, the entities “reading” our papers and deciding what to cite won’t be humans: they’ll be AI recommendation engines</strong> telling people what is most relevant. Even once the rumored AI economic bubble bursts, I suspect it’s unlikely tools like this will go away, unless there becomes enough of a pushback on their use that it becomes unprofitable to provide them.</p>
<section id="consequences-of-aio-artificial-intelligence-optimization-for-scientific-publishing" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="consequences-of-aio-artificial-intelligence-optimization-for-scientific-publishing">Consequences of AIO (artificial intelligence optimization) for scientific publishing</h3>
<ul>
<li><p><strong>Pressure to get in the corpus</strong>: Initially, AI was trained on huge chunks of the internet, books, and other sources, under a legal theory that it’s transformative fair use (various lawsuits by authors and publishers beg to differ). There are now some licensing deals arising for AI training, like <a href="https://www.latimes.com/business/story/2025-09-17/reddit-seeks-to-strike-next-ai-content-pact-with-google-openai">Reddit’s deal with Google</a>. In the search engine space, such deals are rare: for most websites (especially under the standard ad-supported model), views are what matter, so unless one has a truly unique resource (which arguably is Reddit) one doesn’t block any search engine, and in fact web publishers take steps to make searching easier (like creating site maps). The same pressures will come for publishing. A publisher might cut a deal to allow only AI company 1 to learn from their articles, and the publisher will get some money from that. If AI company 2 is what Grammarly uses to generate citations, then none of the publisher’s articles get cited by people using Grammarly to do their work, dropping impact factors across the board for that publisher’s journals. This also increases the pressure for work to be open access so there’s no paywall blocking indexing (not that paywalls have stopped scraping in the past).</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Formatting for bots</strong>: If most “readers” aren’t humans, one wants articles structured in such a way that the bots can parse them easily, to make them more likely to be recommended. This could lead to nice things like accessible metadata, but it could also lead to things like very inflexible article structure. My guess is that publishers will try to optimize for this as it’s pretty easy for them to test and control.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Writing for bots</strong>: Every recipe online starts with a multi-paragraph essay before getting into the actual recipe (with a few exceptions – huzzah for <a href="https://www.kingarthurbaking.com/recipes/fudge-brownies-recipe">King Arthur</a>!). This supposedly helps with ranking in search engines; it also <a href="https://copyrightalliance.org/are-recipes-cookbooks-protected-by-copyright/">helps with copyright</a>. It annoys actual humans who get to the recipe (thus the addition of “Jump to recipe” buttons on pages) but this wall of text helps get views in the first place. I don’t think that’s happening yet in science, but my guess is that making writing work best for AIO is coming. For example, Nature Publishing Group (NPG) now has a <a href="https://natureresearchassistant.com">manuscript advisor</a> that will give advice on style, alternative titles, abstracts, etc. (as well as suggest references). It would be easy to tune this so that the advice reflects what works best for getting a paper recommended later. I don’t know what specific advice that would be yet: maybe shorter sentences, maybe bulleted texts (like buzzfeed listicles), maybe long introductions so the paper is enriched for the words that signal its relevance to a field. Many journals are now including abstracts in two languages: the standard one for that journal and the language for the region where the work was done. If AIs deprioritize work with two languages, will there be pressure to discontinue two language abstracts?</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Figures for bots</strong>: Right now we create figures to appeal to people (“I’m limited to two figures – fine, see panel K of figure 1”). Recommendation engines focus on text at the moment, but there are enough video and image generation AI efforts that we can expect generators to start suggesting existing figures (with citations) as well, especially for student work. This will prioritize figures that each make a single point rather than multipanel figures, figures with insets, etc. This honestly is probably a good thing (if the number of figures is allowed to go up), especially for accessibility, but I expect this to start happening.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Reviewing by bots</strong>: “Is this article a good fit for this journal?” is a question human associate editors are often faced with, and part of “fit” is often “important enough.” It’s a very fuzzy concept and subject to all sorts of issues. I doubt we’re far off from being able to predict number of citations for a manuscript using a machine learning tool (based on factors like the subject of the research, nature of the discovery, connectedness of the authors, and more). For example, in my field, a paper describing new species is likely to have far fewer citations over the next few years than a paper describing a new software package, but their importance doesn’t necessarily match this. What will happen when editors, in addition to seeing “major revision, minor revision, minor revision” from human reviewers sees “this manuscript is expected to have only 48-57% of the citations of the median paper in your journal”? With pressures to improve impact factors (which are flawed but still used a lot) this may start having an effect. Some solutions for improving a potential low impact paper might be beneficial for science (“write this in a more accessible manner, making sure to define your terms”) some might not be (“have Bob write a few sentences and become a coauthor – everyone always cites Bob’s papers a lot, including him when he writes invited reviews”).</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Biases</strong>: We know that AIs and other algorithms trained on data can reflect human biases (see Cathy O’Neil’s <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Weapons_of_Math_Destruction"><em>Weapons of Math Destruction</em></a> which came out nearly a decade ago, as well as the work of <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Timnit_Gebru">Timnit Gebru</a> and many others). It’s not like humans picking papers to read and cite are bias free, but the AIs will have some of the same plus biases unique to them. For example, perhaps a recommendation engine prefers using fewer words (reduced use of tokens, maybe), so articles from <em>Evolution</em> might be recommended more than articles from <em>Proceedings of the Royal Society B: Biological Sciences</em> which requires more words to cite (maybe until it launches its rebranded title, <em>SirBio</em>).</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Spiraling</strong>: Mad cow and other prion diseases are what you get when you feed an animal on tissue from a closely related animal: a malformed protein is similar enough to its own proteins to lead to more malformed proteins, etc. and this gets worse the more cycles of cannibalism occur. There is a lot of work on the issues that can come from AI being trained on AI-generated material, and this is definitely going to happen, especially as there will be incentives to hide whether material in a paper is AI-created. To take a simple made-up example: if 10% of papers cited are from the Nature Publishing Group (a guess), and their Manuscript Adviser tends to recommend papers from their journals for legit reasons (“avoid super spammy journals from that bad publisher over there”), then perhaps the next year of papers has 11% NPG citations, and that then becomes the corpus for future years, and so forth.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Stasis</strong>: “What software should I use to make a phylogenetic tree?” The best software twenty years ago is not the best software today, and there could be some amazing new thing released tomorrow. Trained on a corpus of fifty years of papers on making trees, what will a recommendation engine suggest? More papers will use the older software, but perhaps it will have a bias for what the most recent papers use (if programmed in). But nothing in the training corpus will have used the new great tool. How long will it take to start recommending the newest, best thing? Probably longer than it would take a trusted colleague who keeps up with the literature to recommend the new software. This is especially true if one wants to prioritize work done pre-AI to prevent the spiraling issue.</p></li>
</ul>
<p>I’m not sure how to make this actionable for people at the moment – we don’t know enough about how AIO will work (maybe someone will launch a consulting company to start doing this). My guess is that it will lead to more harms than benefits. I do think it’s going to be the case that whether or not we individually <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Just_Say_No#/media/File:Photograph_of_Mrs._Reagan_speaking_at_a_%22Just_Say_No%22_Rally_in_Los_Angeles_-_NARA_-_198584.jpg">want</a> to use AI to help write papers, our professional incentives will lead us to make sure our work is present in the training corpus used by such tools and is optimized for its use. I also believe publishers are going to start acting to make the AIs happy. We can steer what happens to try to avoid the pitfalls, but it’s worth considering the structural incentives that will encourage certain changes.</p>
<p><em>Note after writing this, I noticed that the R package <code>pkgdown</code>, used to make websites, now has a <a href="https://tidyverse.org/blog/2025/11/pkgdown-2-2-0/">new function</a> that “that automatically creates files that make it easier for LLMs to read your documentation.” So optimization for output (in this case, help files for R packages one writes) to be used in a training corpus has already come for software.</em></p>
<hr>
<p>To subscribe, go to <a href="https://brianomeara.info/blog.xml" class="uri">https://brianomeara.info/blog.xml</a> in an RSS reader.</p>


</section>

<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-citation"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Citation</h2><div><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">BibTeX citation:</div><pre class="sourceCode code-with-copy quarto-appendix-bibtex"><code class="sourceCode bibtex">@online{o'meara2025,
  author = {O’Meara, Brian},
  title = {AI Optimization},
  date = {2025-11-07},
  url = {https://brianomeara.info/posts/ai_optimization/},
  langid = {en}
}
</code></pre><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">For attribution, please cite this work as:</div><div id="ref-o'meara2025" class="csl-entry quarto-appendix-citeas">
O’Meara, Brian. 2025. <span>“AI Optimization.”</span> November 7, 2025.
<a href="https://brianomeara.info/posts/ai_optimization/">https://brianomeara.info/posts/ai_optimization/</a>.
</div></div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>ai</category>
  <category>optimization</category>
  <category>seo</category>
  <category>publishing</category>
  <guid>https://brianomeara.info/posts/ai_optimization/</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 07 Nov 2025 05:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>PhyloPapers 2025, Reticulate evolution</title>
  <dc:creator>Brian O&#39;Meara</dc:creator>
  <link>https://brianomeara.info/posts/phylopapers_2025_Oct_10/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>This week I wanted students to learn more about reticulate evolution (phylogenetic networks):</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>Gil Yardeni, Michael H. J. Barfuss, Walter Till, Matthew R. Thornton, Clara Groot Crego, Christian Lexer, Thibault Leroy and Ovidiu Paun. 2025. “The Explosive Radiation of the Neotropical Tillandsia Subgenus Tillandsia (Bromeliaceae) Has Been Accompanied by Pervasive Hybridization” Systematic Biology <a href="https://doi.org/10.1093/sysbio/syaf039" class="uri">https://doi.org/10.1093/sysbio/syaf039</a></p>
</blockquote>
<p>This looks at subgenus <em>Tillandsia</em> inside genus <em>Tillandsia</em>, a group of morphologically quite diverse plants.</p>
<p>This paper was good for teaching because it was fairly focused: what is the phylogenetic network of the group and how is gene flow affecting this?</p>
<p>It’s yet another paper showing the utility of deleting massive amounts of data – in this case, looking at windows of the genome far enough apart that there is likely ample recombination between them. It was also useful in showing how one has to compromise. They used ASTRAL-III to infer a phylogenetic tree of all their samples incorporating processes like incomplete lineage sorting that might case gene tree - species tree mismatch. But they then used a much reduced number of taxa to analyze the history with zero to three possible reticulation events; given the massively larger search space when going from a tree to a network, they used a reduced set of samples. These were reasonable choices, but it shows the need for software that can feasibly look for reticulations for problems of hundreds of taxa or more.</p>
<p>The paper also used ABBA-BABA and related tests to scan along the genome to look for areas behaving unusually. Students have trouble understanding these at first (the ratio of the ‘wrong’ gene trees for sets of four lineages [ones that don’t match the species tree] having information about hybridization is a weird concept) but I think this paper explains it well, especially for an empirical paper not tasked with doing a review. It was also nice to see this being done as a genome scan as a discovery process. A lot of especially intro science is framed as rejection of dull hypotheses (“are these two different things not the same?”), but there’s still a lot of need for “let’s strap a camera on a sub and see what’s down there”, “let’s look at that galaxy in infrared”, “let’s see what <em>Tillandsia</em> are doing with their chromosomes”.</p>
<p>Side note I only briefly touched on in class: subgenus <em>Tillandsia</em> within <em>Tillandsia</em>?! “I study <em>Tillandsia</em> species,” even for someone using the same taxonomic concepts as oneself, is an ambiguous statement without including the rank. Yet another advantage of phylocode, where <em>Tillandsia</em> would have only one definition (and if one wanted to name smaller groups within it, one could without having to use subgenera, subsubgenera, superspecies, etc.). Unfortunately, <em>Tillandsia</em> as of today doesn’t seem to be <a href="https://www.phyloregnum.org/?term=Tillandsia">defined at all in phylocode</a> based on the online name repository; it might be in the <a href="https://www.routledge.com/Phylonyms-A-Companion-to-the-PhyloCode/deQueiroz-Cantino-Gauthier/p/book/9781138332935"><strong>Phylonyms</strong> companion volume</a> to the code itself, but I lack a copy (but it’s on sale for $240 hardcover, only $225 for the eBook, so…).</p>
<p>I made intro slides with some of my background material and some figures from the paper: <a href="YardeniEtAl2025_Networkss.pdf">PDF</a> and <a href="YardeniEtAl2025_Networks.pptx">PowerPoint</a>.</p>
<hr>
<p>To subscribe, go to <a href="https://brianomeara.info/blog.xml" class="uri">https://brianomeara.info/blog.xml</a> in an RSS reader.</p>



<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-citation"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Citation</h2><div><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">BibTeX citation:</div><pre class="sourceCode code-with-copy quarto-appendix-bibtex"><code class="sourceCode bibtex">@online{o'meara2025,
  author = {O’Meara, Brian},
  title = {PhyloPapers 2025, {Reticulate} Evolution},
  date = {2025-10-10},
  url = {https://brianomeara.info/posts/phylopapers_2025_Oct_10/},
  langid = {en}
}
</code></pre><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">For attribution, please cite this work as:</div><div id="ref-o'meara2025" class="csl-entry quarto-appendix-citeas">
O’Meara, Brian. 2025. <span>“PhyloPapers 2025, Reticulate
Evolution.”</span> October 10, 2025. <a href="https://brianomeara.info/posts/phylopapers_2025_Oct_10/">https://brianomeara.info/posts/phylopapers_2025_Oct_10/</a>.
</div></div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>phylopapers</category>
  <category>phylogenetics</category>
  <category>teaching</category>
  <category>reticulate</category>
  <category>networks</category>
  <guid>https://brianomeara.info/posts/phylopapers_2025_Oct_10/</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 10 Oct 2025 04:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>PhyloPapers 2025, Behavior and genomics</title>
  <dc:creator>Brian O&#39;Meara</dc:creator>
  <link>https://brianomeara.info/posts/phylopapers_2025_Oct_03/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>This week I wanted students to learn more about using genomics to understand behavior:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>Sara E. Lipshutz, Mark S. Hibbins, Alexandra B. Bentz, Aaron M. Buechlein, Tara A. Empson, Elizabeth M. George, Mark E. Hauber, Douglas B. Rusch, Wendy M. Schelsky, Quinn K. Thomas, Samuel J. Torneo, Abbigail M. Turner, Sarah E. Wolf, Mary J. Woodruff, Matthew W. Hahn &amp; Kimberly A. Rosvall. 2025. “Repeated behavioural evolution is associated with convergence of gene expression in cavity-nesting songbirds” Nature Ecology &amp; Evolution. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41559-025-02675-x" class="uri">https://doi.org/10.1038/s41559-025-02675-x</a></p>
</blockquote>
<p>[Note my conflict of interest: I was on Sara Lipshutz’ PhD committee]</p>
<p>One of the students in the class requested a modern paper on behavior. This paper had a lot of material for students to parse, but I think it’s good for them to see what a modern, chewy paper looks like. It has everything from careful natural history observations of birds attacking models to modern genomics to measures of hormones.</p>
<p>In all my classes I emphasize the difficulty of discretizing biology. Nature is full of variation. Even things that seem easiy countable, like number of limbs, have had variation over time and within species (quick, how many femurs do snakes have? <a href="https://www.cell.com/current-biology/fulltext/S0960-9822(16)31069-7">Two in pythons</a>). For this paper, a question was about aggression in cavity-nesting birds (birds nesting in holes in trees, for example) versus ones making open nests (the classic “use a crayon to draw a bird nest” nests). But even there, some birds only use cavity nests, some only use open nests, and some use both – how to categorize those? And does it matter if 99% of pairs in a species use a cavity or 3% of pairs use a cavity? Even continuous measures, like amount of aggression towards a model armed with a bluetooth speaker, require careful decisions. Is glaring at the model included in time spent in aggression? Flying around it yelling? Making full contact? This paper was useful in illustrating how these decisions are made.</p>
<p>The paper also had an interesting study design for a phylogenetics class. The authors chose non-overlapping pairs of species that differ in nesting habit. This is good, as it’s a lot like doing a twin study, but there still is differential relatedness between the pairs and so the authors used phylogenetic linear mixed models (PGLMMs – note, the “LLM” is not large language model) to control for relatedness. They also poked at the data in other ways to see if there could be confounding effects – for example, perhaps depth of the split between species in the pair had an effect on the results.</p>
<p>The genomic aspects I think were also informative. They looked for groups of genes that were expressed consistently differently between cavity and open nesters. There were a few found, but it felt appropriately preliminary: it wasn’t presented as “these are the genes that lead to aggression” but rather as candidates for potential further study. It was also an opportunity to teach students about how we understand putative gene function (from gene ontology databases).</p>
<p>I made intro slides with some of my background material and some figures from the paper: <a href="LipshutzEtAl_2025_BehaviorAndGenomics.pdf">PDF</a> and <a href="LipshutzEtAl_2025_BehaviorAndGenomics.pptx">PowerPoint</a>.</p>
<p>[Note that this blog post is dated for the class date, but I’m actually pushing it on Oct.&nbsp;11, 2025]</p>
<hr>
<p>To subscribe, go to <a href="https://brianomeara.info/blog.xml" class="uri">https://brianomeara.info/blog.xml</a> in an RSS reader.</p>



<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-citation"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Citation</h2><div><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">BibTeX citation:</div><pre class="sourceCode code-with-copy quarto-appendix-bibtex"><code class="sourceCode bibtex">@online{o'meara2025,
  author = {O’Meara, Brian},
  title = {PhyloPapers 2025, {Behavior} and Genomics},
  date = {2025-10-03},
  url = {https://brianomeara.info/posts/phylopapers_2025_Oct_03/},
  langid = {en}
}
</code></pre><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">For attribution, please cite this work as:</div><div id="ref-o'meara2025" class="csl-entry quarto-appendix-citeas">
O’Meara, Brian. 2025. <span>“PhyloPapers 2025, Behavior and
Genomics.”</span> October 3, 2025. <a href="https://brianomeara.info/posts/phylopapers_2025_Oct_03/">https://brianomeara.info/posts/phylopapers_2025_Oct_03/</a>.
</div></div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>phylopapers</category>
  <category>phylogenetics</category>
  <category>teaching</category>
  <category>genomics</category>
  <category>behavior</category>
  <guid>https://brianomeara.info/posts/phylopapers_2025_Oct_03/</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 03 Oct 2025 04:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>PhyloPapers 2025, Simulation</title>
  <dc:creator>Brian O&#39;Meara</dc:creator>
  <link>https://brianomeara.info/posts/phylopapers_2025_Sep_24/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>This week I wanted students to learn more about using simulations:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>Ornela N. Dehayem, Ryan F. A. Brewer, Luis Valente, Frederic Lens, Rampal S. Etienne. 2025. “Impact of sampling strategy on inference of community assembly processes in phylogenetic island biogeography”. Methods in Ecology and Evolution. 16:1507–1520. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1111/2041-210X.70058" class="uri">https://doi.org/10.1111/2041-210X.70058</a></p>
</blockquote>
<p>Simulation is used a lot to validate methods, but I like teaching it to students because it’s also important in power analyses. In my experience it is still rare for students to figure out if their proposed research will have enough species, data, etc. to potentially answer their question before embarking on it. It can save so much future heartache to spend a few days seeing whether, for example, if this trait leads to evolution of this other trait at a particular rate there’s any chance of being confident in a result from a likely 17-taxon tree.</p>
<p>However, simulation is hard to do well. For one thing, the space of parameters to examine can grow very quickly. One of the reasons I first learned R was because I had done a bunch of simulations (perl to test a C++ program) to test some methods I made for species delimitation (<a href="https://doi.org/10.1093/sysbio/syp077">O’Meara 2010</a>) but I hadn’t realized how hard it would be to plot something like 6 variables at once (so why not bar charts on top of bar charts in an <a href="https://pmc.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/articles/PMC5841455/figure/fig4/">array of bar charts</a>?). “Number of taxa might matter… and speciation rate… and the rate of trait evolution… and tree shape… and age… and…”. It can also be hard to figure out for a given parameter what values to try. Does this new method to estimate different substitution rates work well? On a three-taxon tree with mis-estimated branches, nope, it works horribly. On a 10,000-taxon tree where branch lengths are perfectly correlated with time, it works splendidly. But what will be relevant to biologists? That’s one of the reasons Jeremy Beaulieu and I (<a href="https://doi.org/10.1111/evo.12614">Beaulieu &amp; O’Meara 2015</a>) made sure to include units in a simulation so people could see whether they’re reasonable (even though one reviewer asked for us to delete units!). The ability to pre-determine the outcome of a simulation can also lead to odd choices depending on who is doing the simulating. For example, one paper in our field evaluated the performance of a Bayesian method written by many of the same authors by using simulation parameters that match the priors used in the later analysis. Unsurprisingly, it worked well when its prior was centered on the truth – with such a sim, it might work even better without any data! On the other hand, one could simulate using models that violate the assumptions of a method and then show that the method fails (“the normal distribution is a terrible way to get confidence interval for a mean… when data are simulated from a univariate uniform distribution”).</p>
<p>Dehayem et al.&nbsp;(2025) is interesting because it’s a paper testing a method created by many of the same authors, so presumably they’d be more accepting of results that show their method works, but it does a careful job. It is handling a complex scenario: arrival and diversification on islands, including hard to estimate parameters like extinction rate. There are some needed assumptions made in the simulation (for example, that this model describes the process so the parameter values are meaningful). It gets parameters from previously fit biological datasets, which is a good thing to do as it centers them on presumably realistic values. They also tried various ways to violate the model assumptions, such as a bias against sampling young species (there may be no gene flow, but humans haven’t recognized the populations as different species yet). There are many other potential things to vary, but it keeps it pretty focused and thus understandable. This made it an accessible jumping off point for discussions of simulations.</p>
<p>I made intro slides with some of my background material and some figures from the paper: <a href="DehayemEtAl_2025_Simulation.pdf">PDF</a> and <a href="DehayemEtAl_2025_Simulation.pptx">PowerPoint</a>.</p>
<p>[Note that this blog post is dated for the class date, but I’m actually pushing it on Oct.&nbsp;11, 2025]</p>
<hr>
<p>To subscribe, go to <a href="https://brianomeara.info/blog.xml" class="uri">https://brianomeara.info/blog.xml</a> in an RSS reader.</p>



<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-citation"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Citation</h2><div><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">BibTeX citation:</div><pre class="sourceCode code-with-copy quarto-appendix-bibtex"><code class="sourceCode bibtex">@online{o'meara2025,
  author = {O’Meara, Brian},
  title = {PhyloPapers 2025, {Simulation}},
  date = {2025-09-24},
  url = {https://brianomeara.info/posts/phylopapers_2025_Sep_24/},
  langid = {en}
}
</code></pre><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">For attribution, please cite this work as:</div><div id="ref-o'meara2025" class="csl-entry quarto-appendix-citeas">
O’Meara, Brian. 2025. <span>“PhyloPapers 2025, Simulation.”</span>
September 24, 2025. <a href="https://brianomeara.info/posts/phylopapers_2025_Sep_24/">https://brianomeara.info/posts/phylopapers_2025_Sep_24/</a>.
</div></div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>phylopapers</category>
  <category>phylogenetics</category>
  <category>teaching</category>
  <category>simulation</category>
  <guid>https://brianomeara.info/posts/phylopapers_2025_Sep_24/</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 24 Sep 2025 04:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>PhyloPapers 2025, Phylogeography</title>
  <dc:creator>Brian O&#39;Meara</dc:creator>
  <link>https://brianomeara.info/posts/phylopapers_2025_Sep_17/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>This week I wanted students to learn more about phylogeography:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>Manica Balant<sup>1</sup>, Daniel Vitales<sup>1</sup>, Zhiqiang Wang<sup>1</sup>, Zoltán Barina, Lin Fu, Tiangang Gao, Teresa Garnatje, Airy Gras, Muhammad Qasim Hayat, Marine Oganesian, Jaume Pellicer, Seyed A. Salami, Alexey P. Seregin, Nina Stepanyan-Gandilyan, Nusrat Sultana, Shagdar Tsooj, Magsar Urgamal, Joan Vallès, Robin van Velzen, Lisa Pokorny. 2025. “Integrating target capture with whole genome sequencing of recent and natural history collections to explain the phylogeography of wild-growing and cultivated <em>Cannabis</em>”. Plants People Planet. 1-18. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1002/ppp3.70043" class="uri">https://doi.org/10.1002/ppp3.70043</a> [<sup>1</sup> = equal contributions]</p>
</blockquote>
<p>This study examines wild and cultvated <em>Cannabis</em>, which is according to the paper has been used “as fibre (ropes, fabric and paper), medicinally (over 200 recorded uses), as food (nutrient-rich seeds) and in various magico-religious rituals”. It uses many samples from around the globe and genomic data to examine population structure.</p>
<p>One thing that has stood out in this paper and others considered for the course is the now apparent standard toolset of using <a href="https://mafft.cbrc.jp/alignment/software/">mafft</a>, <a href="https://web.stanford.edu/group/pritchardlab/structure.html">Structure</a>, <a href="https://github.com/smirarab/ASTRAL">ASTRAL-III</a>, and <a href="https://github.com/iqtree/iqtree2">IQ-TREE2</a>. The age of some of the software is unexpected: the latest release of Structure is from over 13 years ago, and for ASTRAL-III it’s over five years ago. That’s not necessarily a bad thing – it’s not like hackers are trying to take over the banking system by exploiting potential vulnerabilities in unpatched phylogenetic software – it’s just surprising. You would think that especially for popular analytical questions there would be new innovations or just <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=jn_P13FkQYw">new hotness</a>. For ASTRAL the developers “encourage using the new code” of <a href="https://github.com/chaoszhang/ASTER">ASTER</a>, though as this only was <a href="https://doi.org/10.1093/molbev/msaf172">published in a peer-reviewed journal</a> in July 2025 it’s reasonable that papers we’re reading now don’t use it yet (and I doubt answers under ASTRAL-III are wrong). But I do worry as researchers continue to use ChatGPT and similar for analyses and ask “<a href="https://scienceforeveryone.science/statistics-in-the-era-of-ai/">what’s the problem in doing stats with an (AI) consultant?</a>” popular approaches will be baked into the training data and then will be continually suggested as the options to use, even when <a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41586-020-2176-1">papers come out showing problems with classic approaches</a> (and see all the studies STILL looking at net diversification rate through time) or new approaches unlock new questions. There’s already a bias towards that built into the field – it’s more efficient to use approaches one already knows (and you might know the limitations well, too, which is important), and all the tutorials or posts are about the classic software, but at least new info is constantly being put into our human brains, where we could have a preference towards recent approaches (though on R-sig-phylo there was a counterargument that the agentic AIs will learn about new approaches and suggest them). Though I guess one advantage of fossilization of methods advice is we’ll all start using <a href="https://subulatepalpomere.com/2013/04/16/changing-of-the-guard/">MacClade</a> again.</p>
<p>One thing I loved about the paper was the use of herbarium and fresh specimens. It’s yet another example of the benefits of repositories of biological information (recognized at many, but not <a href="https://www.science.org/content/article/tragic-mistake-decision-close-duke-university-s-herbarium-triggers-furor">all</a>, places) as well as expertise to collect in the field. The paper also demonstrated the feasibility of genomic scale data.</p>
<p>A shift in thinking I’ve undergone but still feels unnatural is how in modern evolutionary biology a key workflow step is <strong>massively deleting</strong> data. It wasn’t that long ago we were looking at chromatograms in Sequencher to identify every possible base by eye (while still excluding bad reads); in contrast, in this paper the data were filtered from 68,212 single nucleotide polymorphisms (SNPS) down to just 2,875. This is important to do for data from GBIF (“nope, that oak is not from the ocean, someone flipped a sign”) and things like the TRY database of plant traits, too. This paper was useful for discussing this shift with students.</p>
<p>A conclusion from the paper was that <em>Cannibis sativa</em> is one species (as hypothesized by Linnaeus) and not two with the addition of <em>C. indica</em>. Perhaps a useful anecdote for intro bio when the standard move is to dunk on “Lamarckism” (though this requires more nuance than the cartoon version): the describer of the incorrectly split <em>C. indica</em>: Jean-Baptiste Lamarck. Though one student raised a good point: it would be interesting to redo the Structure analyses using only the wild plants, not escaped or domesticated cultivars – one possibility is that human meddling allowed interbreeding of <em>C. sativa</em> and <em>C. indica</em> that would have been relatively reproductively isolated otherwise.</p>
<p>One note for those who might want to teach the paper: I made sure to let students know that some uses of the plant are illegal in this jurisdiction (true at both our state and federal level) before asking them to provide information (for discussion questions on the paper before class, for example). I don’t want students trying to, say, make a joke, put in writing something that could be read by others as disclosure of illegal drug use – who knows how such info could be scraped into systems and misinterpreted in the future.</p>
<p>I made intro slides with some of my background material and some figures from the paper: <a href="BalantVitalesWangEtAl_Phylogeography.pdf">PDF</a> and <a href="BalantVitalesWangEtAl_Phylogeography.pptx">PowerPoint</a>.</p>
<p>[Note that this blog post is dated for the class date, but I’m actually pushing it on Oct.&nbsp;11, 2025]</p>
<hr>
<p>To subscribe, go to <a href="https://brianomeara.info/blog.xml" class="uri">https://brianomeara.info/blog.xml</a> in an RSS reader.</p>



<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-citation"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Citation</h2><div><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">BibTeX citation:</div><pre class="sourceCode code-with-copy quarto-appendix-bibtex"><code class="sourceCode bibtex">@online{o'meara2025,
  author = {O’Meara, Brian},
  title = {PhyloPapers 2025, {Phylogeography}},
  date = {2025-09-17},
  url = {https://brianomeara.info/posts/phylopapers_2025_Sep_17/},
  langid = {en}
}
</code></pre><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">For attribution, please cite this work as:</div><div id="ref-o'meara2025" class="csl-entry quarto-appendix-citeas">
O’Meara, Brian. 2025. <span>“PhyloPapers 2025, Phylogeography.”</span>
September 17, 2025. <a href="https://brianomeara.info/posts/phylopapers_2025_Sep_17/">https://brianomeara.info/posts/phylopapers_2025_Sep_17/</a>.
</div></div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>phylopapers</category>
  <category>phylogenetics</category>
  <category>teaching</category>
  <category>phylogeography</category>
  <guid>https://brianomeara.info/posts/phylopapers_2025_Sep_17/</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 17 Sep 2025 04:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>PhyloPapers 2025, Genomic species delimitation</title>
  <dc:creator>Brian O&#39;Meara</dc:creator>
  <link>https://brianomeara.info/posts/phylopapers_2025_Sep_12/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>This week I wanted students to learn more about modern approaches for species delimitation:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>Sonal Singhal, Adam D. Leaché, Matthew K. Fujita, Carlos Daniel Cadena, and Felipe Zapata. 2025. “A Genomic Perspective on Species Delimitation” Annu. Rev.&nbsp;Ecol. Evol. Syst. 2025. 56:467–89 <a href="https://doi.org/10.1146/annurev-ecolsys-102723-055311" class="uri">https://doi.org/10.1146/annurev-ecolsys-102723-055311</a></p>
</blockquote>
<p>In contrast to the other papers so far in the class, this is a review paper rather than original research (though, like many modern review papers, it actually does a fair amount of new bibliometric analysis). I’m not going to have us read a lot of review papers, but this one touched on various topics that came up in previous discussions (like the multispecies coalescent) and was a bit of a breather for students in that it had less jargon. They loved it and found it understandable. I think it was a very thorough and fair overview of the subject.</p>
<p>The two biggest questions students had were about the machine learning mentions and the <em>gdi</em> metric (<a href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/28003535/">Jackson et al.&nbsp;2017</a>). People now often think of AI as large language models like ChatGPT, but it covers a wide variety of approaches: image recognition, like that used by iNaturalist; approaches to impute missing data; methods to infer relationships from large sets of data; etc. One could imagine hoping for a genomic equivalent for the long wished-for “barcoding gap” (a discrete difference between intra- and interspecific differences), for example. The <em>gdi</em> is a measure we came up with to compare differences between potential species: it is scaled from 0 for panmixia to 1 for strong divergence. (I actually fought my coauthors, because I didn’t really like the <em>gdi</em>, but my collaborators won out and they were right). I think part of the confusion from the Singhal et al.&nbsp;paper is that the <em>gdi</em> in their Fig 2 is shown as a property of a population, when it’s actually a measure used between two populations.</p>
<p>One thing that both I and the attendees liked was the discussion at the end of the paper about not making genomic approaches a requirement for species delimitation publications. Genomics brings a lot of possibilities (such as looking for genomic regions correlated with lack of gene flow), and it may even be cheaper than older sorts of data which have less information. But genomic data are still not feasible for all researchers or locations. Especially given the need to do basic species discovery in so many groups, using available data to understand biodiversity is more critical than waiting until one can do multiple full genomes.</p>
<p>An interesting data point from the bibliometric analysis was that only in 36% of cases did discoveries about a need to change taxonomy lead to a taxonomic change in the papers. This is in line with my anecdotal experience. There are good reasons for this (a taxonomic change is a big deal and requires expertise – one doesn’t want to rush into it) but it is a bit odd that methods intended to discover new species or collapse oversplit ones usually don’t lead to this in a usable way.</p>
<p>Overall, I expect this paper to become widely used in teaching and for people getting into the field.</p>
<p>I made intro slides with some of my background material and some figures from the paper: <a href="SinghalEtAl2025_GenomicSpeciesDelimitation.pdf">PDF</a> and <a href="SinghalEtAl2025_GenomicSpeciesDelimitation.pptx">PowerPoint</a>.</p>
<hr>
<p>To subscribe, go to <a href="https://brianomeara.info/blog.xml" class="uri">https://brianomeara.info/blog.xml</a> in an RSS reader.</p>



<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-citation"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Citation</h2><div><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">BibTeX citation:</div><pre class="sourceCode code-with-copy quarto-appendix-bibtex"><code class="sourceCode bibtex">@online{o'meara2025,
  author = {O’Meara, Brian},
  title = {PhyloPapers 2025, {Genomic} Species Delimitation},
  date = {2025-09-12},
  url = {https://brianomeara.info/posts/phylopapers_2025_Sep_12/},
  langid = {en}
}
</code></pre><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">For attribution, please cite this work as:</div><div id="ref-o'meara2025" class="csl-entry quarto-appendix-citeas">
O’Meara, Brian. 2025. <span>“PhyloPapers 2025, Genomic Species
Delimitation.”</span> September 12, 2025. <a href="https://brianomeara.info/posts/phylopapers_2025_Sep_12/">https://brianomeara.info/posts/phylopapers_2025_Sep_12/</a>.
</div></div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>phylopapers</category>
  <category>phylogenetics</category>
  <category>teaching</category>
  <category>delimitation</category>
  <category>genomics</category>
  <guid>https://brianomeara.info/posts/phylopapers_2025_Sep_12/</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 12 Sep 2025 04:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>PhyloPapers 2025, Growth of the tree of life</title>
  <dc:creator>Brian O&#39;Meara</dc:creator>
  <link>https://brianomeara.info/posts/phylopapers_2025_Sep_05/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>This week I wanted students to learn more about the growth of our knowledge of the tree of life. We’re reading:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>Molly Chen, Artem I. Kholodov and Laura A. Hug (2025). The evolution of the tree of life. Phil. Trans. R. Soc. B 380: 20240091. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1098/rstb.2024.0091" class="uri">https://doi.org/10.1098/rstb.2024.0091</a></p>
</blockquote>
<p>This is a really cool paper: it took snapshots of the info in GenBank at five year intervals, built trees from the available info at each time step, and compared how the trees changed over time. It also looked at trees from key papers over time. I also liked it for class as it touched on long branch attraction and tree distances, which are useful background for students to know. The paper also generated discussion of tree construction, including use of backbone trees, as well as the need for taxonomic name resolution and massive deletion of sequences (for example, going from 2.2 million genomes down to 333K after filtering). I still remember the days of <a href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/portal/utils/pageresolver.fcgi?recordid=68bce924dbd3fe45a71f670a">fighting hard for every base pair</a>, so the shift in the genomic era to tossing most info is still viscerally painful, but useful.</p>
<p>This is also a paper where the supplement has some genuinely useful info: it’s available at <a href="https://doi.org/10.6084/m9.figshare.c.7897347.v1" class="uri">https://doi.org/10.6084/m9.figshare.c.7897347.v1</a>.</p>
<p>One thing that became apparent is how many of us, myself included, have nearly all our natural history and taxonomic knowledge focused on eukaryotes. Even issues like the possible lack of monophyly of Archaea were revelations to many: the three domain view of life is often still taught as the default. I plan to read more widely to understand the diversity of life better (my secret hope is that at some point <a href="https://rileyblack.net">Riley Black</a> will write a book on single-celled life as engaging as her other ones…).</p>
<p>I made intro slides with some of my background material and some figures from the paper: <a href="ChenEtAl2025_EvolutionOfTheTreeOfLife.pdf">PDF</a> and <a href="ChenEtAl2025_EvolutionOfTheTreeOfLife.pptx">PowerPoint</a>.</p>
<hr>
<p>To subscribe, go to <a href="https://brianomeara.info/blog.xml" class="uri">https://brianomeara.info/blog.xml</a> in an RSS reader.</p>



<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-citation"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Citation</h2><div><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">BibTeX citation:</div><pre class="sourceCode code-with-copy quarto-appendix-bibtex"><code class="sourceCode bibtex">@online{o'meara2025,
  author = {O’Meara, Brian},
  title = {PhyloPapers 2025, {Growth} of the Tree of Life},
  date = {2025-09-06},
  url = {https://brianomeara.info/posts/phylopapers_2025_Sep_05/},
  langid = {en}
}
</code></pre><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">For attribution, please cite this work as:</div><div id="ref-o'meara2025" class="csl-entry quarto-appendix-citeas">
O’Meara, Brian. 2025. <span>“PhyloPapers 2025, Growth of the Tree of
Life.”</span> September 6, 2025. <a href="https://brianomeara.info/posts/phylopapers_2025_Sep_05/">https://brianomeara.info/posts/phylopapers_2025_Sep_05/</a>.
</div></div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>phylopapers</category>
  <category>phylogenetics</category>
  <category>teaching</category>
  <guid>https://brianomeara.info/posts/phylopapers_2025_Sep_05/</guid>
  <pubDate>Sat, 06 Sep 2025 04:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>GRFP 2025</title>
  <dc:creator>Brian O&#39;Meara</dc:creator>
  <link>https://brianomeara.info/posts/grfp_2025/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<section id="update-sept-9-2025" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="update-sept-9-2025">Update (Sept 9, 2025):</h3>
<p>GRFP is LIVE!!! <a href="https://www.nsf.gov/funding/opportunities/grfp-nsf-graduate-research-fellowship-program" class="uri">https://www.nsf.gov/funding/opportunities/grfp-nsf-graduate-research-fellowship-program</a></p>
<p>Deadline is Oct.&nbsp;27, 2025, for life sciences (which suggests they plan to fund life sciences), and shortly after that for other fields. There still isn’t a full solicitation (the detailed guidelines of what they want in a proposal), and they oddly do not link to the <a href="https://www.nsf.gov/funding/opportunities/grfp-nsf-graduate-research-fellowship-program/nsf24-591/solicitation">old solicitation</a>. This could mean they’re changing something (page count, what they ask, etc.) but it’s hard to know. This is also fewer days than I had been expecting given the <a href="https://www.nsf.gov/funding/overview#phase-1-proposal-preparation-and-submission-f9f">policy</a> of 90 days from them announcing an opportunity to applying, but maybe they’re considering that the fact that this is a renewal of a program as meaning they don’t have to meet the window (and really, who would rather them have a deadline go much later so grad students and programs don’t know about GRFP funding until very late in the cycle?).</p>
<p>Another interesting part of the webpage is that the estimated number of awards is:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>1 to 3000 - NSF will support up to 3000 new Graduate Research Fellowships per fiscal year under this program solicitation pending availability of funds.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>That is different from last year’s language of</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>Estimated Number of Awards: 2,300</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>NSF will support up to 2,300 new Graduate Research Fellowships per fiscal year under this program solicitation pending availability of funds.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>They’re giving a 1-3,000 range rather than what typically is the expected number of awards. My guess is they’re still hoping to get a large number of awards. Given the <a href="https://www.aip.org/fyi/nsf-seeks-model-for-graduate-fellowships-co-funded-by-government-and-industry">potential external funders</a>, maybe NSF is leaving room for them to fund the typical awardees <em>plus</em> honorable mention students. Though it also opens the possibility that in March NSF will announce “congrats to the NSF GRFP awardees: Martha. Just Martha.”</p>
<p>Regarding availability of funding, there is currently uncertainty about a potential government shutdown at the end of September (as well as uncertainty about next year’s NSF funding in general). During a shutdown, NSF staff will not be able to respond to any questions; with some shutdowns, government websites go dark (in the past <a href="https://www.science.org/content/article/latest-shutdown-information-nih-and-nsf-funded-researchers-update">I’ve archived ones</a>), and deadlines <em>might</em> be pushed back (but do not count on it). Potential applicants should thus stay on top of this news and prepare.</p>
</section>
<section id="original-post-sept-4-2025" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="original-post-sept-4-2025">Original post (Sept 4, 2025):</h3>
<p>The <a href="https://www.nsf.gov/funding/opportunities/grfp-nsf-graduate-research-fellowship-program">US National Science Foundation Graduate Research Fellowship Program (GRFP)</a> has long been a way of supporting students going into grad school. In the US, students going to grad school in the sciences are often paid, and have tuition covered, for teaching or doing research (more common in PhD programs than Masters programs, and support can vary). The NSF GRFP pays students (typically more than university stipends) to do their work, without needing to use their time for other research or teaching (both can be valuable, but time is limited). It is an investment by the government in a student’s career; unusually for NSF, it’s an investment in the person rather than the project.</p>
<p>Historically, deadlines were in mid-October, but so far this year the <a href="https://www.nsf.gov/funding/opportunities/grfp-nsf-graduate-research-fellowship-program/nsf24-591/solicitation">old solicitation</a> has not been updated and so the program isn’t taking proposals yet. A big question for students is whether it will run at all.</p>
<p>There’s some good news. An August 28, 2025, <a href="https://www.aip.org/fyi/nsf-seeks-model-for-graduate-fellowships-co-funded-by-government-and-industry">article</a> on the American Institute of Physics site focused mostly on a new model on having fellowships co-funded by government and industry, but it had some details on the traditional GRFP, too:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>“An NSF spokesperson said GRFP will continue this year and that the solicitation is currently in development. They did not comment on whether the fellowship model that emerges from the UIDP workshop might replace GRFP.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>“Most years, the solicitation goes out in July, allowing applicants 90 days to submit before the deadline in mid-October, former GRFP program directors Susan Brennan and Gisèle Muller-Parker said. They added that NSF may push back the application deadline to November or December, but that doing so would make it hard for the agency to finalize its decisions by its usual April deadline.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>“The delay may be a result of current federal funding proposals for NSF. The president’s budget request proposes a 55% cut to GRFP for fiscal year 2026, while the Senate Appropriations Committee’s bill proposes flat funding, which would support 2,000 new fellowships, according to the bill report. The Senate and House are scheduled to return from their August recess next week and have until Sept.&nbsp;30 to pass their funding bills.”</p>
</blockquote>
<p>As of this morning (Sept.&nbsp;4, 2025) there hasn’t been a new solicitation. NSF has a <a href="https://www.nsf.gov/funding/overview#phase-1-proposal-preparation-and-submission-f9f">policy</a> that “Applicants have a minimum of 90 days from NSF’s announcement of a funding opportunity to prepare and submit a proposal.” Policies have been more fluid lately, but assuming that policy still holds, then the earliest possible deadline is Dec.&nbsp;3, 2025. It’s still probably a good idea to prepare earlier, but at least there’s a chance the call will still go out (but it’s still uncertain how many awards will be possible given funding changes).</p>
<p>There also used to be a dedicated website for GRFP info: <a href="https://www.nsfgrfp.org/" class="uri">https://www.nsfgrfp.org/</a>, which now resolves to the NSF page for the upcoming solicitation. The Internet Archive has an <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20250120221242/https://www.nsfgrfp.org/">older version of the website</a> which has some good information.</p>
<p>(I posted much of the above on BlueSky last week, but discoverability isn’t great there, so I made this blog post).</p>
<p>Under recent solicitations, people could apply to the GRFP twice: once as undergrads, and once (typically in their second year) in grad school. Since the people in the first set might also be applying to grad school, the <a href="https://applyingtoeeb.info" class="uri">https://applyingtoeeb.info</a> page I made may have some helpful info, too.</p>
<hr>
<p>To subscribe, go to <a href="https://brianomeara.info/blog.xml" class="uri">https://brianomeara.info/blog.xml</a> in an RSS reader.</p>


</section>

<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-citation"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Citation</h2><div><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">BibTeX citation:</div><pre class="sourceCode code-with-copy quarto-appendix-bibtex"><code class="sourceCode bibtex">@online{o'meara2025,
  author = {O’Meara, Brian},
  title = {GRFP 2025},
  date = {2025-09-04},
  url = {https://brianomeara.info/posts/grfp_2025/},
  langid = {en}
}
</code></pre><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">For attribution, please cite this work as:</div><div id="ref-o'meara2025" class="csl-entry quarto-appendix-citeas">
O’Meara, Brian. 2025. <span>“GRFP 2025.”</span> September 4, 2025. <a href="https://brianomeara.info/posts/grfp_2025/">https://brianomeara.info/posts/grfp_2025/</a>.
</div></div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>funding</category>
  <category>GRFP</category>
  <category>NSF</category>
  <guid>https://brianomeara.info/posts/grfp_2025/</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 04 Sep 2025 04:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>PhyloPapers 2025, Bayesian analysis</title>
  <dc:creator>Brian O&#39;Meara</dc:creator>
  <link>https://brianomeara.info/posts/phylopapers_2025_Aug_29/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>This week I wanted students to learn more about the background for tree inference. We’re reading</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>Laura P. A. Mulvey, Mark C. Nikolic, Bethany J. Allen, Tracy A. Heath and Rachel C. M. Warnock (2025). From fossils to phylogenies: exploring the integration of paleontological data into Bayesian phylogenetic inference. <em>Paleobiology</em> 51, 214–236. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1017/pab.2024.47" class="uri">https://doi.org/10.1017/pab.2024.47</a></p>
</blockquote>
<p>It has good background on Bayesian approaches. It also brings in fossil data, which may appeal to some of the paleontologists in the class. The paper is very much in favor of Fossilized Birth Death (FBD) models, and is honest about this: “Through this review, we hope to celebrate the FBD model family, inform readers of its nuances and potential uses, and stimulate discussion around best practices for answering empirical questions.”</p>
<p>I agree these models are useful, but there can be caveats. Jeremy Beaulieu and I incorporated FBD models with likelihood in <a href="https://speciationextinction.info/articles/adding_fossils.html">hisse</a>, and tested the effect of less than perfect sampling of fossils:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>Jeremy M Beaulieu and Brian C O’Meara (2022) Fossils do not substantially improve, and may even harm, estimates of diversification rate heterogeneity. <em>Systematic Biology</em> 72(1), 50-61. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1093/sysbio/syac049" class="uri">https://doi.org/10.1093/sysbio/syac049</a></p>
</blockquote>
<p>I’m not having the students read our paper (we’re still doing intro about tree building; I think doing both would be too much nuance at this stage), but others curious about FBD models might be interested and may overlook it (Mulvey et al.&nbsp;(2025) don’t cite or mention it in their review, for example). The implementation is too slow for tree inference, but it can be used for estimating various diversification and fossil rates under a likelihood approach, so not requiring (or benefitting) from priors.</p>
<p>For teaching, I really like how the Mulvey et al.&nbsp;(2025) paper gets into the various uses of the FBD model: to help with inferring the tree, dating, estimating parameters, etc. A lot of students think of models as tests, fit for one purpose, but models are general ways of representing the world and can be put to many uses. For example, Brownian motion models of continuous traits can be used for estimating ancestral states, but they can also help infer trees or for estimating rates of evolution, too: they’re just a representation of how traits change over time under various assumptions. The same for FBD.</p>
<p>I made intro slides with some of my background material and some figures from the paper: <a href="MulveyEtAl2025_Bayesian_FBD.pdf">PDF</a> and <a href="MulveyEtAl2025_Bayesian_FBD.pptx">PowerPoint</a></p>
<p>One thing I’m going to do this week is talk less – last time the mini-lecture went on too long, but I want more student interaction.</p>
<hr>
<p>To subscribe, go to <a href="https://brianomeara.info/blog.xml" class="uri">https://brianomeara.info/blog.xml</a> in an RSS reader.</p>



<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-citation"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Citation</h2><div><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">BibTeX citation:</div><pre class="sourceCode code-with-copy quarto-appendix-bibtex"><code class="sourceCode bibtex">@online{o'meara2025,
  author = {O’Meara, Brian},
  title = {PhyloPapers 2025, {Bayesian} Analysis},
  date = {2025-08-29},
  url = {https://brianomeara.info/posts/phylopapers_2025_Aug_29/},
  langid = {en}
}
</code></pre><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">For attribution, please cite this work as:</div><div id="ref-o'meara2025" class="csl-entry quarto-appendix-citeas">
O’Meara, Brian. 2025. <span>“PhyloPapers 2025, Bayesian
Analysis.”</span> August 29, 2025. <a href="https://brianomeara.info/posts/phylopapers_2025_Aug_29/">https://brianomeara.info/posts/phylopapers_2025_Aug_29/</a>.
</div></div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>phylopapers</category>
  <category>phylogenetics</category>
  <category>teaching</category>
  <category>FBD</category>
  <category>Bayesian</category>
  <guid>https://brianomeara.info/posts/phylopapers_2025_Aug_29/</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 29 Aug 2025 04:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>PhyloPapers 2025, first class</title>
  <dc:creator>Brian O&#39;Meara</dc:creator>
  <link>https://brianomeara.info/posts/phylopapers_2025_Aug_22/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>I’m teaching a new class this semester. It is a graduate-level seminar reading recent phylogenetic papers, but also with a bit of instruction at the beginnng of each class as a gentle way of onboarding people into phylogenetic methods and evolutionary thinking. My hope is that it will be good for people just learning in this area while still getting deep for those already in the field. So far it has 13 students enrolled and 9 people auditing (generally fellow faculty). Before each class, enrollees are asked:</p>
<ol type="1">
<li>What was the discovery or innovation in this paper?</li>
<li>How this was supported?</li>
<li>What didn’t you understand about the paper, the methods, the questions, and/or the organisms?</li>
</ol>
<p>My goal is to make it a positive learning experience – sometimes classes focusing on papers can devolve into “paper shredding” sessions where everyone takes pot shots at it. This can be a cheap way to perform competence at one another, but it’s not fair to the paper’s authors and also can lead to cynicism about the possibility of learning. Nearly all papers have a mixture of good and bad features, often due to very real constraints we all face, but they also do contribute insights about the world.</p>
<p>For the first week I wanted to show student a recent paper where making the phylogeny helped with understanding the biology. The focus is to have students learn a bit about why and how we make phylogenies and then build in deeper. I chose</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>Alison R. Irwin, Nicholas W. Roberts, Ellen E. Strong, Yasunori Kano, Daniel I. Speiser, Elizabeth M. Harper, and Suzanne T. Williams. 2025 “Evolution of Large Eyes in Stromboidea (Gastropoda): Impact of Photic Environment and Life History Traits” Systematic Biology 74(2):301–322. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1093/sysbio/syae063" class="uri">https://doi.org/10.1093/sysbio/syae063</a></p>
</blockquote>
<p>as it uses a few different phylogenetic approaches in an appealing study system.</p>
<p>I made intro slides with some of my background material and some figures from the paper: <a href="IrwinEtAl2025_BuildingPhylogenies.pdf">PDF</a> and <a href="IrwinEtAl2025_BuildingPhylogenies.pptx">PowerPoint</a></p>
<p>Some of the material used:</p>
<ul>
<li>The paper: <a href="https://doi.org/10.1093/sysbio/syae063" class="uri">https://doi.org/10.1093/sysbio/syae063</a></li>
<li>Sequences: <a href="https://doi.org/doi:10.5061/dryad.pnvx0k6v0" class="uri">https://doi.org/doi:10.5061/dryad.pnvx0k6v0</a></li>
<li>Other background info: <a href="https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.13768189" class="uri">https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.13768189</a> (though I had to use <a href="https://zenodo.org/records/8260767">version 1</a> as the more recent one is under embargo)</li>
<li><a href="https://www.mesquiteproject.org">Mesquite</a> for visualizing the sequences</li>
</ul>
<p>Note I wasn’t involved in the Irwin et al.&nbsp;(2025) paper at all (not as a reviewer, AE, etc.), so I don’t have any insights into its development.</p>
<hr>
<p>To subscribe, go to <a href="https://brianomeara.info/blog.xml" class="uri">https://brianomeara.info/blog.xml</a> in an RSS reader.</p>



<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-citation"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Citation</h2><div><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">BibTeX citation:</div><pre class="sourceCode code-with-copy quarto-appendix-bibtex"><code class="sourceCode bibtex">@online{o'meara2025,
  author = {O’Meara, Brian},
  title = {PhyloPapers 2025, First Class},
  date = {2025-08-22},
  url = {https://brianomeara.info/posts/phylopapers_2025_Aug_22/},
  langid = {en}
}
</code></pre><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">For attribution, please cite this work as:</div><div id="ref-o'meara2025" class="csl-entry quarto-appendix-citeas">
O’Meara, Brian. 2025. <span>“PhyloPapers 2025, First Class.”</span>
August 22, 2025. <a href="https://brianomeara.info/posts/phylopapers_2025_Aug_22/">https://brianomeara.info/posts/phylopapers_2025_Aug_22/</a>.
</div></div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>phylopapers</category>
  <category>phylogenetics</category>
  <category>teaching</category>
  <guid>https://brianomeara.info/posts/phylopapers_2025_Aug_22/</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 22 Aug 2025 04:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Watching memory in targets in R</title>
  <dc:creator>Brian O&#39;Meara</dc:creator>
  <link>https://brianomeara.info/posts/targetsmemory/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>I loved drake for R workflows, and I love using its successor, <a href="https://books.ropensci.org/targets/">targets</a> – great thanks to author Will Landau, his funder, Eli Lilly &amp; Company, and its host, rOpenSci. The basic workflow it creates is simple and reproducible:</p>
<ul>
<li>A file of functions.</li>
<li>A list of targets that use your functions and other functions to create a series of steps</li>
</ul>
<p>It’s much more logical than the mixture of functions and workflow you see in a lot of beginning R user scripts. It also saves time: if you have a three step process, A -&gt; B -&gt; C, you can run it through once, decide step B needs to be tweaked, change the function for that step, and it will know to run only steps B and C again, keeping A unchanged. This is great for doing simulation analyses: “oh, let’s add more conditions to understand the behavior between t=5 and t=50, as that is where things seem to change” – only the new values will be run. I use targets for everything from <a href="https://github.com/bomeara/hyperbolic_rates/blob/main/hyperanalysis/_targets.R">analyses and creating figures for papers</a> to creating a <a href="https://collegetables.info">multi-thousand page website</a> for helping my kids compare colleges (as one does).</p>
<p>It has <a href="https://books.ropensci.org/targets/crew.html">great abilities</a> for working on clusters and other high performance computing structures. We ran into an issue, though, with running on a colleague’s beefy multicore computer (which isn’t running queueing software, but it’s one with a large amount of RAM and over a hundred cores). We used <a href="https://wlandau.github.io/crew/">crew</a> with targets to handle batching out jobs to the cores. The issue is that while this could make sure there were cores available, it was not tracking memory use. The jobs we were sending out involved doing analyses on simulated trees: these could be just a handful of species or many thousands, and so the jobs were wildly different in terms of memory usage. If we figured out the average memory usage for a job and set to not hit the cap on average, there was still a chance of using up too much memory, especially as smaller jobs finished earlier so the population of running jobs becomes more enriched for slow, high memory jobs later in the run. On the other hand, if we conservatively set the number of cores used to a low number, we’re taking longer to run things than we need to as we’re nowhere near the memory or core limit. Perhaps with a more sophisticated batching system memory use would be incorporated, but it’s an odd kind of job for this because memory need varies a lot based on the input object.</p>
<p>So, a kludge I made:</p>
<p>To do parallel, we use crew:</p>
<pre><code>tar_option_set(
        packages = c( "tidyverse",  "tarchetypes", "ggplot2", "RColorBrewer", "ggrepel", "ggtext",  "pdftools", "readr", "parallel", "phytools", "TreeSim", "viridis", "RPANDA", "epm", "parallel", "ggbeeswarm", "JuliaCall", "memuse"),
        controller= crew_controller_local(workers = 80, seconds_timeout = 600, garbage_collection = TRUE)
)</code></pre>
<p>Our relevant slow target is:</p>
<pre><code>    tar_target(
        inference_results,
        command = DoInference(many_trees),
        pattern = map(many_trees),
        iteration = "list"
    )</code></pre>
<p>Where we have simulated trees from previous simulation steps in the list <code>many_trees</code>.</p>
<p>In the <code>DoInference()</code> function, I set a threshold of 10 GB for desired amount of free RAM on the cluster (<code>free_GBram_threshold</code>) then used this code before the actual analysis starts:</p>
<pre><code>    Sys.sleep(runif(1, 0, ntax)) # sleep for a random amount of time to avoid all processes starting at the same time, have bigger trees start later
    freeGBram &lt;- .Call(memuse:::R_meminfo_raminfo)$freeram / 1e9
    while(freeGBram &lt; max(free_GBram_threshold, sqrt(ntax))) {
        Sys.sleep(10)
        freeGBram &lt;- .Call(memuse:::R_meminfo_raminfo)$freeram / 1e9
    }</code></pre>
<p><code>ntax</code> is the number of species on a tree, roughly proportional to how big a job it will be to run.</p>
<p>This uses the <code>memuse</code> package to see how much RAM is available on the system, and then does a loop to wait until there is enough free before starting the expensive part of the analysis. If there is enough RAM, everything runs happily, with a slight bias for starting easier jobs sooner. As RAM fills up, the same number of jobs are technically running, but some are just doing repeated sleep cycles until there’s memory capacity. This isn’t ideal – there could be low-memory jobs that would fit easily, but the big jobs are just occupying a core running <code>Sys.sleep()</code> forever – but for our setup, where there was one user on the computer trying to juggle memory, it worked ok.</p>
<hr>
<p>To subscribe, go to <a href="https://brianomeara.info/blog.xml" class="uri">https://brianomeara.info/blog.xml</a> in an RSS reader.</p>



<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-citation"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Citation</h2><div><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">BibTeX citation:</div><pre class="sourceCode code-with-copy quarto-appendix-bibtex"><code class="sourceCode bibtex">@online{o'meara2025,
  author = {O’Meara, Brian},
  title = {Watching Memory in Targets in {R}},
  date = {2025-07-25},
  url = {https://brianomeara.info/posts/targetsmemory/},
  langid = {en}
}
</code></pre><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">For attribution, please cite this work as:</div><div id="ref-o'meara2025" class="csl-entry quarto-appendix-citeas">
O’Meara, Brian. 2025. <span>“Watching Memory in Targets in R.”</span>
July 25, 2025. <a href="https://brianomeara.info/posts/targetsmemory/">https://brianomeara.info/posts/targetsmemory/</a>.
</div></div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>Rstats</category>
  <category>targets</category>
  <guid>https://brianomeara.info/posts/targetsmemory/</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 25 Jul 2025 04:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Course ads on R-sig-phylo</title>
  <dc:creator>Brian O&#39;Meara</dc:creator>
  <link>https://brianomeara.info/posts/rsig/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>The R project maintains <a href="https://www.r-project.org/mail.html">special interest mailing lists</a>: using R in ecology, using R in phylogenetics, etc.:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>Additionally, there are several specific Special Interest Group (=: SIG) mailing lists; however do post to only one list at time (‘SIG’ or general one), cross-posting is considered to be impolite.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>The phylogenetics one has been a good place for discussion and learning; I even quote posts from it at length in the <a href="https://thej022214.github.io/OUwie/reference/OUwie.anc.html#details-1">help for ancestral state reconstruction</a> using Ornstein-Uhlenbeck models in the OUwie documentation, as Joe Felsenstein, Dave Bapst, Simone Blomberg, Marguerite Butler, Nick Matzke, and Thomas Hansen all weighed in (I wrote the function so that by default it gives an error until a user indicates they actually read the documentation about the risks of this analysis).</p>
<p>However, lately the list is filled with posts for courses in R. It might not be unreasonable: a workshop in R for phylogenetics, like the <a href="https://eqgw.github.io/index.html">evolutionary quantitative genetics workshop</a> led by community members Josef Uyeda and Fabio Machado, could be appropriately sent to the list. But now the list nearly <em>all</em> ads for courses, most of which do not relate to phylogenetics. Out of the last 50 <a href="https://www.mail-archive.com/r-sig-phylo@r-project.org/index.html">threads</a> on the list (Feb 2025-July 2025):</p>
<ul>
<li>22 were by Carlo Pecoraro of Physalia Courses</li>
<li>9 were by Oliver Hooker of PR Statistics</li>
<li>8 were by Soledad De Esteban-Trivigno of Transmitting Science</li>
</ul>
<p>Nearly all of these were for paid courses offered by these groups.</p>
<p>There were also two (2!) threads with actual questions on R in phylogenetics (only one of which had answers), a request to nominate scientists for a medal, and two posts from the long-serving volunteer list moderator, Hilmar Lapp, about proper conduct, including <a href="https://www.mail-archive.com/r-sig-phylo@r-project.org/msg06067.html">one about too many training course advertisements</a>. Hilmar’s request was that groups post no more than two courses a month and only post each course once (no “last chance of” or similar follow-ups). All the companies above violated this (links to examples): <a href="https://www.mail-archive.com/r-sig-phylo@r-project.org/msg06092.html">Physalia</a> (which also posts over 3.5 courses per month), <a href="https://www.mail-archive.com/r-sig-phylo@r-project.org/msg06082.html">PR Statistics</a>, and <a href="https://www.mail-archive.com/r-sig-phylo@r-project.org/msg06106.html">Transmitting Science</a>.</p>
<p>An easy criticism would be to argue for different moderation choices or actions, but any such move puts even more work on a long-serving community member. Why should someone volunteer their time to play whack-a-mole with multiple people who are paid to send out announcements as part of their day job? It’s not sustainable. It would be better if companies decided to be responsible and respect listserv rules (including the R-project’s request not to cross-post). They could even start their own R-sig listserv of courses that people could opt into – there’s a need for quality R courses, after all.</p>
<p>Use of mailing lists just to sell courses is even worse outside R-sig-phylo – for example, in June the <a href="https://stat.ethz.ch/pipermail/r-sig-ecology/2025-June/thread.html">28 threads in the R-sig-ecology list</a> were ALL for courses (11 from Physalia, 8 from PR Statistics, 6 from the Institute for Statistical and Data Science, 2 from Transmitting Science, 1 from Highland Statistics), despite the huge number of R users in ecology, and the trend is continuing in July.</p>
<p>Email discussion lists are definitely declining (you can see looking through the R special interest lists how many are practically abandoned) – we all get too many emails, and in some ways social media has replaced the need for mailing lists to ask questions and get answers (see <code>#rstats</code> on bluesky, for example). But one could imagine that in the coming era of AI slop, mailing lists with responses limited to those written by actual humans would once more become essential. It’s sad to see something like R-sig-phylo, which has been a place for good discussion and could be again, get overwhelmed by companies choosing to use it to sell courses: who wants to join or stay on a list if only 4% of posts are directly connected to the list topic? I myself was considering unsubscribing this morning – thus this plea for things to change (and I might as an intermediate step just block any mail from particular companies).</p>
<section id="update-aug-22-2025" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="update-aug-22-2025">Update Aug 22, 2025</h3>
<p>Two of the companies involved have apologized for sending off-topic postings and said they will no longer do this. I’m glad to see this improvement.</p>
<hr>
<p>To subscribe, go to <a href="https://brianomeara.info/blog.xml" class="uri">https://brianomeara.info/blog.xml</a> in an RSS reader.</p>


</section>

<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-citation"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Citation</h2><div><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">BibTeX citation:</div><pre class="sourceCode code-with-copy quarto-appendix-bibtex"><code class="sourceCode bibtex">@online{o'meara2025,
  author = {O’Meara, Brian},
  title = {Course Ads on {R-sig-phylo}},
  date = {2025-07-18},
  url = {https://brianomeara.info/posts/rsig/},
  langid = {en}
}
</code></pre><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">For attribution, please cite this work as:</div><div id="ref-o'meara2025" class="csl-entry quarto-appendix-citeas">
O’Meara, Brian. 2025. <span>“Course Ads on R-Sig-Phylo.”</span> July 18,
2025. <a href="https://brianomeara.info/posts/rsig/">https://brianomeara.info/posts/rsig/</a>.
</div></div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>Rstats</category>
  <guid>https://brianomeara.info/posts/rsig/</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 18 Jul 2025 04:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Conference locations</title>
  <dc:creator>Brian O&#39;Meara</dc:creator>
  <link>https://brianomeara.info/posts/conferencelocations/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>A committee across three evolution societies (Society for the Study of Evolution, Society of Systematic Biologists, American Society of Naturalists) surveyed members and read the literature to make recommendations on how to select conference locations. I wasn’t on this committee, but I served as a liason between them and the joint meeting committee. Their report is <a href="https://www.evolutionmeetings.org/uploads/4/8/8/0/48804503/finalreport.toshare_c-conflocations_dec2024.pdf">here</a>. An important thing to note is that it was finalized in December 2024, before all the changes that have happened in the world since then.</p>
<p>This is intended as a guide for the <a href="https://www.evolutionmeetings.org">Evolution meetings</a>, which happen most commonly in the US (where the majority of the members are) but which do rotate around the world (Brazil, New Zealand, France, Canada, and more). For years the meeting locations were decided based on avoiding states on the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/California_state-funded_travel_ban">California travel ban</a> for both potential safety reasons and due to limitations on travel from scientists in California, but California has now repealed this ban; other factors considered include cost (of travel, lodging, and the convention center), other safety issues, and spreading out where the meetings are. Appeal of the location also matters – the meetings are run to break even, not make or lose money, but having a location where people want to go is important.</p>
<p>The committee noted how much members valued different factors and used these to develop a weighted rubric for choosing locations within the US. There is a separate level of decision about which country to have a conference in, and that can change radically with geopolitical realities, visa restrictions, distribution of members, and much more – this is an increasingly important question but was out of scope for the committee.</p>
<p>So, assuming the conference will be somewhere in the US, the rubric on locations is:</p>
<table class="caption-top table">
<colgroup>
<col style="width: 29%">
<col style="width: 62%">
<col style="width: 7%">
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr class="header">
<th>Factor</th>
<th>Metric</th>
<th>Weight</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr class="odd">
<td>Personal safety</td>
<td>Gun safety (1-5, 1=strongest)</td>
<td>3/16</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>Personal safety</td>
<td>Hate crime incidence (1-5, 1=lowest)</td>
<td>3/16</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td>Experiencing discrimination</td>
<td>LGBTQ+ legal protection (1-5, 1=lowest)</td>
<td>1/8</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>Experiencing discrimination</td>
<td>Race/ethnicity legal protection (1-5, 1=high)</td>
<td>1/8</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td>Availability of medical care</td>
<td>Abortion policies (1-5, 1=least restrictive)</td>
<td>1/8</td>
</tr>
<tr class="even">
<td>Availability of medical care</td>
<td>Gender affirming care laws (1-5, 1=least restrictive)</td>
<td>1/8</td>
</tr>
<tr class="odd">
<td>Legal risks</td>
<td>Anti-trans bathroom laws (1-5, 1=no bans, 5=criminal offense)</td>
<td>1/8</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<p>Lower scores are better. The sources they pointed to for data included:</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://everytownresearch.org/rankings/" class="uri">https://everytownresearch.org/rankings/</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.justice.gov/hatecrimes/state-data" class="uri">https://www.justice.gov/hatecrimes/state-data</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.lgbtmap.org/" class="uri">https://www.lgbtmap.org/</a></li>
<li><a href="https://bjs.ojp.gov/sites/g/files/xyckuh236/files/media/document/naacp_hate_crime_laws_by_state.pdf" class="uri">https://bjs.ojp.gov/sites/g/files/xyckuh236/files/media/document/naacp_hate_crime_laws_by_state.pdf</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.ncsl.org/civil-and-criminal-justice/racial-and-ethnic-disparities-in-the-criminal-justice-system#anchor5408" class="uri">https://www.ncsl.org/civil-and-criminal-justice/racial-and-ethnic-disparities-in-the-criminal-justice-system#anchor5408</a></li>
<li><a href="https://states.guttmacher.org/policies/" class="uri">https://states.guttmacher.org/policies/</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.lgbtmap.org/equality-maps/healthcare_laws_and_policies" class="uri">https://www.lgbtmap.org/equality-maps/healthcare_laws_and_policies</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.lgbtmap.org/equality-maps/nondiscrimination/bathroom_bans" class="uri">https://www.lgbtmap.org/equality-maps/nondiscrimination/bathroom_bans</a></li>
</ul>
<p>This is not the only factor. For example, cost for travel and lodging can vary substanially between locations, and does not always follow conceptions of “expensive” places – a place on the US West Coast with lots of direct flights might be cheaper than a place with a lower cost of living but where most attendees would have to take two or three connecting flights.</p>
<p>One issue that has come up in the past with the California ban list is changing conditions between when a conference is scheduled and when it is held: for example, Ohio was considered fine for years, then it changed its laws. For a meeting like the Evolution meetings, with around 1500 attendees, conference centers are reserved 4-5 years in advance. Things like laws on healthcare access can change dramatically over that time; they can also change at a national level making any state laws moot. Moving can result in large financial penalties – one back of the envelope calculation suggested changing one particular venue might result in hundreds of dollars more per individual registration. It can thus be infeasible to move events even with a year or two warning, making it even more important to try to understand trends before picking locations.</p>
<p>For more detail on the committee’s reasoning and their insights from their survey, check out their <a href="https://www.evolutionmeetings.org/uploads/4/8/8/0/48804503/finalreport.toshare_c-conflocations_dec2024.pdf">PDF</a>. You can see more about choosing locations and other questions for the Evolution meeting <a href="https://www.evolutionmeetings.org/general-information.html">here</a>.</p>
<hr>
<p>To subscribe, go to <a href="https://brianomeara.info/blog.xml" class="uri">https://brianomeara.info/blog.xml</a> in an RSS reader.</p>



<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-citation"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Citation</h2><div><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">BibTeX citation:</div><pre class="sourceCode code-with-copy quarto-appendix-bibtex"><code class="sourceCode bibtex">@online{o'meara2025,
  author = {O’Meara, Brian},
  title = {Conference Locations},
  date = {2025-06-19},
  url = {https://brianomeara.info/posts/conferencelocations/},
  langid = {en}
}
</code></pre><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">For attribution, please cite this work as:</div><div id="ref-o'meara2025" class="csl-entry quarto-appendix-citeas">
O’Meara, Brian. 2025. <span>“Conference Locations.”</span> June 19,
2025. <a href="https://brianomeara.info/posts/conferencelocations/">https://brianomeara.info/posts/conferencelocations/</a>.
</div></div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>conferences</category>
  <category>travel</category>
  <category>meetings</category>
  <guid>https://brianomeara.info/posts/conferencelocations/</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 19 Jun 2025 04:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Williams College stops seeking federal grants</title>
  <dc:creator>Brian O&#39;Meara</dc:creator>
  <link>https://brianomeara.info/posts/williamsgrants/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>Jeffrey Mervis in <em>Science</em> is reporting that <a href="https://www.science.org/content/article/u-s-college-first-decline-federal-science-grants-because-new-dei-language">Williams College is declining federal science grants</a>. According to the article:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>School officials told the faculty Williams won’t accept new grants from the National Science Foundation (NSF) or the National Institutes of Health (NIH) until the agencies clarify new language requiring grantee institutions to certify they aren’t doing anything to “promote or advance diversity, equity, and inclusion (DEI) … in violation of federal antidiscrimination laws.”</p>
</blockquote>
<p>and</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>The provost’s email to faculty also cites a new initiative from the U.S. Department of Justice that allows private citizens to file a complaint against institutions receiving federal funds that they believe are violating federal civil rights laws. Refusing federal grants might decrease the risk that Williams could be sued, the email notes.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Williams College is a small liberal arts college with a high graduation rate, good ratio of tenure stream faculty to students, and an increasing ratio of applicants to available positions (see <a href="https://collegetables.info/168342.html">here</a>). Their faculty, staff, and students publish <a href="https://openalex.org/works?page=1&amp;filter=authorships.institutions.lineage%3Ai22675022&amp;sort=publication_year%3Adesc">hundreds of academic works per year</a>. They have a <a href="https://investment.williams.edu/endowment/">robust endowment</a>. Williams has taken <a href="https://williamsrecord.com/464356/news/williams-college-budget-fiscal-year-2024-explained-fy24/">steps</a> to control expenses while focusing on priorities. All this is just to say that, from a poorly informed external perspective (mine), they seem to do be doing well overall – while there is concern about a lot of small liberal arts colleges, Williams is likely not in that set.</p>
<p>So one question I had was what the potential impact of declining grants could be on a college like this. Looking up grants at <a href="https://www.nsf.gov/awardsearch/advancedSearch.jsp">NSF</a> and <a href="https://reporter.nih.gov">NIH</a>, Williams College was listed as getting nine NSF grants worth $2M in 2024 and nine NSF grants worth $1.8M in 2023; it had no NIH grants in 2024 and one worth $435K in 2023. Based on its budget guide, its F&amp;A rate (the negotiated amount that <em>mostly</em> covers the cost of infrastructure, personnel, and similar to support the research) is 50.8%. So, if we take its two year average of NSF and NIH funding, it could expect $2.1M in grants per year, of which about $1.4M is direct costs and $713K is indirect costs (the exact numbers are hard to calculate as not all direct costs are subject to the F&amp;A rate).</p>
<p>This can pay for a lot of research, and so its <strong>loss will have a real impact on Williams College</strong>, and on <strong>everyone else who would benefit from the discoveries that would have been made</strong>. Federal funding is a zero sum game (if things work well) so the grant money Williams will not get will hopefully flow somewhere else, but Williams stepping back from competing means the pool of ideas to fund is impoverished, the same as any competition if a set of people are excluded from it.</p>
<p>The policy of declining funding has to be weighed against the risks associated with that funding, but some of those risks are unknown – for example, what are the potential risks from a private citizen complaint, and what is the probability of those risks? One federal sanction applied to a different college has been to prohibit international student enrollment (as of today, June 7, 2025, that has been temporarily put on hold, but the final resolution is not certain). International students often pay full tuition, so their loss would be a significant financial hit; that could be less true at Williams since it gives <a href="https://www.williams.edu/admission-aid/financial-aid/international/">substantial aid</a> to many international students, but it would still be costly (quick calculation: 2,146 undergrads, 9% are international, 30% of international pay full tuition = $4.2M in tuition just from these ~58 students, far more than the grant funding loss). Other potential risks include changing taxes on endowments or pressure to remove accreditation. Maybe forgoing federal research funding reduces these risks, though there still are requirements that come with things like federal funding for students that Williams still accepts (a few colleges, like Hillsdale College, <a href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/local/education/hillsdale-college-subject-of-senate-debate-is-known-for-rejecting-federal-funds/2017/12/04/126f94ca-d91b-11e7-b1a8-62589434a581_story.html">choose not to accept federal funds</a> and thus are not subject to Title IV and some other regulations).</p>
<p>This policy also reduces the risk of wasted effort on grant proposals. According to the <a href="https://nsf-gov-resources.nsf.gov/files/00-NSF-FY26-CJ-Entire-Rollup.pdf">proposed NSF budget</a> (see Summary Tables page 5), the success rate for grants will drop from 26% to 7%. That suggests that, if Williams College proposals have the same success rate as the average (likely wrong due to variation across programs and areas, but wrong in an unclear direction), faculty would have written 35 proposals to get their nine funded ones in 2024, but next budget year would have to write 129 to get nine funded ones. Presumably scaling up writing this much wouldn’t be feasible: if instead they put in as many proposals as likely in the past, they could only expect 2-3 grants under the proposed budget. So the prohibition on receiving funding from proposals (and presumably not writing them) means a loss of 2-3 grants rather than 9 (if the proposed budget becomes the de facto one that NSF spends), but also saves the effort of writing 14 proposals for each one that happens to get funded.</p>
<p>One other effect is on tenure expectations. Williams’ new policy makes it less likely to fire early career faculty for not getting major grants (in a tough climate to win funding) since the institution prohibits getting those grants for now (see another <a href="https://brianomeara.info/posts/fundingfortenure/">post</a> by me on this).</p>
<p>These are all rough numbers based on readily available external information only – I’m not part of the Williams community to know all the factors at play, and I have no special insight into what is happening and could happen at the federal level. I also could have just made simple errors (such as missing a whole set of grants in the NSF data).</p>
<p>Overall, I’m not sure if the Williams College policy is a good one or not. It is more likely to be good if it came from a shared governance process so that a lot of smart, concerned people who would be affected by it helped craft it. But my first response to questions like this is to run numbers and analyses, and try to consider all the potential pros and cons, so I’m putting the rough analysis here in case others find parts of it useful.</p>
<hr>
<p>To subscribe, go to <a href="https://brianomeara.info/blog.xml" class="uri">https://brianomeara.info/blog.xml</a> in an RSS reader.</p>



<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-citation"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Citation</h2><div><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">BibTeX citation:</div><pre class="sourceCode code-with-copy quarto-appendix-bibtex"><code class="sourceCode bibtex">@online{o'meara2025,
  author = {O’Meara, Brian},
  title = {Williams {College} Stops Seeking Federal Grants},
  date = {2025-06-07},
  url = {https://brianomeara.info/posts/williamsgrants/},
  langid = {en}
}
</code></pre><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">For attribution, please cite this work as:</div><div id="ref-o'meara2025" class="csl-entry quarto-appendix-citeas">
O’Meara, Brian. 2025. <span>“Williams College Stops Seeking Federal
Grants.”</span> June 7, 2025. <a href="https://brianomeara.info/posts/williamsgrants/">https://brianomeara.info/posts/williamsgrants/</a>.
</div></div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>grants</category>
  <category>financing</category>
  <guid>https://brianomeara.info/posts/williamsgrants/</guid>
  <pubDate>Sat, 07 Jun 2025 04:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Periodical cicadas</title>
  <dc:creator>Brian O&#39;Meara</dc:creator>
  <link>https://brianomeara.info/posts/cicadas/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<section id="periodical-cicadas" class="level1">
<h1>Periodical cicadas</h1>
<p>We aren’t used to abundance in the natural world any longer. There used to be millions of bison on the plains: now there are <a href="https://www.fws.gov/species/plains-bison-bison-bison-bison">around 20,000</a> (plus ones in commercial herds), not enough wild individuals to fill a fifth of the seats of our local football stadium. Passenger pigeons have gone from flocks taking days to pass overhead to extinction. There is scientific evidence for a <a href="https://www.pnas.org/doi/10.1073/pnas.2023989118">massive decline of insects</a> (plus the anecdotal evidence – how many insects have you had to clean off the front of your car, or how many have you seen circling the porch lights lately?). American chestnuts have gone from a population of billions to functional extinction.</p>
<p>Given all this, it’s amazing that there are still creatures whose survival strategy is abundance: fill every hungry mouth, and the excess survive and reproduce. Periodical cicadas emerge at a location every 13 or 17 years (depends on the species) in tremendous numbers. We had one brood in Eastern Tennessee last year, and the brood this year is starting to emerge.</p>
<p>It’s still early, but you can defintely hear them and if you look carefully, see them (follow the sound; then look for ones flying near the tops of trees; then look more closely at the places where they land; eventually you will get a good search image. Later in the year they’ll be extremely obvious in the places they live). Here’s a zoomed in picture from yesterday of several on a branch (look for bits peeking out behind leaves):</p>
<p><img src="https://brianomeara.info/posts/cicadas/Cicadas.jpg" class="img-fluid" alt="Branch with many green leaves glowing in the sun. Two cicadas black with orange accents, are visible, with other ones partially hidden elsewhere on the branch."></p>
<p>And the surprising thing is how accessible they are. These are on a bike path next to Calhoun’s in Oak Ridge, TN – I found them from the sound of their calling, over the sound of a podcast in a closed car. Here’s the tree with them now, so folks in Oak Ridge can find them (walk on the greenway from the rowing association towards Calhoun’s, look at the tops of the two trees on the right just after you cross the bridge close to the restaurant):</p>
<p><img src="https://brianomeara.info/posts/cicadas/CicadaTree.png" class="img-fluid" alt="A tree next to a bike path has a red circle on it; a metal bridge handrail is to the side."></p>
<p>And a <a href="https://www.google.com/maps?q=loc:36.0432778,-84.2026222">map</a> showing their location:</p>
<p><img src="https://brianomeara.info/posts/cicadas/CicadaMap.png" class="img-fluid" alt="An aerial map of Oak Ridge, TN, showing the location of the cicadas with a marker, near Calhoun's restaurant."></p>
<p>It is still early in the emergence – I hope for more as the season progresses. These were still pretty high up in the trees; last year they were lower and more accessible in a slightly different location (broods can overlap somewhat).</p>
<p>One approach to finding them near you is to use iNaturalist, which has a <a href="https://www.inaturalist.org/observations?d1=2025-04-01&amp;subview=map&amp;taxon_id=83854">map</a> of periodical cicadas from this year:</p>
<p><img src="https://brianomeara.info/posts/cicadas/CicadaINat.png" class="img-fluid" alt="A map of the eastern US showing the locations of periodical cicadas observed since April 1, 2025."></p>
<p><a href="https://cicadasafari.org">Cicada Safari</a> has more info on periodical cicadas.</p>
<hr>
<p>To subscribe, go to <a href="https://brianomeara.info/blog.xml" class="uri">https://brianomeara.info/blog.xml</a> in an RSS reader.</p>


</section>

<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-citation"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Citation</h2><div><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">BibTeX citation:</div><pre class="sourceCode code-with-copy quarto-appendix-bibtex"><code class="sourceCode bibtex">@online{o'meara2025,
  author = {O’Meara, Brian},
  title = {Periodical Cicadas},
  date = {2025-05-18},
  url = {https://brianomeara.info/posts/cicadas/},
  langid = {en}
}
</code></pre><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">For attribution, please cite this work as:</div><div id="ref-o'meara2025" class="csl-entry quarto-appendix-citeas">
O’Meara, Brian. 2025. <span>“Periodical Cicadas.”</span> May 18, 2025.
<a href="https://brianomeara.info/posts/cicadas/">https://brianomeara.info/posts/cicadas/</a>.
</div></div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>cicadas</category>
  <category>natural history</category>
  <guid>https://brianomeara.info/posts/cicadas/</guid>
  <pubDate>Sun, 18 May 2025 04:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Funding for tenure</title>
  <dc:creator>Brian O&#39;Meara</dc:creator>
  <link>https://brianomeara.info/posts/fundingfortenure/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>In the US, science funding is being cut, including the elimination of entire areas of study from federal funding. There are predictions of yet more reductions. This will affect what will be studied, who can study it, and even who survive diseases. Various individuals and groups are working to address this. I want to address just one small part of this where faculty still have (some) control: criteria we use in awarding tenure.</p>
<p>The standards for tenure can be opaque to various degrees: we all do teaching, research, and service, and institutions vary in how they weight each of these within the institution and across faculty members. Institutions vary in what constitutes evidence for each. For example, one person might teach a large number of intro classes and have peer evaluation of their teaching, while at a different institution someone may teach a few small enrollment classes and be evaluated on how well they are mentoring grad students. The AAUP has a <a href="https://www.aaup.org/report/2022-aaup-survey-tenure-practices">survey</a> of tenure practices, a quarter-century old <a href="https://www.aaup.org/sites/default/files/files/Good%20Practice%20in%20Tenure%20Evaluation.pdf">book</a> about best practices (probably due for some updating), and a <a href="https://www.aaup.org/issues/tenure/resources-tenure">page</a> aggregating additional resources for those seeking to learn more.</p>
<p>But imagine if a department had a standard for tenure of using 10,000 pipette tips. Each time you finish a box of tips, you put an empty box against the wall: only 105 boxes total to get to tenure! Of course, this doesn’t work for people doing bird banding, or theoretical ecology, or any of a myriad of research programs. Pipette tips are a tool, not a goal. Within a narrow area they might be an okay proxy for productivity: back when I was <a href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/nuccore/?term=brian+o%27meara">sequencing ant DNA</a> my pipette box accumulation rate could have been a good way to spot check how much time I was spending in the ant lab. But it would have been a terrible way to measure how much work I was spending coding new methods or writing papers. And using tips as a criterion could warp the research program: instead of banding birds, someone might have to change the research to do blood draws on captured birds to have a wet lab component, just in order to use enough tips to get tenure.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://brianomeara.info/posts/fundingfortenure/emptyboxes.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Stack of about forty empty pipette boxes: navy blue boxes, most for 200 µl pipette tips, with opaque white covers, in a wood cabinet."></p>
<figcaption>Enough boxes to be 38% of the way to tenure? Photo from <a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/labrats/comments/nvzy6b/what_on_earth_do_you_do_with_your_empty_tip_boxes/">reddit user strawspiderflower.</a></figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>I suggest funding is the same. It is a <em>tool</em> that enables research, outreach, and more, but it <em>isn’t the goal itself</em>. It’s fantastically useful, of course. I’ve been lucky to work with 17 postdocs so far as a mentor, all of whom needed money for things like food and health care: about half the time, that came from grants I wrote, with the rest of the time coming from grants written by others (thanks, NSF, and the UTK team who wrote the <a href="https://legacy.nimbios.org/about/impact">NIMBioS (National Institute for Mathematical and Biological Synthesis)</a> grant!). Other people need funding to pay for sequencing, or to fly to Costa Rica to collect insects, or to get a LI-COR to measure leaf respiration. And different research requires different amounts of funding – someone collecting fossils in the Arctic is not a better scientist than someone collecting fossils ten miles away from campus, but the former requires more money (and is generally less accessible to students). If both scientists are publishing good work at the same rate, why do we care that one person had to rent a helicopter and another a bicycle? It gets even more stark between fields: someone doing mathematical models may need far less funding than someone working on cancer research in a general biology department, and they also have access to different funding sources (at least historically, NIH provided more money than NSF), but the department is better for having both of them in the same place.</p>
<p>This is a time when there is even less reason to judge people by their funding. Federal funders and others have been cutting off funding for entire subfields. Faculty are pivoting their science to be able to keep doing work that matters. We want to encourage this: let them grow their research program and adapt to the changing world (this does not mean not trying to make improvements, but it does recognize external constraints). Having a performance standard that is based on the quality of science they are communicating makes sense. Adding a second metric, funding, warps that. In evolutionary biology, we teach about tradeoffs: armor is great, so is flight, but we don’t have flying armored turtles. Funding can serve the science, but making it a criterion in itself creates potential tradeoffs between the best science to do and the best science to get funding.</p>
<p><strong>Suggested action item</strong>: Departments should have conversations about criteria for tenure, and explictly discuss, and put in writing, that funding is NOT one of those criteria. Ideally, this should be put into departmental bylaws. The end of the semester is a hard time for this, but faculty are going to be trying to figure out what to do this summer: giving them reassurance about optimizing just for good science will let them focus on this. For some, this will require figuring out funding, but not for all. When people come back together in the Fall, bylaws that mention funding should be amended, as well as similar work at higher levels of an institution. There might be work that correlates with funding (Has a faculty member been able to recruit and mentor grad students? Have they been able to develop modern, publishable datasets?) but <em>the work</em> is what we care about, not the funding itself.</p>
<section id="what-about-indirect-costs-startup-etc." class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="what-about-indirect-costs-startup-etc.">What about indirect costs, startup, etc.?</h3>
<p>An objection to ignoring funding as a criterion for tenure is that grants are ways to support other aspects of the university. It is worth digging into the details of this, though.</p>
<p>First, though it’s an imperfect analogy, it can be useful to compare a new lab to a new coffee shop. To start up a coffee shop, one needs to get a building, equipment, and supplies: everything from flour to make the donuts to a soap dispenser in the bathroom to cups for the coffee. Then one needs to hire and train staff. Only then can one open for business and start making money. For example, for a <a href="https://finance.yahoo.com/news/much-costs-own-starbucks-franchise-180021683.html">Starbucks</a>, it costs $315,000 to license a store (which includes some equipment) and one must have $700,000 in cash for other costs. [Note I really wanted to find the similar cost for the far superior Dunkin’ Donuts instead, but it’s not available]. That’s the same order of magnitude as starting a biology lab at a research-intensive university, where startups in the hundreds of thousands of dollars are common.</p>
<p>One question any business owner has to face is how much to price each item. There’s the obvious cost of ingredients; there’s also the fractional cost of the employee that makes the coffee: a fancier coffee takes more time and so should cost more. But there are other costs that are harder to calculate. What fraction of a light bulb’s lifespan is used to illuminate the coffee station where the coffee is made? How much of the cash register’s overall cost is each cup of coffee responsible for? What about the person working the cash register? One way to do this would be to measure this exactly for everything: “hot tea” takes less time to say than “regular coffee black with two sugars” so the latter costs more of the cashier’s time. A different approach would be to figure out the obvious costs for the ingredients and direct labor, figure out all the other costs for the entire store, and find a ratio that makes it break even with a little extra for profit. For example, if a small cup of coffee costs $1.00 to make, add 50% to the cost of that to cover all the other costs and charge $1.50; maybe bump it up to $1.59 for a little profit.</p>
<p>The same applies for a lab. If one is proposing a project to sequence ant DNA to infer their phylogeny, there’s the cost to go to collect the ants in the field, the DNA extraction kits, PCR reagents, sequencing costs, and more. There’s the cost for the grad student to do the work (stipend, health care, and tuition). These are all calculated ahead of time and charged to the funder. But there are also all the other costs: someone to make sure the lab is run safely, having a building to do the work in, paying to run the -80 ˚C freezer, and more. Rather than figuring out these costs per project, the institution where the work happens negotiates with the federal government about the average overall costs. At a university, every $100 of direct cost might mean $50-60 in indirect costs, so that can be the negotiated rate. For institutions like children’s hospitals, it can be even higher, like <a href="https://www.childrenshospital.org/sites/default/files/2024-09/BCH%20RATE%20AGREEMENT_03.18.24.pdf">78%</a> at Children’s Hospital Boston.</p>
<p>The thing is, the folk wisdom about this (backed by research: <a href="https://pmc.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/articles/PMC3987954/">Holbrook and Sanberg (2013)</a>) is that universities lose money on this. The indirect costs do not quite cover the cost of the research. In some ways, this is like athletics programs: they only <a href="https://sportsdata.usatoday.com/ncaa/finances">rarely</a> make money, but they help with brand recognition, student spirit, and more. Research is even more central to the mission of a university – universities are about generating new knowledge and sharing it, and funded research is a major part of this. Overall amount of research expenditure is also a metric used in rating or categorizing universities – it looks “good” by metrics some care about to have a lot of research expenditure.</p>
<p>Moreover, just in terms of earnings per square foot, research labs are a spectacularly bad way to make money. Take the University of Florida, a major research university. As of the latest data (2023), it had <a href="https://ncses.nsf.gov/surveys/science-engineering-research-facilities/2023#survey-info">3,884,000 square feet</a> for research and engineering; it also spent (from external funds) <a href="https://ncsesdata.nsf.gov/profiles/site?method=rankingbysource&amp;ds=herd">$1,250,201,000</a>, for an average of $322 per square foot. A Starbucks has sales of $700/sqft, McDonald’s $2196/sqft, an Apple store $25,000/sqft, and even Walmart is $407/sqft (from <a href="https://www.analystinterview.com/article/understanding-sales-per-square-foot-a-key-metric-in-retail-food-and-beverages">here</a>, which is not peer-reviewed). And consider the cost to run a Walmart compared to a bunch of labs with the same total amount of square footage: Walmart has no fume hoods, no centrifuges, few expensive freezers, minimal computers, etc. and yet it only makes about 3% profit on this earnings per square foot. Walmart’s earnings for this space are 25% higher than what U. of Florida brings in with grants – it is hard to imagine U. of Florida is breaking even at this rate (and that is before proposed cuts in indirect rates). But the university is fostering <a href="https://explore.research.ufl.edu">great research</a> that has both immediate impacts (<a href="https://news.ufl.edu/2025/01/citrus-greening-research/">helping citrus growers</a>) and long-term discoveries (<a href="https://explore.research.ufl.edu/secrets-of-the-sea.html">detecting wildlife with wisps of DNA in the ocean</a>) while also training students and postdocs as part of its educational mission. And this sort of contribution is common for the thousands of universities across the US.</p>
<p>So, TL;DR: any university is likely losing money on research in general; given the high variance in how much funding different research groups bring in, it is likely that nearly all individual labs are overall subsidized by the university (the “Use AI to find people who are bad credit risks” or the “Patent a banana that stays yellow for months” labs might be exceptions). Many people, even from “successful” labs (based on grants), are not bringing in enough funding to break even, but they are worth the investment due to their discoveries. Our institutions at a high level realize that the research is what matters and focus on that. For those of us who are even closer to the research, in the same departments as those doing the work, we should similarly value the quality of the work, not the money or other tools used to help achieve it. We must put in structural changes to reassure our junior colleagues that we will evaluate their work, not their funding, especially now.</p>
<hr>
<p>To subscribe, go to <a href="https://brianomeara.info/blog.xml" class="uri">https://brianomeara.info/blog.xml</a> in an RSS reader.</p>


</section>

<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-citation"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Citation</h2><div><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">BibTeX citation:</div><pre class="sourceCode code-with-copy quarto-appendix-bibtex"><code class="sourceCode bibtex">@online{o'meara2025,
  author = {O’Meara, Brian},
  title = {Funding for Tenure},
  date = {2025-05-04},
  url = {https://brianomeara.info/posts/fundingfortenure/},
  langid = {en}
}
</code></pre><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">For attribution, please cite this work as:</div><div id="ref-o'meara2025" class="csl-entry quarto-appendix-citeas">
O’Meara, Brian. 2025. <span>“Funding for Tenure.”</span> May 4, 2025. <a href="https://brianomeara.info/posts/fundingfortenure/">https://brianomeara.info/posts/fundingfortenure/</a>.
</div></div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>NSF</category>
  <category>NIH</category>
  <category>tenure</category>
  <category>funding</category>
  <category>indirect costs</category>
  <guid>https://brianomeara.info/posts/fundingfortenure/</guid>
  <pubDate>Sun, 04 May 2025 04:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>How long does balance in eponymous names require?</title>
  <dc:creator>Brian O&#39;Meara</dc:creator>
  <link>https://brianomeara.info/posts/eponymous_birds/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>Today I saw a <a href="https://bsky.app/profile/zoojlinnsoc.bsky.social/post/3llgxuqt7pg2x">post</a> on bluesky from the <em>Zoological Journal of the Linnean Society</em> about a <a href="https://doi.org/10.1093/zoolinnean/zlaf022">new paper</a> by Dr.&nbsp;George Sangster on eponyms in birds: naming birds after people. This is an issue I’ve been curious about for some time, partly due to the related issue of naming awards after people (see <a href="https://brianomeara.info/evol2023.html#award-naming">here</a>). Issues that come up in these areas are 1) should we name organisms after people who did awful things? 2) how extensive are the biases in who gets species named after them? 3) what are the effects of either of the above on recruiting and retainng people in the field? and 4) how will changes in naming practices, both moving forward and (more controversially) changing existing names affect the above three points? The paper represents a tremendous amount of careful work to address the second question, including an analysis of how the biases have changed over time.</p>
<p>The <a href="https://doi.org/10.1093/zoolinnean/zlaf022">paper</a> is well worth reading and contributes greatly to this discussion. However, I was a bit surprised by one of its conclusions:</p>
<p>“Importantly, there is no need for drastic changes in naming practices, because the desired changes (greater representation of women and non-western people) are already taking place (and have been for several decades).”</p>
<p>The paper does identify trends in this direction, but I was curious about how long the changes would require. Dr.&nbsp;Sangster generously released the analyzed data as a supplemental file, so I downloaded it to run some analyses. It already had some linear regressions showing changes in representation since 1900; I threw the file into R to do similar analyses, but extrapolating to the future.</p>
<section id="proportionality-in-new-names" class="level2" data-number="1">
<h2 data-number="1" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="proportionality-in-new-names"><span class="header-section-number">1</span> Proportionality in new names</h2>
<p>The first question is how long with current trends it will take for a proportional fraction of the eponymous names to be named after people in the different groups. For gender, if we limit the population of potential namesakes to women and men only, and assume they are equal frequencies in the population, parity is at 50%. For Western vs non-Western, one standard would also be 50%; a better one might be to use proportion of the world population that is Western vs non-Western (though this has also changed over time). Using populations sizes from <a href="https://www.worldometers.info/world-population/">here</a>, and adopting the definition of Western the paper seemed to use, 85.8% of people are non-Western.</p>
<p>Using these thresholds and linear regression, with a 95% confidence interval:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Year when half of NEW eponyms are named for women: 2340 (2220, 2662)</strong></li>
<li><strong>Year when half of NEW eponyms are named for non-Western people: 2101 (2070, 2156)</strong></li>
<li><strong>Year when a proportional number of NEW eponyms are named for non-Western people: 2255 (2191, 2367)</strong></li>
</ul>
<p>So, it will take 315 years to have equal representation of women in new eponyms, and 230 years to have proportional representation of non-Western people, under the current yearly increase in representation in names taxonomists choose. This is about as far in the future as Linneaus was in the past. That’s a long time.</p>
<p>Below are some plots showing the extrapolations. Clearly, extrapolating out this far is silly: but the big point is that even with current trends it’s going to take a very, very long time.</p>
<p><img src="https://brianomeara.info/posts/eponymous_birds/women_future.jpg" class="img-fluid" alt="Scatter plot showing the proportion of women in eponymous names over time, with a linear regression line showing the trend. A dotted line shows the 50% value, which is not reached until far in the future."></p>
<p><img src="https://brianomeara.info/posts/eponymous_birds/nonwestern_future.jpg" class="img-fluid" alt="Scatter plot showing the proportion of non-Western people in eponymous names over time, with a linear regression line showing the trend. A dotted line shows the 50% value and the 85% values."></p>
</section>
<section id="proportionality-in-all-names" class="level2" data-number="2">
<h2 data-number="2" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="proportionality-in-all-names"><span class="header-section-number">2</span> Proportionality in all names</h2>
<p>A different question is how long it will take for half of the eponymous bird species to be named after women, and how long it will take for the proportion of eponymous names for non-Western people to be equal to their population. One issue is that birds are a well-studied group: the number of new species being described is declining (though not an argument for lack of a need for more taxonomy):</p>
<p><img src="https://brianomeara.info/posts/eponymous_birds/new_birds.jpg" class="img-fluid" alt="Scatter plot showing the number of new bird species described over time, with a linear regression line and smooth regression line showing the trend after 1900."></p>
<p>An extrapolation into the future quickly results in having a negative number of newly described species in future years. I instead used a more optimistic assumption that the future will resemble the 10 year average of the most recent years in the dataset, so with 16.7 species described per year.</p>
<p>We can see how the number of species named after women, men, Westerners, and non-Westerners has changed over time up to the present:</p>
<p><img src="https://brianomeara.info/posts/eponymous_birds/full_predictions_present.jpg" class="img-fluid" alt="Line plot showing the number of eponymous names over time. Men and Western are very similar (since they were the vast majority of people having species named after them) but the rate has slowed down; Women and non-Western people are increasing, but the number of such species is still far lower than for the first two groups."></p>
<p>And then we can continue the trend into the future, incorporating the increasing proportion of species named for women and non-Western people but also the trend of a greater proportion of eponyms overall (which I was surprised to learn about in the original paper). I ran the model for a thousand years into the future:</p>
<p><img src="https://brianomeara.info/posts/eponymous_birds/full_predictions_future.jpg" class="img-fluid" alt="Line plot showing the number of eponymous names over time from 1758 to 3025. Lines for Men and Westerners continue to be well above the lines for Women and non-Westerners for the duration of the plot."></p>
<p>So at least over the next thousand years, eponymous bird names will not reach parity with human population proportions for the groups analyzed in this paper.</p>
</section>
<section id="conclusions" class="level2" data-number="3">
<h2 data-number="3" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="conclusions"><span class="header-section-number">3</span> Conclusions</h2>
<p>Taxonomy works on long time scales. But if having more representative names is considered important, business as usual, even with trends for more inclusive naming practices, are at best centuries from reaching parity for new names and may never reach it for all names in birds.</p>
</section>
<section id="analysis-code" class="level2" data-number="4">
<h2 data-number="4" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="analysis-code"><span class="header-section-number">4</span> Analysis code</h2>
<p>This was all done in R using the packages <code>targets</code>, <code>tidyverse</code>, <code>ggplot2</code>, <code>readxl</code>, <code>ggpmisc</code>, <code>stringr</code>, <code>ggrepel</code>, and <code>RColorBrewer</code>. Source code is at <a href="https://github.com/bomeara/eponymous_birds" class="uri">https://github.com/bomeara/eponymous_birds</a>.</p>
</section>
<section id="acknowledgements" class="level2" data-number="5">
<h2 data-number="5" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="acknowledgements"><span class="header-section-number">5</span> Acknowledgements</h2>
<p>Thank you to Dr.&nbsp;Sangster for the detailed work on this important issue, for writing a compelling paper, and for making the data so available. Again, I encourage you to read <a href="https://doi.org/10.1093/zoolinnean/zlaf022">this work</a> for its insights.</p>
<hr>
<p>To subscribe, go to <a href="https://brianomeara.info/blog.xml" class="uri">https://brianomeara.info/blog.xml</a> in an RSS reader.</p>


</section>

<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-citation"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Citation</h2><div><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">BibTeX citation:</div><pre class="sourceCode code-with-copy quarto-appendix-bibtex"><code class="sourceCode bibtex">@online{o'meara2025,
  author = {O’Meara, Brian},
  title = {How Long Does Balance in Eponymous Names Require?},
  date = {2025-03-28},
  url = {https://brianomeara.info/posts/eponymous_birds/},
  langid = {en}
}
</code></pre><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">For attribution, please cite this work as:</div><div id="ref-o'meara2025" class="csl-entry quarto-appendix-citeas">
O’Meara, Brian. 2025. <span>“How Long Does Balance in Eponymous Names
Require?”</span> March 28, 2025. <a href="https://brianomeara.info/posts/eponymous_birds/">https://brianomeara.info/posts/eponymous_birds/</a>.
</div></div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>taxonomy</category>
  <category>birds</category>
  <category>rstats</category>
  <guid>https://brianomeara.info/posts/eponymous_birds/</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 28 Mar 2025 04:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Uncertainty and risk</title>
  <dc:creator>Brian O&#39;Meara</dc:creator>
  <link>https://brianomeara.info/posts/uncertaintyandrisk/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>As I write this (Jan 31, 2025), it is an odd time. The new US presidential administration cut off disbursement of most federal funds; a court order then stayed this, and the memo pausing disbursement was retracted, but there is still an argument as to whether funds may flow. Regardless, the National Science Foundation is still not disbursing funds, even to PRFB postdocs who rely on requested withdrawals to be paid (even requests from last week are not being processed). There is an “updated often” <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20250131165539/https://new.nsf.gov/executive-orders">page</a> from NSF that hasn’t changed in a couple of days. It’s not clear when or if funding will resume, nor what programs, if any, might be cut. Some colleges have told people to rein in expenditures, others just to limit expenditures that might violate an executive order, some have said change nothing in how funds should be used.</p>
<p>In the meantime, on social media there are many splashy advertisements to recruit students for NSF-sponsored research experiences for undergrads (REUs). These can be transformative: undergrads are supported over a summer to do new research they drive, often surrounded by strong mentoring and other support structures. If a student takes this, it replaces essentially a summer job or other internship.</p>
<p>This is also a time when grad recruiting is happening: some programs are flying students out for interviews and visits. In the sciences, generally students are both admitted to a program <strong>and</strong> offered a job as a teaching assistant or research assistant; the job pays tuition, offers healthcare, and gives a student a stipend. TAs are generally centrally funded: there must be people to run discussion sections or labs, and so departments get a certain number of lines to staff their classes. The funding for these will generally come out of university funds, a mixture of tuition and perhaps state support or endowment funds. RAs are generally funded by external grants (with some exceptions). If an RA dries up, a student might then be put on a TA line.</p>
<p>The uncertainty is what happens to REUs and RA lines in the future. It could be that everything reverts to how it was: it is a rigorous process to select what the government will fund (with the vast majority of proposals being rejected), using criteria that were passed into law and have been stable for many years, and so changing them, especially on already awarded funds, might not take place (and there are legal and prudential arguments for such an outcome). The other extreme is that all current NSF funding is cut, eliminating REUs and RAs entirely, and even existing TAs might be needed for current grad students on an RA. Or it could be something in between. There is nothing public that is definitive either way. And even if we had perfect knowledge of current plans, that is of only modest predictive value: maybe a lawsuit stops one intended outcome, maybe another Sputnik moment leads to an <em>increase</em> in funding. We just can’t know, and that may go on for a while.</p>
<section id="what-we-can-do" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="what-we-can-do">What we can do</h3>
<p>There are lots of discussions about what various external actors should be doing with this; a thing we have control of is <strong>how we handle this uncertainty</strong>. A big part of that is deciding <strong>who inherits the risk</strong> and <strong>how the risk is communicated</strong>.</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Business as usual</strong> <em>(high student risk, low university risk, max opportunities)</em>: For example, one approach is to assume things continue as before: anything with allocated or promised funding will continue to receive funds. Offers are made to an REU or grad school, likely with a small parenthetical statement on “(subject to availability of funds),” and students jump at the offered chance and get rid of their other options. This is optimal for the REU or grad program: if all goes well, great students sign up early, so the grant or the RA line is filled with strong candidates. If funds do go away, the students are out of a job and have to scramble, but the program itself is fine – no loss of money. This maximizes risk to students. It also incentivizes minimizing communication of risk so students feel safe signing up early. But students are in a very poor position to understand risk: if faculty and administrators don’t know what is going on, what chance does a sophomore applying to an REU or a senior applying for a grad program have?</li>
<li><strong>University steps up</strong> <em>(low student risk, high university risk, min opportunities)</em>: A different approach would be to have the university assume the risk. Make the offers, but if funding does not arrive, the university takes on the burden of supporting the students. This is a major risk to the university, but the university at least has better ways to assess risk (through connections to lobbyists, legislators, etc.) than a bunch of undergrads do. A university also likely has a much fatter savings account (endowment) than students, though often with contraints on how it can be spent. Besides the risk to the university, this does also lead to fewer opportunities: the university might be able to support only half the enrollment a grant would, so fewer students get an offer.</li>
<li><strong>Max transparency</strong> <em>(low student risk, moderate university risk, moderate opportunities)</em>: An intermediate approach would be maximal communication. Be very up front about risks to funding and that, even if the program wants to admit them, students should keep a backup plan up to some reasonable date. One approach to this, borrowed from college athletics, could be letters of intent. “We intend to admit you to our REU / grad program with this offer, but cannot formally promise this until [some date].” Then, when funding is assured or the university is comfortable assuming the risk for the student, send a formal offer of admissions. The risk is that “good” students might go to a university adopting the first approach (“I have a letter of intent from you, but they gave me an offer [with an asterisk I missed], so I’m going there”); the benefit is that it’s possible that there are more students admitted than under approach two. It’s also less dishonest than the first approach (which does not exactly lie, but is far from forthcoming about possibilities).</li>
</ul>
<p>This is likely to be a long period of uncertainty, with a lot of focus on what people can do to change things at national levels. But we do have (more) control on what we do within our own institutions. We will need to continually ask ourselves who we are helping, who we are putting at risk, and how we can be honest about this. This is on us.</p>
<hr>
<p>To subscribe, go to <a href="https://brianomeara.info/blog.xml" class="uri">https://brianomeara.info/blog.xml</a> in an RSS reader.</p>


</section>

<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-citation"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Citation</h2><div><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">BibTeX citation:</div><pre class="sourceCode code-with-copy quarto-appendix-bibtex"><code class="sourceCode bibtex">@online{o'meara2025,
  author = {O’Meara, Brian},
  title = {Uncertainty and Risk},
  date = {2025-01-31},
  url = {https://brianomeara.info/posts/uncertaintyandrisk/},
  langid = {en}
}
</code></pre><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">For attribution, please cite this work as:</div><div id="ref-o'meara2025" class="csl-entry quarto-appendix-citeas">
O’Meara, Brian. 2025. <span>“Uncertainty and Risk.”</span> January 31,
2025. <a href="https://brianomeara.info/posts/uncertaintyandrisk/">https://brianomeara.info/posts/uncertaintyandrisk/</a>.
</div></div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>NSF</category>
  <category>REU</category>
  <category>gradschool</category>
  <category>funding</category>
  <guid>https://brianomeara.info/posts/uncertaintyandrisk/</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 31 Jan 2025 05:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Field Safety</title>
  <dc:creator>Brian O&#39;Meara</dc:creator>
  <link>https://brianomeara.info/posts/fieldsafety/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>Over the 2023-2024 academic year, a committee in UTK EEB worked on field safety. This involves things like avoiding snakebite and traffic accidents (see Richard Conniff’s <a href="https://strangebehaviors.wordpress.com/2011/01/14/the-wall-of-the-dead/">memorial to fallen naturalists</a>) but also social factors. I am putting some information from this here to help others access it, but note it is a team effort.</p>
<p>We went through a set of readings. Some relevant ones in this area include:</p>
<ul>
<li>Demery &amp; Pipkin (2020): <a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/s41559-020-01328-5" class="uri">https://www.nature.com/articles/s41559-020-01328-5</a></li>
<li>Rudzki et al.&nbsp;(2022): <a href="https://besjournals.onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1111/2041-210X.13970" class="uri">https://besjournals.onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1111/2041-210X.13970</a></li>
<li>Blonder (2022): <a href="https://esajournals.onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/full/10.1002/bes2.2031" class="uri">https://esajournals.onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/full/10.1002/bes2.2031</a></li>
<li>Clancy et al.&nbsp;(2014): <a href="https://journals.plos.org/plosone/article?id=10.1371/journal.pone.0102172" class="uri">https://journals.plos.org/plosone/article?id=10.1371/journal.pone.0102172</a></li>
</ul>
<p>To help with this, several of us made a checklist. It is below. Feel free to adapt it for your own use.</p>
<p><strong>Work travel checklist</strong></p>
<p><strong>Discussions to have before going</strong></p>
<ul>
<li><p>Introductions between all participants</p></li>
<li><p>Comfort levels with risk, activities</p>
<ul>
<li>Discussing criteria for deciding when/if to end fieldwork; students (everyone) should be empowered to speak up about conditions and expectations</li>
</ul></li>
<li><p>Health needs, accessibility needs, safety needs of all participants, medication needs</p></li>
<li><p>Financial arrangements: how paying for things works in the field: who is paying for what and how</p></li>
<li><p>Housing arrangement discussions</p></li>
<li><p>Personal space, downtime, bathroom needs / procedures</p></li>
<li><p>Bathrooms: people should use the one they feel most comfortable with; it is no one on the team’s role to police others’ bathroom use. Note that various locations may have different policies; it is up to individuals to assess these for themselves.</p></li>
<li><p>Culture, language, and etiquette of the location, especially internationally</p></li>
<li><p>Weapons in the field</p>
<ul>
<li><p>People you will encounter in the field will be armed (and think about PTSD)</p></li>
<li><p>Note <a href="https://policy.tennessee.edu/policy/sa0875-firearms/">UTK firearms policy</a> if any participant may be considering carrying</p></li>
<li><p>UTK policies for weapons (e.g.&nbsp;knives, pepper spray): <a href="https://studentconduct.utk.edu/wp-content/uploads/sites/53/2021/08/2m3k1ac-Fall-StudentCodeOfConduct_WEB.pdf">UTK Student Code of Conduct</a>. Carrying a knife in the field can be useful if allowable</p></li>
<li><p>Note policies of various places about firearms (GSMNP does not allow firearms, for example)</p></li>
<li><p>Discuss safety in general</p></li>
</ul></li>
<li><p>Possible hazards at site</p>
<ul>
<li>List the ones possible: could be human factors (civil unrest), wildlife, falling branches, driving risks, etc.</li>
</ul></li>
</ul>
<p><strong>To resolve months in advance</strong></p>
<ul>
<li><p>Vaccination requirements</p></li>
<li><p>Research permits for site</p></li>
<li><p>Import permits</p></li>
<li><p>Chemical permits: look at EHS policies for chemical safety</p></li>
<li><p>Visas (note that participants may be citizens of different countries leading to different requirements)</p></li>
<li><p>State department guidelines for various countries</p></li>
<li><p>California travel warnings for certain states</p></li>
<li><p>LGBTQ travel advisories for non-US travel: <a href="https://travel.state.gov/content/travel/en/international-travel/before-you-go/travelers-with-special-considerations/lgbtqi.html" class="uri">https://travel.state.gov/content/travel/en/international-travel/before-you-go/travelers-with-special-considerations/lgbtqi.html</a></p></li>
<li><p>Travel insurance: <a href="https://cge.utk.edu/intlsos/" class="uri">https://cge.utk.edu/intlsos/</a> if university-sponsored travel (ask EEB for funding if you are paying on your own)</p></li>
<li><p>UTK travel authorization form (extra steps if international;​​ <a href="https://cge.utk.edu/travel/" class="uri">https://cge.utk.edu/travel/</a>)</p></li>
<li><p>Have discussion about health needs, accessibility needs, safety needs of all participants, medication needs</p></li>
<li><p>For air travel, documentation required for boarding (think about how equipment and chemicals will be shipped)</p></li>
<li><p>Request travel advance from the department</p></li>
</ul>
<p><strong>At least a month in advance of field work</strong></p>
<ul>
<li><p>Daily communication plan established</p></li>
<li><p>Hazard plan for each site established</p>
<ul>
<li><p>Consider all hazards, including but not limited to automobiles (wear seat belts!), landslides, flooding, volcanic eruptions, earthquakes, extreme heat, wildfires, civil unrest, protests, animals, plants, diseases, racism, sexism</p></li>
<li><p>Recreational hazards: swimming in ocean, ziplining, rafting, etc.</p></li>
</ul></li>
<li><p>Field research letter from the department</p></li>
<li><p>Notify residents near the field site about plans, get permissions if possible - in letter, email, phone, or go door to door</p></li>
<li><p>Check if site or travel route has a recent history of incidents - for example, is it a possible <a href="https://justice.tougaloo.edu/sundown-towns/using-the-sundown-towns-database/state-map/">sundown town</a>? What places are not safe to stop for gas?</p>
<ul>
<li>Check for short term events that may cause risks, delays, etc.: anything from a parade to roads washing out to an event that could get heated</li>
</ul></li>
<li><p>Assess need for satellite phones or other communication devices that work without cell service [Update Oct 2, 2025: satellite messaging from cell phones is becoming available. Recent iPhones can <a href="https://support.apple.com/en-us/105097">send messages or ask for help</a>, and T-Mobile has a service (included with some T-Mobile plans, but also available for $10/month for people on other plans) that lets users send <a href="https://www.theverge.com/news/790412/t-mobile-satellite-service-apps-x-whatsapp-google-maps">messages, use maps, and even video chat</a> over satellite.]</p></li>
<li><p>Appropriate field clothing (footwear, sun protection)</p></li>
<li><p>Make sure there are enough vehicles (UTK fleet: <a href="https://fleetmanagement.utk.edu/" class="uri">https://fleetmanagement.utk.edu/</a>)</p></li>
<li><p>Get book of receipts (for buying things that don’t usually come with receipts)</p></li>
<li><p>Have protocol for saving receipts of all kinds</p></li>
<li><p>Consider travel advance, especially for longer trips.</p></li>
<li><p>Mileage logbook</p></li>
<li><p>List of emergency contacts, including:</p>
<ul>
<li><p>Local contact info for emergency assistance (911 isn’t global); International SOS card <a href="https://cge.utk.edu/intlsos/" class="uri">https://cge.utk.edu/intlsos/</a></p></li>
<li><p>Contacts of others on the trip</p></li>
<li><p>UTK assistance:</p>
<ul>
<li><p>Travel office</p></li>
<li><p>Title IX office (for harassment): <a href="https://titleix.utk.edu/" class="uri">https://titleix.utk.edu/</a></p></li>
<li><p>Workmans’ compensation (for getting coverage for injuries during work/travel): <a href="https://riskmanagement.tennessee.edu/workers-compensation/" class="uri">https://riskmanagement.tennessee.edu/workers-compensation/</a></p></li>
</ul></li>
</ul></li>
</ul>
<p><strong>Before leaving</strong></p>
<ul>
<li><p>Project specific equipment: personal gear, safety gear (hard hats, gloves, etc.), scientific equipment, sharpies, baggies, etc. Spell them all out as a separate checklist specific to this activity.</p></li>
<li><p>Cell phones charged</p></li>
<li><p>Chargers</p></li>
<li><p>Sufficient water <a href="https://www.rei.com/learn/expert-advice/hydrate.html">(0.5-1 liters per person per hour in the field)</a></p></li>
<li><p>First aid kit on board (comprehensive, not just bandaids. Handle sprains, pain, deep cuts, etc.)</p></li>
<li><p>Sunscreen</p></li>
<li><p>Car magnets</p></li>
<li><p>Food/snacks</p></li>
<li><p>Hygiene products</p>
<ul>
<li><p>Hand sanitizer</p></li>
<li><p>Soap</p></li>
<li><p>Toilet paper, trowel for digging hole (when allowed in the field)</p></li>
<li><p>Tampons/pads</p></li>
</ul></li>
<li><p>Personal medication (brought by each individual)</p>
<ul>
<li><p>Allergy medication</p></li>
<li><p>Painkillers</p></li>
<li><p>Digestive medications</p></li>
</ul></li>
<li><p>Flashlights (spare batteries?)</p></li>
<li><p>Emergency tool kit (pliers, hammer, rope, screwdriver, pry bar, etc)</p></li>
<li><p>GPS</p></li>
<li><p>Signaling device (Garmin InReach, Motorola Defy Satellite Link, or similar) if going to an area without good cell coverage</p></li>
<li><p>Trip plan (let someone know where you are, when you’ll be back, how often you’ll check in)</p></li>
</ul>
<p><strong>Handling problems when or after they arise</strong></p>
<ul>
<li><p>Reach out to the head or associate heads</p></li>
<li><p>Title IX (for sexual harassment, stalking, or similar): <a href="https://titleix.utk.edu/" class="uri">https://titleix.utk.edu/</a></p></li>
<li><p>Office of Equity and Diversity (racism, sexism, accessibility): <a href="https://oed.utk.edu/" class="uri">https://oed.utk.edu/</a></p></li>
<li><p>Office of Environmental Health &amp; Safety (emergency response, safety issues): <a href="https://ehs.utk.edu/" class="uri">https://ehs.utk.edu/</a></p></li>
<li><p>Ombudsperson (confidential advice): <a href="https://ombuds.utk.edu/" class="uri">https://ombuds.utk.edu/</a></p></li>
<li><p>Office of Research Integrity (authorship conflicts, responsible conduct of research): <a href="https://research.utk.edu/research-integrity/" class="uri">https://research.utk.edu/research-integrity/</a></p></li>
<li><p>NSF hotline: <a href="https://oig.nsf.gov/contact/hotline" class="uri">https://oig.nsf.gov/contact/hotline</a></p></li>
</ul>
<hr>
<p>To subscribe, go to <a href="https://brianomeara.info/blog.xml" class="uri">https://brianomeara.info/blog.xml</a> in an RSS reader.</p>



<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-citation"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Citation</h2><div><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">BibTeX citation:</div><pre class="sourceCode code-with-copy quarto-appendix-bibtex"><code class="sourceCode bibtex">@online{o'meara2024,
  author = {O’Meara, Brian},
  title = {Field {Safety}},
  date = {2024-05-08},
  url = {https://brianomeara.info/posts/fieldsafety/},
  langid = {en}
}
</code></pre><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">For attribution, please cite this work as:</div><div id="ref-o'meara2024" class="csl-entry quarto-appendix-citeas">
O’Meara, Brian. 2024. <span>“Field Safety.”</span> May 8, 2024. <a href="https://brianomeara.info/posts/fieldsafety/">https://brianomeara.info/posts/fieldsafety/</a>.
</div></div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>field safety</category>
  <category>fieldwork</category>
  <category>safety</category>
  <category>NSF</category>
  <category>inclusion</category>
  <guid>https://brianomeara.info/posts/fieldsafety/</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 08 May 2024 04:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Dentist for likelihood</title>
  <dc:creator>Brian O&#39;Meara</dc:creator>
  <link>https://brianomeara.info/posts/dentist/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>If you want to estimate the uncertainty in parameter estimates, including potential correlation issues between parameters, you can use our new package <code>dentist</code> (<a href="https://doi.org/10.1111/2041-210X.14297">Boyko and O’Meara, 2024</a>). It can take a function that computes a likelihood and explore parameters around it to get uncertainty, including varying by multiple parameters at once to help detect ridges.</p>
<p>If you don’t know <em>why</em> you want this, read on.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://brianomeara.info/posts/dentist/images/Fig3b.png" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Two univariate scatterplots showing a mixture of black points near the optimum and gray further out. It also has a bivariate plot showing a tilted ellipse with black points in the good enough region."></p>
<figcaption>Figure 3b from the <a href="https://doi.org/10.1111/2041-210X.14297">dentist</a> paper, showing the focal region in black, maximum likelihood estimate in red, and other sampled points too far from the optimum in gray</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>There are many R functions that use likelihood to fit models (<code>OUwie</code>, <code>geiger</code>, <code>corHMM</code>, <code>phytools</code>, and many more), which are often compared with measures like the Akaike Information Criterion (AIC). Jeremy Beaulieu and I (among <em>many</em> others) have long pushed for for people to focus on parameter estimates rather than just which model fits best. An Ornstein-Uhlenbeck model with two optima might fit better than a model with one, but while it is statistically supported it might not be biologically very relevant if the optima are close and the tip values range much more widely due to a low pull parameter. If different species range in size from 2 to 30 mm, two optima of 5 and 7 mm rather than one of 6 mm might not matter much in practice.</p>
<p>But even when people report parameter estimates, they often don’t report uncertainty in those estimates. This is deeply weird. We’re used to seeing “42 (CI 37-52) mm” or “42 ± 9 mm” but in comparative methods, people will only report “42 mm” (or, more commonly, “42” since we often omit units, too?!).</p>
<p>A major reason for this is lack of tools. Some software does not calculate uncertainty at all. Some does, but only using an approximation of curvature at the peak itself (methods using the Hessian). Others do it with a Bayesian approach, which has some advantages, but requires setting a prior, and which can hide ridges in the likelihood surface if the prior is uniform, lognormal, normal, exponential, or anything else that is not perfectly flat for all values.</p>
<p>Dentist is a new approach. It has something of the feel of MCMC, but rather than traversing a surface of likelihood times prior, it explores a “dented” likelihood surface to find the contour with points far enough from the optimum to represent a confidence interval. Imagine a likelihood surface is a mountain peak; we dent it so that it looks like a crater, and we try to find the rim. We have algorithms to do this with different kinds of moves if needed.</p>
<p>When it is done, the user gets not only the best parameter estimate but also a visualization of the confidence region around this space and a table with the parameter bounds. They can thus see ridges, as well as get a good estimate based on looking at the actual surface rather than just an estimate at the discovered peak.</p>
<p>For more details on why to use it, how to use it, and how it can fail, please see the <a href="https://doi.org/10.1111/2041-210X.14297">paper</a>.</p>
<p>It was a joy working with James Boyko on this. He was essential for pushing it forward, testing methods, writing, and so much more.</p>
<p>Our paper has the usual boilerplate about thanking the reviewers and associate editor (Natalie Cooper). But in this case it is genuine. The paper, and method, improved through peer review (most essentially by encouraging us to let the threshold be set based on the number of parameters rather than left entirely up to the users, but in other ways, too, including pushing us to compare more directly with other approaches). There are lots of issues with peer review (biases in the reviews, unpaid expert efforts for obscenely profitable companies, delays in publication, impact selection, and more) but it really can help sometimes, as it did here.</p>
<p>And finally, thank you to the US National Science Foundation (grant DEB-1916539) and the Eric and Wendy Schmidt AI in Science Postdoctoral Fellowship, a Schmidt Futures programme.</p>
<hr>
<p>To subscribe, go to <a href="https://brianomeara.info/blog.xml" class="uri">https://brianomeara.info/blog.xml</a> in an RSS reader.</p>



<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-citation"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Citation</h2><div><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">BibTeX citation:</div><pre class="sourceCode code-with-copy quarto-appendix-bibtex"><code class="sourceCode bibtex">@online{o'meara2024,
  author = {O’Meara, Brian},
  title = {Dentist for Likelihood},
  date = {2024-02-29},
  url = {https://brianomeara.info/posts/dentist/},
  langid = {en}
}
</code></pre><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">For attribution, please cite this work as:</div><div id="ref-o'meara2024" class="csl-entry quarto-appendix-citeas">
O’Meara, Brian. 2024. <span>“Dentist for Likelihood.”</span> February
29, 2024. <a href="https://brianomeara.info/posts/dentist/">https://brianomeara.info/posts/dentist/</a>.
</div></div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>R</category>
  <category>Rstats</category>
  <category>likelihood</category>
  <category>uncertainty</category>
  <category>publication</category>
  <guid>https://brianomeara.info/posts/dentist/</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 29 Feb 2024 05:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
