<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss  xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" 
      xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" 
      xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" 
      xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" 
      version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>Brian O&#39;Meara</title>
<link>https://brianomeara.info/blog.html</link>
<atom:link href="https://brianomeara.info/blog.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
<description></description>
<generator>quarto-1.2.475</generator>
<lastBuildDate>Sat, 22 Apr 2023 04:00:00 GMT</lastBuildDate>
<item>
  <title>Fossils do not help fix diversification parameter estimates</title>
  <dc:creator>Brian O&#39;Meara</dc:creator>
  <link>https://brianomeara.info/posts/fossilsdonothelp/index.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p><em>[Note that while setting up my blog, I’m adding backdated posts so that RSS feeds will see them as appearing when they* should *have appeared, not when they were actually written. This post was written April 22, 2023]</em></p>
<p>Jeremy Beaulieu and I have a <a href="https://doi.org/10.1093/sysbio/syac049">paper</a> in <em>Systematic Biology</em> on the impact of fossils on estimating diversification rates. There has been a lot of interest in the fossilized birth-death process, FBD (<a href="https://doi-org.utk.idm.oclc.org/10.1016/j.jtbi.2010.09.010">Stadler 2010</a>), and with the rediscovery in the field that diversification methods might be telling tales signifying nothing, Jeremy and I thought about how the FBD might help. We know fossils help, a lot, with things like ancestral state reconstruction and dating trees: knowing about fossils might help with diversification processes (especially with parameters relating to extinction).</p>
<p>Jeremy implemented it in <a href="https://speciationextinction.info/"><em>hisse</em></a>. One thing we discussed in the implementation is how there are two kinds of fossils FBD uses:</p>
<p><img src="https://brianomeara.info/posts/fossilsdonothelp/fbd_fig1.png" class="img-fluid" alt="Figure 1 from Beaulieu and O'Meara (2022), showing the distribution of fossils on two trees. The left tree shows the sampled fossils; the right plot shows the distinction between parent fossils (ones that have a descendant sample, either a fossil or a tip) and childless fossils (terminal fossils)."></p>
<p>One is terminals that are fossils with no sampled descendants (‘<em>m</em>’ type). The other is parent fossils (‘<em>k</em>’ type): they have a sampled descendant on the tree (which could be a fossil or extant tip). We worried that the methods assume equal probability of sampling for all these fossils, but that empiricists might not be generating data that meet these assumptions. For example, one might put a single <em>T. rex</em> fossil specimen on the tree, but would one put on every individual? All but the most recent one would be parent fossils, and we suspected they could be missing.</p>
<p>We made predictions based on the math, but it’s also useful to test with simulations. Simulations can be tricky when testing models: all models are simplifications of the world that can fail if the world is complex in the wrong ways. One can always write “method X fails under real world conditions Y” if conditions are extreme enough, but that doesn’t necessarily mean that it will fail in everyday use. So in setting up our simulations for this study, we chose to make it biased towards FBD working and based on realistic parameters. One way we biased it was including mass extinctions: methods using only tip data should do terribly for that, and fossils might help.</p>
<p>The key result is in Figure 4:</p>
<p><img src="https://brianomeara.info/posts/fossilsdonothelp/fbd_fig4b.png" class="img-fluid" alt="Figure 4b from Beaulieu and O'Meara (2022), showing the estimated turnover rate with different true turnover rates and different way of running the analysis. It shows a grouping of box plots, with red lines showing the true values. Using extant data only performed far better than using extant with sampled fossil tips; using all the parent and terminal fossils performed about as well as no fossils at all."></p>
<p>Using just the extant tips (dark purple) performed better than using extant tips and fossil tips (white bars) and similarly to using all the fossils, which based on limited data (see our Figure 3) is rarely done empirically. This surprised us: we were expecting fossils to pretty clearly help except when there was a bias to only use tip fossils. It is frankly a little disappointing that even perfect fossil data (we assumed fossil positions were known exactly, for example) does not help noticeably with estimating diversification models (though they remain important for dating, for ancestral state reconstruction, and likely for tree inference, as well).</p>
<p>To see all the code we used, go to https://github.com/thej022214/Fossils_impact_BO .</p>
<p>To see how to use fossils in <em>hisse</em>, including in models with and without traits, look at Jeremy’s vignette: https://speciationextinction.info/articles/adding_fossils.html . Based on our analysis, fossils don’t help much with diversification, but you can prove us wrong for your data, and you can use these tools for things like looking at correlations where fossils might indeed help.</p>



<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Citation</h2><div><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">BibTeX citation:</div><pre class="sourceCode code-with-copy quarto-appendix-bibtex"><code class="sourceCode bibtex">@online{o'meara2023,
  author = {Brian O’Meara},
  title = {Fossils Do Not Help Fix Diversification Parameter Estimates},
  date = {2023-04-22},
  url = {https://brianomeara.info/posts/fossilsdonothelp},
  langid = {en}
}
</code></pre><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">For attribution, please cite this work as:</div><div id="ref-o'meara2023" class="csl-entry quarto-appendix-citeas">
Brian O’Meara. 2023. <span>“Fossils Do Not Help Fix Diversification
Parameter Estimates.”</span> April 22, 2023. <a href="https://brianomeara.info/posts/fossilsdonothelp">https://brianomeara.info/posts/fossilsdonothelp</a>.
</div></div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>fossil</category>
  <category>R</category>
  <category>hisse</category>
  <category>misse</category>
  <category>diversification</category>
  <category>simulation</category>
  <category>publication</category>
  <guid>https://brianomeara.info/posts/fossilsdonothelp/index.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Sat, 22 Apr 2023 04:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://brianomeara.info/posts/fossilsdonothelp/fbd_fig1.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="81" width="144"/>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
