<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss  xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" 
      xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" 
      xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" 
      xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" 
      version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>Brian O&#39;Meara</title>
<link>https://brianomeara.info/blog.html</link>
<atom:link href="https://brianomeara.info/blog.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
<description></description>
<generator>quarto-1.6.40</generator>
<lastBuildDate>Sun, 04 May 2025 04:00:00 GMT</lastBuildDate>
<item>
  <title>Funding for tenure</title>
  <dc:creator>Brian O&#39;Meara</dc:creator>
  <link>https://brianomeara.info/posts/fundingfortenure/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>In the US, science funding is being cut, including the elimination of entire areas of study from federal funding. There are predictions of yet more reductions. This will affect what will be studied, who can study it, and even who survive diseases. Various individuals and groups are working to address this. I want to address just one small part of this where faculty still have (some) control: criteria we use in awarding tenure.</p>
<p>The standards for tenure can be opaque to various degrees: we all do teaching, research, and service, and institutions vary in how they weight each of these within the institution and across faculty members. Institutions vary in what constitutes evidence for each. For example, one person might teach a large number of intro classes and have peer evaluation of their teaching, while at a different institution someone may teach a few small enrollment classes and be evaluated on how well they are mentoring grad students. The AAUP has a <a href="https://www.aaup.org/report/2022-aaup-survey-tenure-practices">survey</a> of tenure practices, a quarter-century old <a href="https://www.aaup.org/sites/default/files/files/Good%20Practice%20in%20Tenure%20Evaluation.pdf">book</a> about best practices (probably due for some updating), and a <a href="https://www.aaup.org/issues/tenure/resources-tenure">page</a> aggregating additional resources for those seeking to learn more.</p>
<p>But imagine if a department had a standard for tenure of using 10,000 pipette tips. Each time you finish a box of tips, you put an empty box against the wall: only 105 boxes total to get to tenure! Of course, this doesn’t work for people doing bird banding, or theoretical ecology, or any of a myriad of research programs. Pipette tips are a tool, not a goal. Within a narrow area they might be an okay proxy for productivity: back when I was <a href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/nuccore/?term=brian+o%27meara">sequencing ant DNA</a> my pipette box accumulation rate could have been a good way to spot check how much time I was spending in the ant lab. But it would have been a terrible way to measure how much work I was spending coding new methods or writing papers. And using tips as a criterion could warp the research program: instead of banding birds, someone might have to change the research to do blood draws on captured birds to have a wet lab component, just in order to use enough tips to get tenure.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://brianomeara.info/posts/fundingfortenure/emptyboxes.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Stack of about forty empty pipette boxes: navy blue boxes, most for 200 µl pipette tips, with opaque white covers, in a wood cabinet."></p>
<figcaption>Enough boxes to be 38% of the way to tenure? Photo from <a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/labrats/comments/nvzy6b/what_on_earth_do_you_do_with_your_empty_tip_boxes/">reddit user strawspiderflower.</a></figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>I suggest funding is the same. It is a <em>tool</em> that enables research, outreach, and more, but it <em>isn’t the goal itself</em>. It’s fantastically useful, of course. I’ve been lucky to work with 17 postdocs so far as a mentor, all of whom needed money for things like food and health care: about half the time, that came from grants I wrote, with the rest of the time coming from grants written by others (thanks, NSF, and the UTK team who wrote the <a href="https://legacy.nimbios.org/about/impact">NIMBioS (National Institute for Mathematical and Biological Synthesis)</a> grant!). Other people need funding to pay for sequencing, or to fly to Costa Rica to collect insects, or to get a LI-COR to measure leaf respiration. And different research requires different amounts of funding – someone collecting fossils in the Arctic is not a better scientist than someone collecting fossils ten miles away from campus, but the former requires more money (and is generally less accessible to students). If both scientists are publishing good work at the same rate, why do we care that one person had to rent a helicopter and another a bicycle? It gets even more stark between fields: someone doing mathematical models may need far less funding than someone working on cancer research in a general biology department, and they also have access to different funding sources (at least historically, NIH provided more money than NSF), but the department is better for having both of them in the same place.</p>
<p>This is a time when there is even less reason to judge people by their funding. Federal funders and others have been cutting off funding for entire subfields. Faculty are pivoting their science to be able to keep doing work that matters. We want to encourage this: let them grow their research program and adapt to the changing world (this does not mean not trying to make improvements, but it does recognize external constraints). Having a performance standard that is based on the quality of science they are communicating makes sense. Adding a second metric, funding, warps that. In evolutionary biology, we teach about tradeoffs: armor is great, so is flight, but we don’t have flying armored turtles. Funding can serve the science, but making it a criterion in itself creates potential tradeoffs between the best science to do and the best science to get funding.</p>
<p><strong>Suggested action item</strong>: Departments should have conversations about criteria for tenure, and explictly discuss, and put in writing, that funding is NOT one of those criteria. Ideally, this should be put into departmental bylaws. The end of the semester is a hard time for this, but faculty are going to be trying to figure out what to do this summer: giving them reassurance about optimizing just for good science will let them focus on this. For some, this will require figuring out funding, but not for all. When people come back together in the Fall, bylaws that mention funding should be amended, as well as similar work at higher levels of an institution. There might be work that correlates with funding (Has a faculty member been able to recruit and mentor grad students? Have they been able to develop modern, publishable datasets?) but <em>the work</em> is what we care about, not the funding itself.</p>
<section id="what-about-indirect-costs-startup-etc." class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="what-about-indirect-costs-startup-etc.">What about indirect costs, startup, etc.?</h3>
<p>An objection to ignoring funding as a criterion for tenure is that grants are ways to support other aspects of the university. It is worth digging into the details of this, though.</p>
<p>First, though it’s an imperfect analogy, it can be worth comparing a new lab to a new coffee shop. To start up a coffee shop, one needs to get a building, equipment, and supplies: everything from flour to make the donuts to a soap dispenser in the bathroom to cups for the coffee. Then one needs to hire and train staff. Only then can one open for business and start making money. For example, for a <a href="https://finance.yahoo.com/news/much-costs-own-starbucks-franchise-180021683.html">Starbucks</a>, it costs $315,000 to license a store (which includes some equipment) and one must have $700,000 in cash for other costs. [Note I really wanted to find the similar cost for the far superior Dunkin’ Donuts instead, but it’s not available]. That’s the same order of magnitude as starting a biology lab at a research-intensive university, where startups in the hundreds of thousands of dollars are common.</p>
<p>One question any business owner has to face is how much to price each item. There’s the obvious cost of ingredients; there’s also the fractional cost of the employee that makes the coffee: a fancier coffee takes more time and so should cost more. But there are other costs that are harder to calculate. What fraction of a light bulb’s lifespan is used to illuminate the coffee station where the coffee is made? How much of the cash register’s overall cost is each cup of coffee responsible for? What about the person working the cash register? One way to do this would be to measure this exactly for everything: “hot tea” takes less time to say than “regular coffee black with two sugars” so the latter costs more of the cashier’s time. A different approach would be to figure out the obvious costs for the ingredients and direct labor, figure out all the other costs for the entire store, and find a ratio that makes it break even with a little extra for profit. For example, if a small cup of coffee costs $1.00 to make, add 50% to the cost of that to cover all the other costs and charge $1.50; maybe bump it up to $1.59 for a little profit.</p>
<p>The same applies for a lab. If one is proposing a project to sequence ant DNA to infer their phylogeny, there’s the cost to go to collect the ants in the field, the DNA extraction kits, PCR reagents, sequencing costs, and more. There’s the cost for the grad student to do the work (stipend, health care, and tuition). These are all calculated ahead of time and charged to the funder. But there are also all the other costs: someone to make sure the lab is run safely, having a building to do the work in, paying to run the -80 ˚C freezer, and more. Rather than figuring out these costs per project, the institution where the work happens negotiates with the federal government about the average overall costs. At a university, every $100 of direct cost might mean $50-60 in indirect costs, so that can be the negotiated rate. For institutions like children’s hospitals, it can be even higher, like <a href="https://www.childrenshospital.org/sites/default/files/2024-09/BCH%20RATE%20AGREEMENT_03.18.24.pdf">78%</a> at Children’s Hospital Boston.</p>
<p>The thing is, the folk wisdom about this (backed by research: <a href="https://pmc.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/articles/PMC3987954/">Holbrook and Sanberg (2013)</a>) is that universities lose money on this. The indirect costs do not quite cover the cost of the research. In some ways, this is like athletics programs: they only <a href="https://sportsdata.usatoday.com/ncaa/finances">rarely</a> make money, but they help with brand recognition, student spirit, and more. Research is even more central to the mission of a university – universities are about generating new knowledge and sharing it, and funded research is a major part of this. Overall amount of research expenditure is also a metric used in rating or categorizing universities – it looks “good” by metrics some care about to have a lot of research expenditure.</p>
<p>Moreover, just in terms of earnings per square foot, research labs are a spectacularly bad way to make money. Take the University of Florida, a major research university. As of the latest data (2023), it had <a href="https://ncses.nsf.gov/surveys/science-engineering-research-facilities/2023#survey-info">3,884,000 square feet</a> for research and engineering; it also spent (from external funds) <a href="https://ncsesdata.nsf.gov/profiles/site?method=rankingbysource&amp;ds=herd">$1,250,201,000</a>, for an average of $322 per square foot. A Starbucks has sales of $700/sqft, McDonald’s $2196/sqft, an Apple store $25,000/sqft, and even Walmart is $407/sqft (from <a href="https://www.analystinterview.com/article/understanding-sales-per-square-foot-a-key-metric-in-retail-food-and-beverages">here</a>, which is not peer-reviewed). And consider the cost to run a Walmart compared to a bunch of labs with the same total amount of square footage: Walmart has no fume hoods, no centrifuges, few expensive freezers, minimal computers, etc. and yet it only makes about 3% profit on this earnings per square foot. Walmart’s earnings for this space are 25% higher than what U. of Florida brings in with grants – it is hard to imagine U. of Florida is breaking even at this rate (and that is before proposed cuts in indirect rates). But the university is fostering <a href="https://explore.research.ufl.edu">great research</a> that has both immediate impacts (<a href="https://news.ufl.edu/2025/01/citrus-greening-research/">helping citrus growers</a>) and long-term discoveries (<a href="https://explore.research.ufl.edu/secrets-of-the-sea.html">detecting wildlife with wisps of DNA in the ocean</a>) while also training students and postdocs as part of its educational mission. And this sort of contribution is common for the thousands of universities across the US.</p>
<p>So, TL;DR: any university is likely losing money on research in general; given the high variance in how much funding different research groups bring in, it is likely that nearly all individual labs are overall subsidized by the university (the “Use AI to find people who are bad credit risks” or the “Patent a banana that stays yellow for months” labs might be exceptions). Many people, even from “successful” labs (based on grants), are not bringing in enough funding to break even, but they are worth the investment due to their discoveries. Our institutions at a high level realize that the research is what matters and focus on that. For those of us who are even closer to the research, in the same departments as those doing the work, we should similarly value the quality of the work, not the money or other tools used to help achieve it. We must put in structural changes to reassure our junior colleagues that we will evaluate their work, not their funding, especially now.</p>
<hr>
<p>To subscribe, go to <a href="https://brianomeara.info/blog.xml" class="uri">https://brianomeara.info/blog.xml</a> in an RSS reader.</p>


</section>

<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-citation"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Citation</h2><div><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">BibTeX citation:</div><pre class="sourceCode code-with-copy quarto-appendix-bibtex"><code class="sourceCode bibtex">@online{o'meara2025,
  author = {O’Meara, Brian},
  title = {Funding for Tenure},
  date = {2025-05-04},
  url = {https://brianomeara.info/posts/fundingfortenure/},
  langid = {en}
}
</code></pre><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">For attribution, please cite this work as:</div><div id="ref-o'meara2025" class="csl-entry quarto-appendix-citeas">
O’Meara, Brian. 2025. <span>“Funding for Tenure.”</span> May 4, 2025. <a href="https://brianomeara.info/posts/fundingfortenure/">https://brianomeara.info/posts/fundingfortenure/</a>.
</div></div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>NSF</category>
  <category>NIH</category>
  <category>tenure</category>
  <category>funding</category>
  <category>indirect costs</category>
  <guid>https://brianomeara.info/posts/fundingfortenure/</guid>
  <pubDate>Sun, 04 May 2025 04:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>How long does balance in eponymous names require?</title>
  <dc:creator>Brian O&#39;Meara</dc:creator>
  <link>https://brianomeara.info/posts/eponymous_birds/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>Today I saw a <a href="https://bsky.app/profile/zoojlinnsoc.bsky.social/post/3llgxuqt7pg2x">post</a> on bluesky from the <em>Zoological Journal of the Linnean Society</em> about a <a href="https://doi.org/10.1093/zoolinnean/zlaf022">new paper</a> by Dr.&nbsp;George Sangster on eponyms in birds: naming birds after people. This is an issue I’ve been curious about for some time, partly due to the related issue of naming awards after people (see <a href="https://brianomeara.info/evol2023.html#award-naming">here</a>). Issues that come up in these areas are 1) should we name organisms after people who did awful things? 2) how extensive are the biases in who gets species named after them? 3) what are the effects of either of the above on recruiting and retainng people in the field? and 4) how will changes in naming practices, both moving forward and (more controversially) changing existing names affect the above three points? The paper represents a tremendous amount of careful work to address the second question, including an analysis of how the biases have changed over time.</p>
<p>The <a href="https://doi.org/10.1093/zoolinnean/zlaf022">paper</a> is well worth reading and contributes greatly to this discussion. However, I was a bit surprised by one of its conclusions:</p>
<p>“Importantly, there is no need for drastic changes in naming practices, because the desired changes (greater representation of women and non-western people) are already taking place (and have been for several decades).”</p>
<p>The paper does identify trends in this direction, but I was curious about how long the changes would require. Dr.&nbsp;Sangster generously released the analyzed data as a supplemental file, so I downloaded it to run some analyses. It already had some linear regressions showing changes in representation since 1900; I threw the file into R to do similar analyses, but extrapolating to the future.</p>
<section id="proportionality-in-new-names" class="level2" data-number="1">
<h2 data-number="1" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="proportionality-in-new-names"><span class="header-section-number">1</span> Proportionality in new names</h2>
<p>The first question is how long with current trends it will take for a proportional fraction of the eponymous names to be named after people in the different groups. For gender, if we limit the population of potential namesakes to women and men only, and assume they are equal frequencies in the population, parity is at 50%. For Western vs non-Western, one standard would also be 50%; a better one might be to use proportion of the world population that is Western vs non-Western (though this has also changed over time). Using populations sizes from <a href="https://www.worldometers.info/world-population/">here</a>, and adopting the definition of Western the paper seemed to use, 85.8% of people are non-Western.</p>
<p>Using these thresholds and linear regression, with a 95% confidence interval:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Year when half of NEW eponyms are named for women: 2340 (2220, 2662)</strong></li>
<li><strong>Year when half of NEW eponyms are named for non-Western people: 2101 (2070, 2156)</strong></li>
<li><strong>Year when a proportional number of NEW eponyms are named for non-Western people: 2255 (2191, 2367)</strong></li>
</ul>
<p>So, it will take 315 years to have equal representation of women in new eponyms, and 230 years to have proportional representation of non-Western people, under the current yearly increase in representation in names taxonomists choose. This is about as far in the future as Linneaus was in the past. That’s a long time.</p>
<p>Below are some plots showing the extrapolations. Clearly, extrapolating out this far is silly: but the big point is that even with current trends it’s going to take a very, very long time.</p>
<p><img src="https://brianomeara.info/posts/eponymous_birds/women_future.jpg" class="img-fluid" alt="Scatter plot showing the proportion of women in eponymous names over time, with a linear regression line showing the trend. A dotted line shows the 50% value, which is not reached until far in the future."></p>
<p><img src="https://brianomeara.info/posts/eponymous_birds/nonwestern_future.jpg" class="img-fluid" alt="Scatter plot showing the proportion of non-Western people in eponymous names over time, with a linear regression line showing the trend. A dotted line shows the 50% value and the 85% values."></p>
</section>
<section id="proportionality-in-all-names" class="level2" data-number="2">
<h2 data-number="2" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="proportionality-in-all-names"><span class="header-section-number">2</span> Proportionality in all names</h2>
<p>A different question is how long it will take for half of the eponymous bird species to be named after women, and how long it will take for the proportion of eponymous names for non-Western people to be equal to their population. One issue is that birds are a well-studied group: the number of new species being described is declining (though not an argument for lack of a need for more taxonomy):</p>
<p><img src="https://brianomeara.info/posts/eponymous_birds/new_birds.jpg" class="img-fluid" alt="Scatter plot showing the number of new bird species described over time, with a linear regression line and smooth regression line showing the trend after 1900."></p>
<p>An extrapolation into the future quickly results in having a negative number of newly described species in future years. I instead used a more optimistic assumption that the future will resemble the 10 year average of the most recent years in the dataset, so with 16.7 species described per year.</p>
<p>We can see how the number of species named after women, men, Westerners, and non-Westerners has changed over time up to the present:</p>
<p><img src="https://brianomeara.info/posts/eponymous_birds/full_predictions_present.jpg" class="img-fluid" alt="Line plot showing the number of eponymous names over time. Men and Western are very similar (since they were the vast majority of people having species named after them) but the rate has slowed down; Women and non-Western people are increasing, but the number of such species is still far lower than for the first two groups."></p>
<p>And then we can continue the trend into the future, incorporating the increasing proportion of species named for women and non-Western people but also the trend of a greater proportion of eponyms overall (which I was surprised to learn about in the original paper). I ran the model for a thousand years into the future:</p>
<p><img src="https://brianomeara.info/posts/eponymous_birds/full_predictions_future.jpg" class="img-fluid" alt="Line plot showing the number of eponymous names over time from 1758 to 3025. Lines for Men and Westerners continue to be well above the lines for Women and non-Westerners for the duration of the plot."></p>
<p>So at least over the next thousand years, eponymous bird names will not reach parity with human population proportions for the groups analyzed in this paper.</p>
</section>
<section id="conclusions" class="level2" data-number="3">
<h2 data-number="3" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="conclusions"><span class="header-section-number">3</span> Conclusions</h2>
<p>Taxonomy works on long time scales. But if having more representative names is considered important, business as usual, even with trends for more inclusive naming practices, are at best centuries from reaching parity for new names and may never reach it for all names in birds.</p>
</section>
<section id="analysis-code" class="level2" data-number="4">
<h2 data-number="4" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="analysis-code"><span class="header-section-number">4</span> Analysis code</h2>
<p>This was all done in R using the packages <code>targets</code>, <code>tidyverse</code>, <code>ggplot2</code>, <code>readxl</code>, <code>ggpmisc</code>, <code>stringr</code>, <code>ggrepel</code>, and <code>RColorBrewer</code>. Source code is at <a href="https://github.com/bomeara/eponymous_birds" class="uri">https://github.com/bomeara/eponymous_birds</a>.</p>
</section>
<section id="acknowledgements" class="level2" data-number="5">
<h2 data-number="5" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="acknowledgements"><span class="header-section-number">5</span> Acknowledgements</h2>
<p>Thank you to Dr.&nbsp;Sangster for the detailed work on this important issue, for writing a compelling paper, and for making the data so available. Again, I encourage you to read <a href="https://doi.org/10.1093/zoolinnean/zlaf022">this work</a> for its insights.</p>
<hr>
<p>To subscribe, go to <a href="https://brianomeara.info/blog.xml" class="uri">https://brianomeara.info/blog.xml</a> in an RSS reader.</p>


</section>

<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-citation"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Citation</h2><div><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">BibTeX citation:</div><pre class="sourceCode code-with-copy quarto-appendix-bibtex"><code class="sourceCode bibtex">@online{o'meara2025,
  author = {O’Meara, Brian},
  title = {How Long Does Balance in Eponymous Names Require?},
  date = {2025-03-28},
  url = {https://brianomeara.info/posts/eponymous_birds/},
  langid = {en}
}
</code></pre><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">For attribution, please cite this work as:</div><div id="ref-o'meara2025" class="csl-entry quarto-appendix-citeas">
O’Meara, Brian. 2025. <span>“How Long Does Balance in Eponymous Names
Require?”</span> March 28, 2025. <a href="https://brianomeara.info/posts/eponymous_birds/">https://brianomeara.info/posts/eponymous_birds/</a>.
</div></div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>taxonomy</category>
  <category>birds</category>
  <category>rstats</category>
  <guid>https://brianomeara.info/posts/eponymous_birds/</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 28 Mar 2025 04:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Uncertainty and risk</title>
  <dc:creator>Brian O&#39;Meara</dc:creator>
  <link>https://brianomeara.info/posts/uncertaintyandrisk/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>As I write this (Jan 31, 2025), it is an odd time. The new US presidential administration cut off disbursement of most federal funds; a court order then stayed this, and the memo pausing disbursement was retracted, but there is still an argument as to whether funds may flow. Regardless, the National Science Foundation is still not disbursing funds, even to PRFB postdocs who rely on requested withdrawals to be paid (even requests from last week are not being processed). There is an “updated often” <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20250131165539/https://new.nsf.gov/executive-orders">page</a> from NSF that hasn’t changed in a couple of days. It’s not clear when or if funding will resume, nor what programs, if any, might be cut. Some colleges have told people to rein in expenditures, others just to limit expenditures that might violate an executive order, some have said change nothing in how funds should be used.</p>
<p>In the meantime, on social media there are many splashy advertisements to recruit students for NSF-sponsored research experiences for undergrads (REUs). These can be transformative: undergrads are supported over a summer to do new research they drive, often surrounded by strong mentoring and other support structures. If a student takes this, it replaces essentially a summer job or other internship.</p>
<p>This is also a time when grad recruiting is happening: some programs are flying students out for interviews and visits. In the sciences, generally students are both admitted to a program <strong>and</strong> offered a job as a teaching assistant or research assistant; the job pays tuition, offers healthcare, and gives a student a stipend. TAs are generally centrally funded: there must be people to run discussion sections or labs, and so departments get a certain number of lines to staff their classes. The funding for these will generally come out of university funds, a mixture of tuition and perhaps state support or endowment funds. RAs are generally funded by external grants (with some exceptions). If an RA dries up, a student might then be put on a TA line.</p>
<p>The uncertainty is what happens to REUs and RA lines in the future. It could be that everything reverts to how it was: it is a rigorous process to select what the government will fund (with the vast majority of proposals being rejected), using criteria that were passed into law and have been stable for many years, and so changing them, especially on already awarded funds, might not take place (and there are legal and prudential arguments for such an outcome). The other extreme is that all current NSF funding is cut, eliminating REUs and RAs entirely, and even existing TAs might be needed for current grad students on an RA. Or it could be something in between. There is nothing public that is definitive either way. And even if we had perfect knowledge of current plans, that is of only modest predictive value: maybe a lawsuit stops one intended outcome, maybe another Sputnik moment leads to an <em>increase</em> in funding. We just can’t know, and that may go on for a while.</p>
<section id="what-we-can-do" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="what-we-can-do">What we can do</h3>
<p>There are lots of discussions about what various external actors should be doing with this; a thing we have control of is <strong>how we handle this uncertainty</strong>. A big part of that is deciding <strong>who inherits the risk</strong> and <strong>how the risk is communicated</strong>.</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Business as usual</strong> <em>(high student risk, low university risk, max opportunities)</em>: For example, one approach is to assume things continue as before: anything with allocated or promised funding will continue to receive funds. Offers are made to an REU or grad school, likely with a small parenthetical statement on “(subject to availability of funds),” and students jump at the offered chance and get rid of their other options. This is optimal for the REU or grad program: if all goes well, great students sign up early, so the grant or the RA line is filled with strong candidates. If funds do go away, the students are out of a job and have to scramble, but the program itself is fine – no loss of money. This maximizes risk to students. It also incentivizes minimizing communication of risk so students feel safe signing up early. But students are in a very poor position to understand risk: if faculty and administrators don’t know what is going on, what chance does a sophomore applying to an REU or a senior applying for a grad program have?</li>
<li><strong>University steps up</strong> <em>(low student risk, high university risk, min opportunities)</em>: A different approach would be to have the university assume the risk. Make the offers, but if funding does not arrive, the university takes on the burden of supporting the students. This is a major risk to the university, but the university at least has better ways to assess risk (through connections to lobbyists, legislators, etc.) than a bunch of undergrads do. A university also likely has a much fatter savings account (endowment) than students, though often with contraints on how it can be spent. Besides the risk to the university, this does also lead to fewer opportunities: the university might be able to support only half the enrollment a grant would, so fewer students get an offer.</li>
<li><strong>Max transparency</strong> <em>(low student risk, moderate university risk, moderate opportunities)</em>: An intermediate approach would be maximal communication. Be very up front about risks to funding and that, even if the program wants to admit them, students should keep a backup plan up to some reasonable date. One approach to this, borrowed from college athletics, could be letters of intent. “We intend to admit you to our REU / grad program with this offer, but cannot formally promise this until [some date].” Then, when funding is assured or the university is comfortable assuming the risk for the student, send a formal offer of admissions. The risk is that “good” students might go to a university adopting the first approach (“I have a letter of intent from you, but they gave me an offer [with an asterisk I missed], so I’m going there”); the benefit is that it’s possible that there are more students admitted than under approach two. It’s also less dishonest than the first approach (which does not exactly lie, but is far from forthcoming about possibilities).</li>
</ul>
<p>This is likely to be a long period of uncertainty, with a lot of focus on what people can do to change things at national levels. But we do have (more) control on what we do within our own institutions. We will need to continually ask ourselves who we are helping, who we are putting at risk, and how we can be honest about this. This is on us.</p>
<hr>
<p>To subscribe, go to <a href="https://brianomeara.info/blog.xml" class="uri">https://brianomeara.info/blog.xml</a> in an RSS reader.</p>


</section>

<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-citation"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Citation</h2><div><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">BibTeX citation:</div><pre class="sourceCode code-with-copy quarto-appendix-bibtex"><code class="sourceCode bibtex">@online{o'meara2025,
  author = {O’Meara, Brian},
  title = {Uncertainty and Risk},
  date = {2025-01-31},
  url = {https://brianomeara.info/posts/uncertaintyandrisk/},
  langid = {en}
}
</code></pre><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">For attribution, please cite this work as:</div><div id="ref-o'meara2025" class="csl-entry quarto-appendix-citeas">
O’Meara, Brian. 2025. <span>“Uncertainty and Risk.”</span> January 31,
2025. <a href="https://brianomeara.info/posts/uncertaintyandrisk/">https://brianomeara.info/posts/uncertaintyandrisk/</a>.
</div></div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>NSF</category>
  <category>REU</category>
  <category>gradschool</category>
  <category>funding</category>
  <guid>https://brianomeara.info/posts/uncertaintyandrisk/</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 31 Jan 2025 05:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Field Safety</title>
  <dc:creator>Brian O&#39;Meara</dc:creator>
  <link>https://brianomeara.info/posts/fieldsafety/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>Over the 2023-2024 academic year, a committee in UTK EEB worked on field safety. This involves things like avoiding snakebite and traffic accidents (see Richard Conniff’s <a href="https://strangebehaviors.wordpress.com/2011/01/14/the-wall-of-the-dead/">memorial to fallen naturalists</a>) but also social factors. I am putting some information from this here to help others access it, but note it is a team effort.</p>
<p>We went through a set of readings. Some relevant ones in this area include:</p>
<ul>
<li>Demery &amp; Pipkin (2020): <a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/s41559-020-01328-5" class="uri">https://www.nature.com/articles/s41559-020-01328-5</a></li>
<li>Rudzki et al.&nbsp;(2022): <a href="https://besjournals.onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1111/2041-210X.13970" class="uri">https://besjournals.onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1111/2041-210X.13970</a></li>
<li>Blonder (2022): <a href="https://esajournals.onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/full/10.1002/bes2.2031" class="uri">https://esajournals.onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/full/10.1002/bes2.2031</a></li>
<li>Clancy et al.&nbsp;(2014): <a href="https://journals.plos.org/plosone/article?id=10.1371/journal.pone.0102172" class="uri">https://journals.plos.org/plosone/article?id=10.1371/journal.pone.0102172</a></li>
</ul>
<p>To help with this, several of us made a checklist. It is below. Feel free to adapt it for your own use.</p>
<p><strong>Work travel checklist</strong></p>
<p><strong>Discussions to have before going</strong></p>
<ul>
<li><p>Introductions between all participants</p></li>
<li><p>Comfort levels with risk, activities</p>
<ul>
<li>Discussing criteria for deciding when/if to end fieldwork; students (everyone) should be empowered to speak up about conditions and expectations</li>
</ul></li>
<li><p>Health needs, accessibility needs, safety needs of all participants, medication needs</p></li>
<li><p>Financial arrangements: how paying for things works in the field: who is paying for what and how</p></li>
<li><p>Housing arrangement discussions</p></li>
<li><p>Personal space, downtime, bathroom needs / procedures</p></li>
<li><p>Bathrooms: people should use the one they feel most comfortable with; it is no one on the team’s role to police others’ bathroom use. Note that various locations may have different policies; it is up to individuals to assess these for themselves.</p></li>
<li><p>Culture, language, and etiquette of the location, especially internationally</p></li>
<li><p>Weapons in the field</p>
<ul>
<li><p>People you will encounter in the field will be armed (and think about PTSD)</p></li>
<li><p>Note <a href="https://policy.tennessee.edu/policy/sa0875-firearms/">UTK firearms policy</a> if any participant may be considering carrying</p></li>
<li><p>UTK policies for weapons (e.g.&nbsp;knives, pepper spray): <a href="https://studentconduct.utk.edu/wp-content/uploads/sites/53/2021/08/2m3k1ac-Fall-StudentCodeOfConduct_WEB.pdf">UTK Student Code of Conduct</a>. Carrying a knife in the field can be useful if allowable</p></li>
<li><p>Note policies of various places about firearms (GSMNP does not allow firearms, for example)</p></li>
<li><p>Discuss safety in general</p></li>
</ul></li>
<li><p>Possible hazards at site</p>
<ul>
<li>List the ones possible: could be human factors (civil unrest), wildlife, falling branches, driving risks, etc.</li>
</ul></li>
</ul>
<p><strong>To resolve months in advance</strong></p>
<ul>
<li><p>Vaccination requirements</p></li>
<li><p>Research permits for site</p></li>
<li><p>Import permits</p></li>
<li><p>Chemical permits: look at EHS policies for chemical safety</p></li>
<li><p>Visas (note that participants may be citizens of different countries leading to different requirements)</p></li>
<li><p>State department guidelines for various countries</p></li>
<li><p>California travel warnings for certain states</p></li>
<li><p>LGBTQ travel advisories for non-US travel: <a href="https://travel.state.gov/content/travel/en/international-travel/before-you-go/travelers-with-special-considerations/lgbtqi.html" class="uri">https://travel.state.gov/content/travel/en/international-travel/before-you-go/travelers-with-special-considerations/lgbtqi.html</a></p></li>
<li><p>Travel insurance: <a href="https://cge.utk.edu/intlsos/" class="uri">https://cge.utk.edu/intlsos/</a> if university-sponsored travel (ask EEB for funding if you are paying on your own)</p></li>
<li><p>UTK travel authorization form (extra steps if international;​​ <a href="https://cge.utk.edu/travel/" class="uri">https://cge.utk.edu/travel/</a>)</p></li>
<li><p>Have discussion about health needs, accessibility needs, safety needs of all participants, medication needs</p></li>
<li><p>For air travel, documentation required for boarding (think about how equipment and chemicals will be shipped)</p></li>
<li><p>Request travel advance from the department</p></li>
</ul>
<p><strong>At least a month in advance of field work</strong></p>
<ul>
<li><p>Daily communication plan established</p></li>
<li><p>Hazard plan for each site established</p>
<ul>
<li><p>Consider all hazards, including but not limited to automobiles (wear seat belts!), landslides, flooding, volcanic eruptions, earthquakes, extreme heat, wildfires, civil unrest, protests, animals, plants, diseases, racism, sexism</p></li>
<li><p>Recreational hazards: swimming in ocean, ziplining, rafting, etc.</p></li>
</ul></li>
<li><p>Field research letter from the department</p></li>
<li><p>Notify residents near the field site about plans, get permissions if possible - in letter, email, phone, or go door to door</p></li>
<li><p>Check if site or travel route has a recent history of incidents - for example, is it a possible <a href="https://justice.tougaloo.edu/sundown-towns/using-the-sundown-towns-database/state-map/">sundown town</a>? What places are not safe to stop for gas?</p>
<ul>
<li>Check for short term events that may cause risks, delays, etc.: anything from a parade to roads washing out to an event that could get heated</li>
</ul></li>
<li><p>Assess need for satellite phones or other communication devices that work without cell service</p></li>
<li><p>Appropriate field clothing (footwear, sun protection)</p></li>
<li><p>Make sure there are enough vehicles (UTK fleet: <a href="https://fleetmanagement.utk.edu/" class="uri">https://fleetmanagement.utk.edu/</a>)</p></li>
<li><p>Get book of receipts (for buying things that don’t usually come with receipts)</p></li>
<li><p>Have protocol for saving receipts of all kinds</p></li>
<li><p>Consider travel advance, especially for longer trips.</p></li>
<li><p>Mileage logbook</p></li>
<li><p>List of emergency contacts, including:</p>
<ul>
<li><p>Local contact info for emergency assistance (911 isn’t global); International SOS card <a href="https://cge.utk.edu/intlsos/" class="uri">https://cge.utk.edu/intlsos/</a></p></li>
<li><p>Contacts of others on the trip</p></li>
<li><p>UTK assistance:</p>
<ul>
<li><p>Travel office</p></li>
<li><p>Title IX office (for harassment): <a href="https://titleix.utk.edu/" class="uri">https://titleix.utk.edu/</a></p></li>
<li><p>Workmans’ compensation (for getting coverage for injuries during work/travel): <a href="https://riskmanagement.tennessee.edu/workers-compensation/" class="uri">https://riskmanagement.tennessee.edu/workers-compensation/</a></p></li>
</ul></li>
</ul></li>
</ul>
<p><strong>Before leaving</strong></p>
<ul>
<li><p>Project specific equipment: personal gear, safety gear (hard hats, gloves, etc.), scientific equipment, sharpies, baggies, etc. Spell them all out as a separate checklist specific to this activity.</p></li>
<li><p>Cell phones charged</p></li>
<li><p>Chargers</p></li>
<li><p>Sufficient water <a href="https://www.rei.com/learn/expert-advice/hydrate.html">(0.5-1 liters per person per hour in the field)</a></p></li>
<li><p>First aid kit on board (comprehensive, not just bandaids. Handle sprains, pain, deep cuts, etc.)</p></li>
<li><p>Sunscreen</p></li>
<li><p>Car magnets</p></li>
<li><p>Food/snacks</p></li>
<li><p>Hygiene products</p>
<ul>
<li><p>Hand sanitizer</p></li>
<li><p>Soap</p></li>
<li><p>Toilet paper, trowel for digging hole (when allowed in the field)</p></li>
<li><p>Tampons/pads</p></li>
</ul></li>
<li><p>Personal medication (brought by each individual)</p>
<ul>
<li><p>Allergy medication</p></li>
<li><p>Painkillers</p></li>
<li><p>Digestive medications</p></li>
</ul></li>
<li><p>Flashlights (spare batteries?)</p></li>
<li><p>Emergency tool kit (pliers, hammer, rope, screwdriver, pry bar, etc)</p></li>
<li><p>GPS</p></li>
<li><p>Signaling device (Garmin InReach, Motorola Defy Satellite Link, or similar) if going to an area without good cell coverage</p></li>
<li><p>Trip plan (let someone know where you are, when you’ll be back, how often you’ll check in)</p></li>
</ul>
<p><strong>Handling problems when or after they arise</strong></p>
<ul>
<li><p>Reach out to the head or associate heads</p></li>
<li><p>Title IX (for sexual harassment, stalking, or similar): <a href="https://titleix.utk.edu/" class="uri">https://titleix.utk.edu/</a></p></li>
<li><p>Office of Equity and Diversity (racism, sexism, accessibility): <a href="https://oed.utk.edu/" class="uri">https://oed.utk.edu/</a></p></li>
<li><p>Office of Environmental Health &amp; Safety (emergency response, safety issues): <a href="https://ehs.utk.edu/" class="uri">https://ehs.utk.edu/</a></p></li>
<li><p>Ombudsperson (confidential advice): <a href="https://ombuds.utk.edu/" class="uri">https://ombuds.utk.edu/</a></p></li>
<li><p>Office of Research Integrity (authorship conflicts, responsible conduct of research): <a href="https://research.utk.edu/research-integrity/" class="uri">https://research.utk.edu/research-integrity/</a></p></li>
<li><p>NSF hotline: <a href="https://oig.nsf.gov/contact/hotline" class="uri">https://oig.nsf.gov/contact/hotline</a></p></li>
</ul>
<hr>
<p>To subscribe, go to <a href="https://brianomeara.info/blog.xml" class="uri">https://brianomeara.info/blog.xml</a> in an RSS reader.</p>



<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-citation"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Citation</h2><div><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">BibTeX citation:</div><pre class="sourceCode code-with-copy quarto-appendix-bibtex"><code class="sourceCode bibtex">@online{o'meara2024,
  author = {O’Meara, Brian},
  title = {Field {Safety}},
  date = {2024-05-08},
  url = {https://brianomeara.info/posts/fieldsafety/},
  langid = {en}
}
</code></pre><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">For attribution, please cite this work as:</div><div id="ref-o'meara2024" class="csl-entry quarto-appendix-citeas">
O’Meara, Brian. 2024. <span>“Field Safety.”</span> May 8, 2024. <a href="https://brianomeara.info/posts/fieldsafety/">https://brianomeara.info/posts/fieldsafety/</a>.
</div></div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>field safety</category>
  <category>fieldwork</category>
  <category>safety</category>
  <category>NSF</category>
  <category>inclusion</category>
  <guid>https://brianomeara.info/posts/fieldsafety/</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 08 May 2024 04:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Dentist for likelihood</title>
  <dc:creator>Brian O&#39;Meara</dc:creator>
  <link>https://brianomeara.info/posts/dentist/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>If you want to estimate the uncertainty in parameter estimates, including potential correlation issues between parameters, you can use our new package <code>dentist</code> (<a href="https://doi.org/10.1111/2041-210X.14297">Boyko and O’Meara, 2024</a>). It can take a function that computes a likelihood and explore parameters around it to get uncertainty, including varying by multiple parameters at once to help detect ridges.</p>
<p>If you don’t know <em>why</em> you want this, read on.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://brianomeara.info/posts/dentist/images/Fig3b.png" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Two univariate scatterplots showing a mixture of black points near the optimum and gray further out. It also has a bivariate plot showing a tilted ellipse with black points in the good enough region."></p>
<figcaption>Figure 3b from the <a href="https://doi.org/10.1111/2041-210X.14297">dentist</a> paper, showing the focal region in black, maximum likelihood estimate in red, and other sampled points too far from the optimum in gray</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>There are many R functions that use likelihood to fit models (<code>OUwie</code>, <code>geiger</code>, <code>corHMM</code>, <code>phytools</code>, and many more), which are often compared with measures like the Akaike Information Criterion (AIC). Jeremy Beaulieu and I (among <em>many</em> others) have long pushed for for people to focus on parameter estimates rather than just which model fits best. An Ornstein-Uhlenbeck model with two optima might fit better than a model with one, but while it is statistically supported it might not be biologically very relevant if the optima are close and the tip values range much more widely due to a low pull parameter. If different species range in size from 2 to 30 mm, two optima of 5 and 7 mm rather than one of 6 mm might not matter much in practice.</p>
<p>But even when people report parameter estimates, they often don’t report uncertainty in those estimates. This is deeply weird. We’re used to seeing “42 (CI 37-52) mm” or “42 ± 9 mm” but in comparative methods, people will only report “42 mm” (or, more commonly, “42” since we often omit units, too?!).</p>
<p>A major reason for this is lack of tools. Some software does not calculate uncertainty at all. Some does, but only using an approximation of curvature at the peak itself (methods using the Hessian). Others do it with a Bayesian approach, which has some advantages, but requires setting a prior, and which can hide ridges in the likelihood surface if the prior is uniform, lognormal, normal, exponential, or anything else that is not perfectly flat for all values.</p>
<p>Dentist is a new approach. It has something of the feel of MCMC, but rather than traversing a surface of likelihood times prior, it explores a “dented” likelihood surface to find the contour with points far enough from the optimum to represent a confidence interval. Imagine a likelihood surface is a mountain peak; we dent it so that it looks like a crater, and we try to find the rim. We have algorithms to do this with different kinds of moves if needed.</p>
<p>When it is done, the user gets not only the best parameter estimate but also a visualization of the confidence region around this space and a table with the parameter bounds. They can thus see ridges, as well as get a good estimate based on looking at the actual surface rather than just an estimate at the discovered peak.</p>
<p>For more details on why to use it, how to use it, and how it can fail, please see the <a href="https://doi.org/10.1111/2041-210X.14297">paper</a>.</p>
<p>It was a joy working with James Boyko on this. He was essential for pushing it forward, testing methods, writing, and so much more.</p>
<p>Our paper has the usual boilerplate about thanking the reviewers and associate editor (Natalie Cooper). But in this case it is genuine. The paper, and method, improved through peer review (most essentially by encouraging us to let the threshold be set based on the number of parameters rather than left entirely up to the users, but in other ways, too, including pushing us to compare more directly with other approaches). There are lots of issues with peer review (biases in the reviews, unpaid expert efforts for obscenely profitable companies, delays in publication, impact selection, and more) but it really can help sometimes, as it did here.</p>
<p>And finally, thank you to the US National Science Foundation (grant DEB-1916539) and the Eric and Wendy Schmidt AI in Science Postdoctoral Fellowship, a Schmidt Futures programme.</p>
<hr>
<p>To subscribe, go to <a href="https://brianomeara.info/blog.xml" class="uri">https://brianomeara.info/blog.xml</a> in an RSS reader.</p>



<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-citation"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Citation</h2><div><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">BibTeX citation:</div><pre class="sourceCode code-with-copy quarto-appendix-bibtex"><code class="sourceCode bibtex">@online{o'meara2024,
  author = {O’Meara, Brian},
  title = {Dentist for Likelihood},
  date = {2024-02-29},
  url = {https://brianomeara.info/posts/dentist/},
  langid = {en}
}
</code></pre><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">For attribution, please cite this work as:</div><div id="ref-o'meara2024" class="csl-entry quarto-appendix-citeas">
O’Meara, Brian. 2024. <span>“Dentist for Likelihood.”</span> February
29, 2024. <a href="https://brianomeara.info/posts/dentist/">https://brianomeara.info/posts/dentist/</a>.
</div></div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>R</category>
  <category>Rstats</category>
  <category>likelihood</category>
  <category>uncertainty</category>
  <category>publication</category>
  <guid>https://brianomeara.info/posts/dentist/</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 29 Feb 2024 05:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>13,000 page site with Rmarkdown and targets</title>
  <dc:creator>Brian O&#39;Meara</dc:creator>
  <link>https://brianomeara.info/posts/collegetables/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>Last year, one of my kids was a junior starting to look at colleges. Picking a college is a big deal; when I get stressed, I like data: my security blanket is a big matrix. There are sites that allow you to compare colleges, but they often use weird metrics (how do provosts rate other colleges), don’t often have a nice table for comparison (turns out some of them put public data behind a paywall, too), and omit some important information (are the instructors used in the student-to-instructor ratio tenure track faculty (who have stability in their jobs) or more contingent faculty who might have to scramble to make ends meet semester to semester?). So I decided to gather data: initially I just wanted to get a table, but then thought, well, it woudn’t be that much harder to put it online, and then… it snowballed into the current site at <a href="https://collegetables.info/" class="uri">https://collegetables.info/</a> with 13,424 pages (including one page for every college and every major). It also was featured in a <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2023/04/15/your-money/college-cost-data-tools.html?unlocked_article_code=hN2IwBdFONp5CmgbxhKM-HVUid0P2EEoomfIcGniJ6EcogeoxOwoimKabx7gynOb0f6-QxIpIELuqqT35rk-nLmDMZMDAljFtcY-YQBvNGWVgLCKOj7omvSxUjcQbXnG4B8H67gTFWQA8USo6Y3Xs5RWuXjQ8Chp2WchftGv-k9oTf7m0nPvki2JmPoQiawOquJTtiwFG9lxEX5-vSzJIvBPu5Gl_-jhW5wisUpTZCQWfzr9Ar56ix7q2rQ2B4qqyQxpPWqow2gJ_D0eF5c4PhAzh-QksTofGv9rUG0SJmgnDhUkCcF361B0kpugBjccqwqYBuaTbSFMqBowPacjapogDFA&amp;giftCopy=1_CurrentCopy&amp;smid=url-share">column</a> by Ron Lieber in the <em>New York Times</em>.</p>
<section id="overview" class="level2" data-number="1">
<h2 data-number="1" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="overview"><span class="header-section-number">1</span> Overview</h2>
<ul>
<li>I use R to gather data from the US government and other sources and make it into a giant table on schools as well as individual pages for each school (and separate pages on fields and majors). There are lots of small plots, too.</li>
<li>You can see all the packages used <a href="https://github.com/bomeara/collegetables_source/blob/main/_packages.R">here</a>.</li>
<li>I use <a href="https://docs.ropensci.org/targets/"><code>targets</code></a> to manage the workflow.</li>
<li>I use <a href="https://bookdown.org/yihui/rmarkdown/"><code>rmarkdown</code></a> to make the individual pages.</li>
<li><a href="https://rstudio.github.io/crosstalk/index.html"><code>crosstalk</code></a> is used to dynamically filter the table and maps.</li>
<li>GitHub pages to host all the individual pages.</li>
<li>Sensible structure for the pages: the ID number for Johns Hopkins is 162928, so its page is <a href="https://collegetables.info/162928.html" class="uri">https://collegetables.info/162928.html</a>; PhD programs in general history are at <a href="https://collegetables.info/majors_Doctorate_History_General.html" class="uri">https://collegetables.info/majors_Doctorate_History_General.html</a>.</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="targets" class="level2" data-number="2">
<h2 data-number="2" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="targets"><span class="header-section-number">2</span> Targets</h2>
<p>I knew that running this could take a while so having some way to do a workflow and cache completed steps would be important. The <a href="https://docs.ropensci.org/targets/"><code>targets</code></a> package (authored by William Michael Landau of Eli Lilly, package part of ropensci, paper at <a href="https://joss.theoj.org/papers/10.21105/joss.02959" class="uri">https://joss.theoj.org/papers/10.21105/joss.02959</a>) is a good way to do this (I used to use <code>targets</code>’ predecessor, <code>drake</code>). The basic idea is that you have a workflow that is a directed acyclic graph (DAG) of steps, and you can run the workflow and it will only run steps that need to be run. It also caches results, so if you change something, it will only rerun the steps that need to be rerun.</p>
<p>Here is the final workflow for the site:</p>
<p><img src="https://brianomeara.info/posts/collegetables/final_workflow.png" class="img-fluid" alt="Directed acyclic graph showing inputs and outputs of workflow"></p>
<p>The main things we care about are the <code>pages_new</code> square on the right (which has one page for each college) and the <code>field_pages</code>, <code>majors</code>, and <code>index_et_al</code> circles which represent pages for fields, majors, and things like the index and about pages. Information flows from the left to the right until the website is all generated.</p>
</section>
<section id="main-data" class="level2" data-number="3">
<h2 data-number="3" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="main-data"><span class="header-section-number">3</span> Main data</h2>
<p>The US National Center for Education Statistics (NCES) has an Integrated Postsecondary Education Data System (IPEDS) that has info on postsecondary schools: schools that students enroll in after high school. It includes colleges and universities, seminaries, trade schools, and more. They have one <a href="https://nces.ed.gov/ipeds/use-the-data/download-access-database">dataset per year</a> stored as a Microsoft Access database which turned out to be hard to convert (and I didn’t want to buy MS Access). They also have <a href="https://nces.ed.gov/ipeds/datacenter/DataFiles.aspx?gotoReportId=7&amp;fromIpeds=true">individual data files per year</a>. Here is a subset of files from 2022:</p>
<p><img src="https://brianomeara.info/posts/collegetables/ipeds_files_2022.png" class="img-fluid" alt="Picture of table of IPEDS files for 2022"></p>
<p>Files are in csv; there is also a data dictionary file in Excel with more info on what each column and states within it means: for example, that “LOCALE” in table “HD2022” means “Locale codes identify the geographic status of a school on an urban continuum ranging from large city to rural” and that code 12 means “City: Midsize”, 31 means “Town, Fringe”, etc.</p>
<p>To get the files, I first made a list of all the file name types (admissions data are in ADM2021, ADM2020, etc.): function <a href="https://github.com/bomeara/collegetables_source/blob/209e413716d90da8527b22d36eef9154fa7efb08/R/functions.R#L10"><code>GetIPEDSNames()</code></a> stores this (functions without a package:: prefix are ones written for the workflow; links go to the function source) – it stores the abbreviations in a vector, with better descriptions of the files as names of the vector.</p>
<p>I then try to get the data files for each year, download them, and do some basic processing using <a href="https://github.com/bomeara/collegetables_source/blob/209e413716d90da8527b22d36eef9154fa7efb08/R/functions.R#L50"><code>GetIPEDSDirectly()</code></a>. Each file is in a zipped directory (which may include multiple files, for example if there is both the original file and a later revised one). I also download the data dictionary. The correct file is loaded (using <code>readr::read_csv</code> unless the file is too large, when I use <code>arrow::read_csv_arrow</code>), the data dictionary is loaded with <code>readxl::read_excel</code>, and then the data dictionary is used to give columns and entries more informative names. These are all then saved as csv files in a local directory.</p>
<p>This is the <code>ipeds_directly</code> step in the highlighted workflow below.</p>
<p><img src="https://brianomeara.info/posts/collegetables/ipeds_workflow.png" class="img-fluid" alt="Highlighted workflow showing IPEDS data steps"></p>
<p>I then use <a href="https://github.com/bomeara/collegetables_source/blob/209e413716d90da8527b22d36eef9154fa7efb08/R/functions.R#L784"><code>AggregateDirectIPEDSDirect()</code></a> to load all the files and store them in an SQLite database (yes, I probably should have just paid for Microsoft Access and gotten the original files in this format).</p>
<p>The next step is creating a massive table (<code>comparison_table_core</code>): one row per institution per year with only the columns I might care about. It’s 86798 rows by 890 columns, using 669.9 MB of memory. One very nice feature of IPEDS data is each institution having a unique UNITID, allowing stitching together of data from different tables and even sometimes different sources. Things like institution names can be duplicated, but the UNITID is unique.</p>
<p>The above steps are the main difficult ones, and I’m omitting various details (handling errors in the datasets, odd formats, etc.). But we have the main data! Info on majors and fields is similar.</p>
</section>
<section id="additional-data" class="level2" data-number="4">
<h2 data-number="4" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="additional-data"><span class="header-section-number">4</span> Additional data</h2>
<p>Another aspect missing from IPEDS data and many college ranking sites is the overall social and natural environment. Things like access to health care procedures, gun regulations, and more are changing and may change into the future. Other things of interest are whether a college is in a desert or forest, how far it is from mountains (one of my kids was interested), and even life expectancy (hopefully not relevant to undergrads, but for people choosing to build a career at an institution, this might be useful info). A lot of info is aggregated at state level (like Erin Reed’s <a href="https://www.erininthemorning.com/p/anti-trans-legislative-risk-assessment">risk of anti-trans legislation map</a> or the Guttmacher Institute’s <a href="https://states.guttmacher.org/policies/">abortion access</a> map), making adding this to the massive table easy; other data like biome or distance to mountains could be per location. A series of functions append info on these various factors to the main table.</p>
<p>I have my own views on which factors and in which directions are important, but I wanted to make the site neutral: someone can filter for colleges in states with high or low proportion of US reps who vote in favor of protecting access to contraception, for example, with no default ordering put in place by me.</p>
<p><a href="https://github.com/GMBA-biodiversity/gmbaR">gmbaR</a> was essential in the distances to mountains calculation.</p>
<p>There are other sources of information I would like to include on social climate (even down to the campus level), but many do not allow reuse of their data, and I wanted to respect their wishes.</p>
</section>
<section id="individual-pages" class="level2" data-number="5">
<h2 data-number="5" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="individual-pages"><span class="header-section-number">5</span> Individual pages</h2>
<p>Parametric rmarkdown is used for institution pages. <a href="https://bookdown.org/yihui/rmarkdown/">Rmarkdown</a> was developed by Yihui Xie and builds on from work by John Gruber (markdown) and John McFarlane (pandoc). Rmarkdown lets you write in text with easy to read formatting and insert blocks of code that can be run when compiling the document. Parametric rmarkdown lets you pass arguments into the document: you could have a template of a report and have it pass in company info: “Over the past quarter stocks in <code>company_name</code> have <code>changed</code> by <code>percent_change</code>, but this is not a guarantee of future stock motion.” You can also have it embed plots or tables. Quarto is in some ways a successor to rmarkdown (I use it for my personal website), but when I was developing collegetables quarto was new enough that I encountered some issues.</p>
<p>For each institution page, I use the template <a href="https://github.com/bomeara/collegetables_source/blob/main/_institution.Rmd">_institution.Rmd</a>. Its header includes the following parameters:</p>
<pre><code>params:
  institution_name: "nothing"
  institution_long_name: "nothing"
  institution_id: "nothing"
  comparison_table: "nothing"
  spark_width: 200
  spark_height: 60
  weatherspark: "nothing"
  index_table: "index_table"
  life_expectancy: "nothing"
  population_by_state_by_age: "nothing"</code></pre>
<p>And then within the body of the template it includes text and some functions to compute info for tables and plots as well as to pass in notes. For example, if the focal institution’s enrollment is decreasing over time, a <a href="https://github.com/bomeara/collegetables_source/blob/209e413716d90da8527b22d36eef9154fa7efb08/_institution.Rmd#L299">note</a> is prepended to the output document. Not all notes are bad, but they are things that people might want to look into.</p>
<p>Then the <a href="https://github.com/bomeara/collegetables_source/blob/209e413716d90da8527b22d36eef9154fa7efb08/R/functions.R#L1538">RenderSingleInstitutionPage()</a> function does a basic loop to pass in information to create the page for each institution. Each page has lots of graphs, as well as embedded things like some javascript libraries. To save on space, I use the <code>self_contained: false</code> argument in the header YAML: that way all the files are not embedded in each page. I also make the graphs as separate files to load (though I might have javascript render them on the fly in the future: I wasn’t satisfied with the information density of the graphs available in javascript when I was first doing them). Alt tags for each image are also generated within the rmarkdown file for improved accessibility.</p>
<p>Getting the initial data is done infrequently; changing the institution pages is more frequent as I tweak something or as one of the state-level datasets changes. So much of the time is spent on re-rendering the institution pages. I now have it in targets do this as a map so if it stops halfway through, it can pick up with the next institution rather than restarting:</p>
<pre><code> tar_target(
    pages_new, 
    RenderSingleInstitutionPage(institution_unitid, comparison_table, fields_and_majors, maxcount=maxcount, CIPS_codes=CIPS_codes, weatherspark=weatherspark, yml=yml, index_table=index_table, life_expectancy=life_expectancy, population_by_state_by_age=population_by_state_by_age, institution_rmd=institution_rmd),
    pattern=map(institution_unitid)
 ),</code></pre>
</section>
<section id="field-and-majors-pages" class="level2" data-number="6">
<h2 data-number="6" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="field-and-majors-pages"><span class="header-section-number">6</span> Field and majors pages</h2>
<p>I also wanted pages on every field and major to let people drill down and search: if I want to major in computer science, which universities are putting out graduates?</p>
<p>I’m still not happy with the soluton, but I made one page of all the major fields of study (<a href="https://collegetables.info/fields_overview.html" class="uri">https://collegetables.info/fields_overview.html</a>) so people can do full text search (or it might pop up a general search engine), then they can did down into the individual fields (i.e., <a href="https://collegetables.info/Library_Science.html" class="uri">https://collegetables.info/Library_Science.html</a>). They can then dig further down into degrees by majors (<a href="https://collegetables.info/majors_Doctorate_Astronomy.html" class="uri">https://collegetables.info/majors_Doctorate_Astronomy.html</a>). I’ve thought of using a treemap or other way to visualize the categories, but it’s hard because the basic level of fields has 48 large categories and 2321 fields within those. This area is probably not as useful for undergrads (who might not know their major in fine detail yet) but could be good for grad students looking to specialize (i.e., “where can I get a Masters in forestry?”: <a href="https://collegetables.info/majors_Masters_Forestry_General.html" class="uri">https://collegetables.info/majors_Masters_Forestry_General.html</a>, though don’t forget the separate degree of <a href="https://collegetables.info/majors_Masters_UrbanForestry.html">urban forestry</a>).</p>
</section>
<section id="interactive-home-page" class="level2" data-number="7">
<h2 data-number="7" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="interactive-home-page"><span class="header-section-number">7</span> Interactive home page</h2>
<p>For the home page with a table, I wanted to have:</p>
<ul>
<li>A table of all the schools</li>
<li>A way to filter the table</li>
<li>A way to show or hide columns</li>
</ul>
<p>Also, any table needs to have a default ordering. Visitors will want to see colleges they know early in the table, so I needed some way to sort.</p>
<pre><code>Psuedoranking = (100 - Admission %) + Yield % + 6-yr grad rate + 10*log1p(Number of undergrads) + 10*log1p(Number of tenure-stream faculty)</code></pre>
<p>This is arbitrary, but it weights colleges by <del>how many dreams they crush</del> selectivity of admissions, whether students who are admitted choose to go there, if those students graduate, how big the school is, and how they are investing in faculty.</p>
<p>For the main table, I use <a href="https://glin.github.io/reactable/"><code>reactable</code></a> to make one that can work on different screen sizes and have filtering and sorting, incluing showing or hiding sets of columns. I use <a href="https://rstudio.github.io/crosstalk/index.html"><code>crosstalk</code></a> to allow filtering of the table to also filter the map, which is made in <a href="https://rstudio.github.io/leaflet/">‘leaflet’</a>.</p>
</section>
<section id="hosting" class="level2" data-number="8">
<h2 data-number="8" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="hosting"><span class="header-section-number">8</span> Hosting</h2>
<p>I use GitHub pages to host the site. It’s stored in two repositories: <a href="https://github.com/bomeara/collegetables_source" class="uri">https://github.com/bomeara/collegetables_source</a> for the source code and <a href="https://github.com/bomeara/collegetables_site" class="uri">https://github.com/bomeara/collegetables_site</a> for the rendered site (I originally had it in one, but it’s a lot of blobby files for git to deal with, and it allows me to separate the development and production branches).</p>
</section>
<section id="learning" class="level2" data-number="9">
<h2 data-number="9" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="learning"><span class="header-section-number">9</span> Learning</h2>
<p>I work in higher ed, so I thought I knew a fair bit about the higher ed landscape going in. However, a few things surprised me:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>“Traditional” isn’t</strong>: Our conventional view of college is it’s a four-year experience in fancy buildings, students live in dorms, tenured faculty walk the halls. Harvard, Berkeley, and the like. But a huge proportion of undergrad degrees are coming from places like <a href="https://collegetables.info/433387.html">Western Governors University</a>, which has 108,000 undergrads, three times as many as <a href="https://collegetables.info/110635.html">UC Berkeley</a>. Yet one of the trade publications for higher education, the <em>Chronicle of Higher Education</em>, mentions “Western Governors University” 362 times, Berkeley 6,442 times, and the even smaller Harvard 14,735 times. Undergraduate enrollment isn’t the only component of higher education: research and other creative activities, service to the community (including public scholarship, ag outreach, and more), commercial spinoffs, graduate education, and more are all important and often are a focus at the more famous schools. But even in discussion of undergrad education, schools affecting lots of students remain not a major focus. (Also, “a four-year experience” is often a lie: the graduation rates commonly reported are six-year graduation rates, and many, many students take longer than the nominal four years for a bachelors degree. Families, look at the four- and six-year grad rates before yelling at your students for taking too long).</li>
<li><strong>Ignore sticker price</strong>: Listed tuitions aren’t what many people pay, and traditional knowledge of what schools are “cheap” versus “expensive” are often wrong. For example, what’s cheaper, U. of Oklahoma or Princeton? For a family making $30K-48K a year getting federal aid, the average cost of Oklahoma is $16,097 but for Princeton it’s $4,502. There are all sorts of things that affect cost (including state aid, institutional aid, loans versus grants, and more), but the sticker price is not a good guide. To help make people think about this, I added a comparison to “expensive” Harvard to every institution page.</li>
<li><strong>Rise in disabilities</strong>: for example, at <a href="https://collegetables.info/130794.html#student-details">Yale</a> the percentage of students with disabilities went from 6% in 2015 to 22% in 2021. <a href="https://www.insidehighered.com/news/2022/05/03/more-students-report-psychological-disabilities">Others have reported</a> on this, but it really jumped out of the data.</li>
<li><strong>Lack of information on mental health resources</strong>: mental health matters a lot in college. What’s the ratio of therapists to students? What’s the wait time to get an appointment? Is there a cap on sessions? I could not find data on this.</li>
<li><strong>Disappearance of books</strong>: many universities seem to be shrinking libraries. Physical circulation is also decreasing, while digital increases. For example, here’s the <a href="https://collegetables.info/100751.html#library-facilities">data for U. of Alabama</a>:</li>
</ul>
<p><img src="https://brianomeara.info/posts/collegetables/UAlabama_library.png" class="img-fluid" alt="Table showing changes in U of Alabama library collection size (decreasing) and usage"></p>
<p>It still has a lot of books, and the number has become stable, but there was a longer term decrease in their collections size. The use of physical collections is decreasing (I divide by the number of faculty and students to get an estimate normalized by university size): on average, every student or faculty member there seems to check out less than one physical thing a year. * <strong>There are many small schools</strong>. For example, there are many schools for hair styling. The beauty of parametric rmarkdown is that including these takes no extra work, and it might help somebody.</p>
</section>
<section id="future" class="level2" data-number="10">
<h2 data-number="10" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="future"><span class="header-section-number">10</span> Future</h2>
<p>My elder kid is applying to colleges now (Fall 2023); they hopefully won’t need this again until they start thinking about potential law / med / theology / grad / etc. schools. My younger kid is only a freshman in high school, so still has some time. I’ll keep poking at the site, though.</p>
<p>I’d love to get more data on life at the colleges: how involved are students in club activities, are fraternities or sororities a big part of campus culture, etc. Mental health resources would also be good. There are data on crimes, but we know underreporting is a huge problem: I worry that the schools that look “worst” for some crimes might be the ones that actually have earned the trust of survivors to report.</p>
</section>
<section id="thank-you" class="level2" data-number="11">
<h2 data-number="11" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="thank-you"><span class="header-section-number">11</span> Thank you</h2>
<p>This would have been impossible without freely available open federal data; I also really appreciate the efforts of people who compiled data at the state level, especially about laws that can affect many. The R ecosystem of packages, including well-written documentation and answered questions online, was also essential. rOpenSci and Posit (formerly Rstudio) were key players in a lot of the important packages. Thanks to my kids for beta-testing.</p>
<p>Note that nothing on the site reflects the views of any of my past, present, or future employers, nor any granting agencies (this was all done in my spare time). It’s had benefits, though, in improving my R and sqlite skills, which does help my day job – I’m actually finishing up a grant proposal using similar techniques (but more in my core research area of evolutionary biology).</p>
<hr>
<p>To subscribe, go to <a href="https://brianomeara.info/blog.xml" class="uri">https://brianomeara.info/blog.xml</a> in an RSS reader.</p>


</section>

<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-citation"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Citation</h2><div><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">BibTeX citation:</div><pre class="sourceCode code-with-copy quarto-appendix-bibtex"><code class="sourceCode bibtex">@online{o'meara2023,
  author = {O’Meara, Brian},
  title = {13,000 Page Site with {Rmarkdown} and Targets},
  date = {2023-10-28},
  url = {https://brianomeara.info/posts/collegetables/},
  langid = {en}
}
</code></pre><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">For attribution, please cite this work as:</div><div id="ref-o'meara2023" class="csl-entry quarto-appendix-citeas">
O’Meara, Brian. 2023. <span>“13,000 Page Site with Rmarkdown and
Targets.”</span> October 28, 2023. <a href="https://brianomeara.info/posts/collegetables/">https://brianomeara.info/posts/collegetables/</a>.
</div></div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>github</category>
  <category>software</category>
  <category>rstats</category>
  <category>highered</category>
  <category>targets</category>
  <category>rmarkdown</category>
  <guid>https://brianomeara.info/posts/collegetables/</guid>
  <pubDate>Sat, 28 Oct 2023 04:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>SSB Code of Ethics</title>
  <dc:creator>Brian O&#39;Meara</dc:creator>
  <link>https://brianomeara.info/posts/codeofethics/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>People who are members of the Society of Systematic Biologists should check for an email with subject: “SSB Code of Ethics”. It contains a link to a ballot and more information.</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>Dear SSB Members,</p>
<p>Based on 4+ years of intensive work by multiple ASN/SSB/SSE joint committees, SSB has developed a Code of Ethics and an accompanying <a href="https://www.evolutioncodeofethics.org/uploads/1/3/9/1/139124864/ssb_coe_-_final.docx.pdf">Enforcement Policy</a>. Here, we ask members to vote on amending the SSB Governance Documents (<a href="https://github.com/systbiol/docs/blob/master/constitution.txt">Constitution and Bylaws</a>) to require members to adhere to this Code of Ethics, to empower the Council to establish and enforce this Code of Ethics, and to establish a mechanism whereby the Code of Ethics can be updated in the future.</p>
<p><strong>The SSB Council has already voted in favor of this Code of Ethics. However, before the Code takes effect, we believe it is necessary to amend the SSB Governance documents (Constitution and Bylaws).</strong></p>
<p>The proposed changes are described in detail, along with accompanying explanations, on the voting page linked below [BCO: only for members; I don’t include the link here]. The proposed amendments are also <a href="https://github.com/systbiol/docs/pull/9/files">available to view in SSB’s GitHub repository</a>, in the context of the entire SSB Constitution.</p>
<p>Voting will remain open through Nov.&nbsp;10th.</p>
<p>As always, thank you for your continued participation in the Society!</p>
<p>The SSB Council</p>
</blockquote>
<p>This reflects a lot of work by a lot of people across SSB, the Society for the Study of Evolution (SSE), and the American Society of Naturalists (ASN), as well as experts outside the societies, and rounds of feedback by members and councils.</p>
<p>I really hope this passes in SSB and ASN (it already did, overwhelmingly, in SSE). I talked a bit about why in my SSB Presidential address this summer (<a href="https://brianomeara.info/evol2023.html">go here</a> for materials from it, <a href="https://youtu.be/2lbfjtOVntA?si=qCNx4-8iv_xj32Lh&amp;t=1002">and here</a> to jump right to the section of the speech on this area). We know misconduct happens in our field, both anecdotally and from quantitative data. One extreme response, though historically common, is ignoring it completely. Another extreme is to do things unofficially based on rumors. A good approach is to have a robust code of ethics with clear procedures. SSB Council has approved a code that has strong protections for confidentiality (but does not allow anonymous reporting), has a trained investigator get evidence in a case, and has a committee of peers decide on any possible sanctions. Now it’s up to the membership to vote on a constitution and bylaw change so the Council can implement it and tweak it as needed. Despite all the work that’s gone into it, there will likely be things that need to be adjusted in future years – this will let the Council do minor changes, while major ones will go to the membership for another vote.</p>
<p>For more on the code, go to <a href="https://www.evolutioncodeofethics.org" class="uri">https://www.evolutioncodeofethics.org</a>, which has an FAQ, diagrams of how it all works, and more.</p>
<p>And a big thank you to all the people who worked on this. Please vote!</p>
<hr>
<p>To subscribe, go to <a href="https://brianomeara.info/blog.xml" class="uri">https://brianomeara.info/blog.xml</a> in an RSS reader.</p>



<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-citation"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Citation</h2><div><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">BibTeX citation:</div><pre class="sourceCode code-with-copy quarto-appendix-bibtex"><code class="sourceCode bibtex">@online{o'meara2023,
  author = {O’Meara, Brian},
  title = {SSB {Code} of {Ethics}},
  date = {2023-10-26},
  url = {https://brianomeara.info/posts/codeofethics/},
  langid = {en}
}
</code></pre><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">For attribution, please cite this work as:</div><div id="ref-o'meara2023" class="csl-entry quarto-appendix-citeas">
O’Meara, Brian. 2023. <span>“SSB Code of Ethics.”</span> October 26,
2023. <a href="https://brianomeara.info/posts/codeofethics/">https://brianomeara.info/posts/codeofethics/</a>.
</div></div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>code of ethics</category>
  <category>SSB</category>
  <category>systematics</category>
  <category>ethics</category>
  <guid>https://brianomeara.info/posts/codeofethics/</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 26 Oct 2023 04:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Fraction of history</title>
  <dc:creator>Brian O&#39;Meara</dc:creator>
  <link>https://brianomeara.info/posts/percentageage/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>On mastodon, <a href="https://mastodon.social/@gundersen">Marius Gunderen</a>, <a href="https://mastodon.social/@gundersen/110972549747804838">posted</a>:</p>
<p>“It’s wild to think about how short human history is. For example, the iron age started approximately 1200BC, which means that if you are 32 years old you have been alive for 1% of the time humans have used iron. If you are 54 years old then you have lived through 1% of horses being domesticated, the wheel being used for transport, written language and living in towns.”</p>
<p>I thought it would be interesting educationally to do this with many events. Enter a human age in years below to do this, then click somewhere outside the box:</p>
<form>
Age in years: <input type="text" id="age" value="44" onchange="convert_age()"><br>
</form>
<p><br></p>
<h3 class="anchored">
Been alive for what percentage of time since:
</h3>
<ul>
<li>Domestication of corn (6700 BCE): <span id="corn"></span>%</li>
<li>Start of the iron age (1200 BCE): <span id="iron"></span>%</li>
<li>Gutenberg printing press (1400 CE): <span id="printing"></span>%</li>
<li>First usable light bulb (1879): <span id="lightbulb"></span>%</li>
<li>First flight (1903): <span id="flight"></span>%</li>
<li>US women right to vote (1920): <span id="womenvote"></span>%</li>
<li>Discovery of the structure of DNA (1953): <span id="dna"></span>%</li>
<li>US banning of segregation (1964): <span id="segregation"></span>%</li>
<li>Widespread scientific acceptance of plate tectonics (1965): <span id="platetectonics"></span>%</li>
<li>First email (1971): <span id="email"></span>%</li>
<li>US discrimination in lending banned (1974): <span id="credit"></span>%</li>
</ul>
<hr>
<p>To subscribe, go to <a href="https://brianomeara.info/blog.xml" class="uri">https://brianomeara.info/blog.xml</a></p>



<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-citation"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Citation</h2><div><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">BibTeX citation:</div><pre class="sourceCode code-with-copy quarto-appendix-bibtex"><code class="sourceCode bibtex">@online{o'meara2023,
  author = {O’Meara, Brian},
  title = {Fraction of History},
  date = {2023-09-01},
  url = {https://brianomeara.info/posts/percentageage/},
  langid = {en}
}
</code></pre><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">For attribution, please cite this work as:</div><div id="ref-o'meara2023" class="csl-entry quarto-appendix-citeas">
O’Meara, Brian. 2023. <span>“Fraction of History.”</span> September 1,
2023. <a href="https://brianomeara.info/posts/percentageage/">https://brianomeara.info/posts/percentageage/</a>.
</div></div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>history</category>
  <category>mastodon</category>
  <guid>https://brianomeara.info/posts/percentageage/</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 01 Sep 2023 04:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Github rate limit</title>
  <dc:creator>Brian O&#39;Meara</dc:creator>
  <link>https://brianomeara.info/posts/githubratelimit/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>Lately I have been getting this error on occasion when running <code>devtools::install()</code> in R:</p>
<pre><code>&gt; devtools::install()
Error: HTTP error 401.
  Bad credentials

  Rate limit remaining: 59/60
  Rate limit reset at: 2023-07-27 21:55:54 UTC</code></pre>
<p>The solution, from <a href="https://community.rstudio.com/t/unable-to-install-packages-from-github/124372" class="uri">https://community.rstudio.com/t/unable-to-install-packages-from-github/124372</a>, is to do</p>
<pre><code>Sys.unsetenv("GITHUB_PAT")</code></pre>
<p>There have been past reports on this in the devtools package, but it was apparently fixed some time ago. I am using Mac OS 13.4, R 4.2.3. This line does fix it, though.</p>
<hr>
<p>To subscribe, go to <a href="https://brianomeara.info/blog.xml" class="uri">https://brianomeara.info/blog.xml</a> in an RSS reader.</p>



<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-citation"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Citation</h2><div><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">BibTeX citation:</div><pre class="sourceCode code-with-copy quarto-appendix-bibtex"><code class="sourceCode bibtex">@online{o'meara2023,
  author = {O’Meara, Brian},
  title = {Github Rate Limit},
  date = {2023-07-27},
  url = {https://brianomeara.info/posts/githubratelimit/},
  langid = {en}
}
</code></pre><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">For attribution, please cite this work as:</div><div id="ref-o'meara2023" class="csl-entry quarto-appendix-citeas">
O’Meara, Brian. 2023. <span>“Github Rate Limit.”</span> July 27, 2023.
<a href="https://brianomeara.info/posts/githubratelimit/">https://brianomeara.info/posts/githubratelimit/</a>.
</div></div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>github</category>
  <category>software</category>
  <category>rstats</category>
  <guid>https://brianomeara.info/posts/githubratelimit/</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 27 Jul 2023 04:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Grad core class in evolutionary biology, 2023 edition</title>
  <dc:creator>Brian O&#39;Meara</dc:creator>
  <link>https://brianomeara.info/posts/evolutioncore2023/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>Our department has long had a core class: one semester on ecology, one on evolution. It originated before I started here (it was somewhat modeled on UC Davis Population Biology’s core class, which I took as a student, in fact), but I’ve taught parts of it (usually a few weeks on phylogenetics and macroevolution) nearly every year I’ve been here. This year, I took over as the instructor for the evolution semester. Years ago the course was largely team taught with perhaps four or five instructors per semester; over time, this has winnowed down. I chose to do it as the sole instructor, with one guest discussion with Dr.&nbsp;Nina Fefferman on getting grants (she’s <a href="http://feffermanlab.org/funding.html">very good</a> at it), as the students wanted to have a discussion on this.</p>
<p>This course is described as “Readings, lectures, and discussion about key concepts in evolution.” In practice, it has several goals:</p>
<ol type="1">
<li>Replace the evolution written exam that was formerly part of qualifying exams (so quals can now focus just on the research project itself). This necessitates broad coverage and robust assessments of knowledge.</li>
<li>Make students fluent in evolutionary thought: students emerging with a Masters or PhD in an ecology and evolutionary biology department should be able to talk about genetic drift, the Modern Synthesis, speciation, and more to people studying evolution, even if the students specialize on some other aspect of science and come with a very different background.</li>
<li>Help students understand how evolution science is done. “Science” is a corpus of knowledge (“the mitochondrion is the powerhouse of the cell”) and is often presented as this in undergraduate courses, but it is also a way to get this knowledge. Students will learn how we gain knowledge in evolution.</li>
<li>Onboarding to the department. This is a particular set of people, assembled with care and at great expense: how to thrive in the department, who people are, etc.</li>
</ol>
<p>Course structure was based on particular topics, with students typically given a paper or two to read and ask questions about, then work through the topic and questions in class (lots of think-pair-share, class questions, etc.). Students asked for more structure, so I started adding basic slides to give broader overviews of the topics and giving sample final exam questions for each topic so they could better understand the type of depth of knowledge I was expecting them to get.</p>
<p>Often this sort of course covers a lot of history of the field, famous scientists, and the like. I focused instead on current understandings of the topics. This aligns with the course description (“key concepts in evolution”) but I argue that it’s more important for students who are doing their own research: what do we know, and what is still left to learn, rather than who thought what in 1968. That said, there is still vocab people should know in the field, including names of people and organisms, as well as local info (faculty members, Scopes trial, and similar), so I made a <a href="Jargonfest.csv">list of jargon (.csv)</a>, see also Section&nbsp;4, and had some multiple choice quizzes and part of the final to encourage students to learn about these terms.</p>
<section id="overall-topics-covered" class="level2" data-number="1">
<h2 data-number="1" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="overall-topics-covered"><span class="header-section-number">1</span> Overall topics covered</h2>
<ul>
<li>Jan 24 Intro</li>
<li>Jan 26 Effective population size: <a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/nrg2526">Charlesworth (2009)</a></li>
<li>Jan 31 Adaptation: <a href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.tree.2016.12.005">Kokko et al.&nbsp;(2017)</a></li>
<li>Feb 2 Spandrels: <a href="https://doi.org/10.1098/rspb.1979.0086">Gould &amp; Lewontin (1979)</a></li>
<li>Feb 7 Neutral theory I: <a href="https://doi.org/10.1146/annurev-genom-082908-150129">Nei et al.&nbsp;(2010, pages 265-274)</a></li>
<li>Feb 9 Neutral theory II: <a href="https://doi.org/10.1146/annurev-genom-082908-150129">Nei et al.&nbsp;(2010, pages 274-289)</a></li>
<li>Feb 14 R (see Section&nbsp;3.1)</li>
<li>Feb 16 Python (see Section&nbsp;3.2)</li>
<li>Feb 21 Game theory: <a href="https://doi.org/10.1146/annurev.es.14.110183.002113">Riechert &amp; Hammerstein (1984)</a> [UTK author]</li>
<li>Feb 23 Quantitative genetics and evolvabililty: <a href="https://doi.org/10.1146/annurev-ecolsys-011121-021241">Hansen &amp; Pélabon (2021)</a></li>
<li>Feb 28 Sexual selection I: <a href="https://doi.org/10.1126/science.abi6308">Rosenthal &amp; Ryan (2022)</a></li>
<li>Mar 2 Sexual selection II: <a href="https://doi.org/10.1007/978-94-017-9585-2_5">Roughgarden (2015)</a></li>
<li>Mar 7 Species concepts: <a href="https://repository.si.edu/handle/10088/4652">de Queiroz (1998)</a></li>
<li>Mar 9 Species delimitation: <a href="https://doi.org/10.1093/sysbio/syw100">Morales et al (2016)</a> [UTK coauthor; COI]</li>
<li>Mar 21 Bayesian, maximum likelihood, and phylogenetics: <a href="https://doi.org/10.1016/s0169-5347(00)02025-5">Lewis (2001)</a></li>
<li>Mar 23 Phylogenetics discrete characters: <a href="https://doi.org/10.1146/annurev-ecolsys-110411-160331">O’Meara (2012)</a> [UTK author; COI]</li>
<li>Mar 28 Phylogenetics utility: slides for this</li>
<li>Mar 30 Work session for students to study and figure out questions</li>
<li>Apr 4 Phylogenetics continuous models: slides, also paper above.</li>
<li>Apr 11 Diversification: <a href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.tree.2007.06.013">Ricklefs (2007)</a></li>
<li>Apr 14 Timeline of life: <a href="https://www.newscientist.com/article/dn17453-timeline-the-evolution-of-life/" class="uri">https://www.newscientist.com/article/dn17453-timeline-the-evolution-of-life/</a></li>
<li>Apr 18 Biogeography: <a href="https://doi.org/10.1007/s12052-012-0421-2">Sanmartín (2012)</a></li>
<li>Apr 20 Paleontology: <a href="https://doi.org/10.1146/annurev-ecolsys-110617-062638">Stigall (2019)</a> [UTK author]</li>
<li>Apr 25 Evolution of behavior: <a href="https://doi.org/10.1146/annurev-ecolsys-110218-025040">Whiten (2019)</a></li>
<li>Apr 27 EvoDevo: <a href="https://doi.org/10.1146/annurev-cellbio-101011-155732">Mallarino &amp; Abzhanov (2012)</a></li>
<li>May 2 Grants (with Dr.&nbsp;Nina Fefferman)</li>
<li>May 4 Eugenics: <a href="https://www.ashg.org/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/Facing_Our_History-Building_an_Equitable_Future_Final_Report_January_2023.pdf">“Facing our History – Building an Equitable Future” by American Society of Human Genetics, page 5-15</a> and <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2022/06/08/magazine/eugenics-movement-america.html?unlocked_article_code=Yd0N6bRMTs9hkiFQjlNyB5EYekKtNRfbRxktfpFMCF_IbOUR5SeUjL0wEYaloYcd4LfTIKspaC31l8N7flxkVtM8NsLmR36mM_0wfoUPGOit7Cxvn-2yd1SUUGplzyIuXlNRylugiCqAC6tDwoA7feN7ILjzA_DHXO6H-JdLmjZUGhgsdxmo4dMy8Y-t2PG1n7GjSO33NofeAVTh4tGOcqLCttGWVo04KPwEDP2oFCyt_UFyPHvz-rKSEx8V2kze-43rjIUOsRL2B5OIkRw452JxvUAl5qRSdu6UcJ-nfTo1AiDu0Vu97NsG_CD8jYmWwegZH6CkXd_VYbuGtGIm-EEydtQ&amp;smid=url-share">Villarosa (2019)</a></li>
<li>May 9 Human evolution: <a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41586-021-03244-5">Bergström et al.&nbsp;(2021)</a></li>
</ul>
<p>Given the audience (a course like this is varied: some are students with a Masters degree in evolution, some have had very little biology and come from fields like linguistics, math, or geography), slightly more than half the articles are reviews, while others are particular studies that illustrate what a field can be. I tried to focus discussions on helping with confusing concepts and then talking about why this area of research and its questions can matter. I worked to pull from authors from a variety of backgrounds and perspectives; I’ll be continuing to revisit the set of papers used in the class in the future (and suggestions welcome!).</p>
</section>
<section id="sec-accessibility" class="level2" data-number="2">
<h2 data-number="2" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="sec-accessibility"><span class="header-section-number">2</span> Accessibility</h2>
<p>Some steps I took to attempt to help with accessibility:</p>
<ul>
<li>PowerPoint live captioning is great: even when the slide show part of a class was done, I’d leave it open and running so that people can see what is being said</li>
<li>The class was in person, but I always had a zoom stream going. No more than one or two students used it at a time, but it still gave flexibility for those who needed it.</li>
<li>I used clear N95 masks: <a href="https://optrel.us/product/p-air-clear-n95-masks-20-pack/" class="uri">https://optrel.us/product/p-air-clear-n95-masks-20-pack/</a>. They’re more expensive than the regular masks, but they let students see my lips while giving me and them some degree of protection.</li>
<li>Quizzes and tests are not timed (other than a deadline to turn them in, days after they were made available)</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="sec-programming" class="level2" data-number="3">
<h2 data-number="3" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="sec-programming"><span class="header-section-number">3</span> Programming</h2>
<p>We spent one week on programming. My goal was to have students get a bit of exposure and get over initial fear: they’re not going to be writing packages after a week, but they’ll know some of how this all works, that error messages are normal, how to get help, how to start using R and python, etc.</p>
<section id="sec-r" class="level3" data-number="3.1">
<h3 data-number="3.1" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="sec-r"><span class="header-section-number">3.1</span> R</h3>
<p>I made an exercise at <a href="https://github.com/bomeara/geewhizR" class="uri">https://github.com/bomeara/geewhizR</a>, focused on this Rmarkdown file (<a href="https://github.com/bomeara/geewhizR/blob/main/main.Rmd" class="uri">https://github.com/bomeara/geewhizR/blob/main/main.Rmd</a>) for students to download; we worked through it in class. You can see it rendered fully here as a <a href="main.pdf">pdf</a>. Some of the basic concepts I wanted them to learn:</p>
<ul>
<li>Rmarkdown for reproducibility and keeping things organized</li>
<li>Installing and loading packages</li>
<li>The importance of actually looking at datasets (using <a href="https://blog.revolutionanalytics.com/2017/05/the-datasaurus-dozen.html">datasaurus</a>)</li>
<li>Getting information from online sources like GBIF, iNaturalist, and Datelife</li>
<li>Making maps</li>
</ul>
<p>The script does all this and gives them something to build from. I also gave them links to these resources:</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://swirlstats.com/" class="uri">https://swirlstats.com/</a>: good way to learn basic R</li>
<li><a href="https://posit.co/resources/cheatsheets/" class="uri">https://posit.co/resources/cheatsheets/</a>: summaries of functions in popular packages</li>
<li><a href="https://cran.r-project.org/web/views/" class="uri">https://cran.r-project.org/web/views/</a>: overviews of packages in particular domains. Phylogenetics can be particularly useful</li>
<li><a href="https://adv-r.hadley.nz/" class="uri">https://adv-r.hadley.nz/</a>: free online R textbook</li>
<li><a href="https://rmarkdown.rstudio.com/" class="uri">https://rmarkdown.rstudio.com/</a>: Rmarkdown, a way to combine code and text</li>
<li><a href="https://quarto.org/" class="uri">https://quarto.org/</a>: The successor to Rmarkdown; works better with both python and R</li>
<li><a href="https://books.ropensci.org/targets/" class="uri">https://books.ropensci.org/targets/</a>: a package for doing complex workflows</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="sec-python" class="level3" data-number="3.2">
<h3 data-number="3.2" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="sec-python"><span class="header-section-number">3.2</span> Python</h3>
<p>I’ve barely used any python so far (I’m heavily invested in the R ecosystem) but it’s worth having students learn it: it’s especially important in genomics and machine learning. I thought showing them how to do machine learning could be useful, including having them viscerally feel the issues that could come from image classification. For a sample problem, since I had shown them a local salamander in the R tutorial, and they were interested, I suggested solving a problem of using machine learning to assess whether a sampled individual was a juvenile or adult (<a href="https://www.inaturalist.org/taxa/27805-Notophthalmus-viridescens/browse_photos"><em>Notophthalmus viridescens</em>, the Eastern Newt</a>) – sort of an “awesome, I can see how this could scale up for my research” inspiration. Thus, I made this exercise (<a href="https://github.com/bomeara/geewhizPython" class="uri">https://github.com/bomeara/geewhizPython</a>), especially this sample script (<a href="https://github.com/bomeara/geewhizPython/blob/main/salamander.py" class="uri">https://github.com/bomeara/geewhizPython/blob/main/salamander.py</a>). I wanted them to learn:</p>
<ul>
<li>Installing python libraries</li>
<li>How to import from python libraries</li>
<li>How to point to a folder (directory)</li>
<li>How to do machine learning with a training and testing dataset</li>
<li>How to pull in information from iNaturalist</li>
<li>Possibilities and problems with machine learning results</li>
</ul>
<p>Some of the other resources I pointed them to:</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://pyinaturalist.readthedocs.io/en/stable/examples/Tutorial_1_Observations.html" class="uri">https://pyinaturalist.readthedocs.io/en/stable/examples/Tutorial_1_Observations.html</a>: the pyinaturalist Python package for using iNaturalist data</li>
<li><a href="https://keras.io" class="uri">https://keras.io</a>: for machine learning in general</li>
<li><a href="https://www.tensorflow.org" class="uri">https://www.tensorflow.org</a>: for a very popular machine learning framework</li>
<li><a href="https://www.anaconda.com/products/distribution" class="uri">https://www.anaconda.com/products/distribution</a>: Anaconda for making isolated python environments</li>
<li><a href="https://jupyter.org" class="uri">https://jupyter.org</a>: Jupyter notebooks (like Rmarkdown, but for python, and often working online)</li>
<li><a href="https://colab.research.google.com" class="uri">https://colab.research.google.com</a>: Google colab, for running python on the web (though consider long term stability: <a href="https://killedbygoogle.com" class="uri">https://killedbygoogle.com</a>)</li>
<li><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Weapons_of_Math_Destruction" class="uri">https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Weapons_of_Math_Destruction</a>: Overview of a book on how algorithms can cause harm (and there’s been a lot more work on this topic since)</li>
<li><a href="https://diffusionbee.com" class="uri">https://diffusionbee.com</a>: An application for making AI art</li>
<li><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Stable_Diffusion" class="uri">https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Stable_Diffusion</a>: Stable Diffusion, an AI for making art</li>
<li><a href="https://chat.openai.com/chat" class="uri">https://chat.openai.com/chat</a>: ChatGPT, an engine that can respond to prompts in various ways, including suggesting code.</li>
</ul>
</section>
</section>
<section id="sec-jargon" class="level2" data-number="4">
<h2 data-number="4" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="sec-jargon"><span class="header-section-number">4</span> Jargon</h2>
<p>This can be downloaded as a <a href="Jargonfest.csv">csv file</a>.</p>
<div class="cell">
<div class="cell-output-display">
<div class="datatables html-widget html-fill-item-overflow-hidden html-fill-item" id="htmlwidget-dd5000d92242385f90c8" style="width:100%;height:auto;"></div>
<script type="application/json" data-for="htmlwidget-dd5000d92242385f90c8">{"x":{"filter":"none","vertical":false,"data":[["1","2","3","4","5","6","7","8","9","10","11","12","13","14","15","16","17","18","19","20","21","22","23","24","25","26","27","28","29","30","31","32","33","34","35","36","37","38","39","40","41","42","43","44","45","46","47","48","49","50","51","52","53","54","55","56","57","58","59","60","61","62","63","64","65","66","67","68","69","70","71","72","73","74","75","76","77","78","79","80","81","82","83","84","85","86","87","88","89","90","91","92","93","94","95","96","97","98","99","100","101","102","103","104","105","106","107","108","109","110","111","112","113","114","115","116","117","118","119","120","121","122","123","124","125","126","127","128","129","130","131","132","133","134","135","136","137","138","139","140","141","142","143","144","145","146","147","148","149","150","151","152","153","154","155","156","157","158","159","160","161","162","163","164","165","166","167","168","169","170","171","172","173","174","175","176","177","178","179","180","181","182","183","184","185","186","187","188","189","190","191","192","193","194","195","196","197","198","199","200","201","202","203","204","205","206","207","208","209","210","211","212","213","214","215","216","217","218","219","220","221","222","223","224","225","226","227","228","229","230","231","232","233","234","235","236","237","238","239","240","241","242","243","244","245","246","247","248","249","250","251","252","253","254","255","256","257","258","259","260","261","262","263","264","265","266","267","268","269","270","271","272","273","274","275","276","277","278","279","280","281","282","283","284","285","286","287","288","289","290","291","292","293","294","295","296","297","298","299","300","301","302","303","304","305","306","307","308","309","310","311","312","313","314","315","316","317","318","319","320","321","322","323","324","325","326","327","328","329","330","331","332","333","334","335","336","337","338","339","340","341","342","343","344","345","346","347","348","349","350","351","352","353","354","355","356","357","358","359","360","361","362","363","364","365","366","367","368","369","370","371","372","373","374","375","376","377","378","379","380","381","382","383","384","385","386","387","388","389","390","391","392","393","394","395","396","397","398","399","400","401","402","403","404","405","406","407","408","409","410","411","412","413","414","415","416","417","418","419"],["adaptation","adaptive landscape","arms race","artificial selection","asexual reproduction","Batesian mimicry","biological constraints","Brownian motion","census population size","central dogma","coadaptation","coevolution","colonization","commensalism","cytoplasmic isolation","dispersal","Dobzhansky-Muller model","dynamic equilibrium","ecological niche","effective population size","endemism","endosymbiosis","ethology","evolutionary medicine","extant","fitness","iteroparity","K-strategy","lek","logistic growth","LUCA","negative selection","neontology","niche","NP-hard","phenotype","phylogeography","population","postzygotic isolating mechanism","prezygotic isolating mechanism","R-strategy","r/K selection","reinforcement","semelparity","sexual dimorphism","sexual selection","social Darwinism","survival of the fittest","theory","urban evolution","zygote","allometry","evo-devo","ontogeny","altruism","alternative splicing","assortative mating","backcrossing","bottleneck","Breeder's equation","canalization","candidate gene","cis-regulatory element","cline","coalescent","codon","codon usage bias","constitutive expression","crossing over","degeneracy of genetic code","dominant","dosage compensation","epigenetics","epistasis","exon","facultative expression","fixation (of alleles)","founder effect","frameshift mutation","frequency-dependent selection","G matrix","gamete","gene","gene dosage","gene drive","gene duplication","gene flow","gene pool","generation time","genetic distance","genetic drift","genetic hitchhiking","genetic load","genetic marker","genomic imprinting","genotype","germ line","haplodiploidy","Hardy-Weinberg principle","hemizygous","heredity","heritability","heterogametic sex","heterosis","homozygous","hox genes","hybrid","hybrid inviability","hybrid swarm","hybrid zone","identical by descent","identical by state","inbreeding depression","indel","intergenic region","intragenomic conflict","introgression","intron","isolation by distance","junk DNA","karyotype","kin selection","linkage disequilibrium","maternal effect","meiosis","Mendelian inheritance","migration","missense mutation","mitosis","Moran process","mutation","mutation rate","N_e","nearly neutral theory","neutral mutation","neutral theory","non-Mendelian inheritance","nonsense mutation","ortholog","panmixia","point mutation","polymorphism","polyploidy","positive selection","psuedogene","Punnett square","quantitative genetics","random mating","reaction norm","recessive","recombination","runaway sexual selection","secondary contact","selection coefficient","selective pressure","selective sweep","selfish genetic element","sex chromosome","stabilizing selection","trans-regulatory element","transcription","translation","wild type","Wright-Fisher process","X-linked gene","Y-linked gene","Alfred Russel Wallace","Alfred Wegener","Austin Peay","Ben Fitzpatrick","Beth Schussler","Brandon Matheny","Carl Woese","Carolus Linnaeus","Charles Darwin","Charles Lyell","Clarence Darrow","Dan Simberloff","Ed Schilling","Elisabeth Vrba","EO Wilson","Ernst Mayr","G. Ledyard Stebbins","George Gaylord Simpson","Gregor Mendel","Henreitte Jager","JBS Haldane","Jean-Baptiste Lamark","Jen Schweitzer","Jessica Budke","Jessie Tanner","Jim Fordyce","Joe Bailey","Joe Williams","John Edmonstone","John Maynard Smith","John Scopes","Julian Huxley","Karen Hughes","Kimberly Sheldon","Laura Russo","Leigh Van Valen","Liz Derryberry","Lynn Margulis","Mary Anning","Michael Gilchrist","Mona Papeş","Montgomery Slatkin","Motoo Kimura","Muller's ratchet","Nina Fefferman","Orou Gaoue","Paul Armsworth","Randy Small","Richard Dawkins","Richard Lewontin","Richard Owen","Ronald Fisher","Rosemary &amp; Peter Gillespie","Sebastian Stockmaier","Sergey Gavrilets","Sewall Wright","Stephanie Kivlin","Steven J. Gould","Theodosius Dobzhansky","Thomas Malthus","Udny Yule","Xingli Giam","Butler Act","Gary Scott","who won the Scopes trial","William Jennings Bryan","adaptationalism","adaptive radiation","allochronic speciation","allopatric speciation","anagenesis","ancestral trait","apomorphy","aptation","background extinction rate","biogeography","biological species concept","Burgess shale","Cambrian explosion","character displacement","chronospecies","cladistics","cladogenesis","comparative methods","continental drift","convergent evolution","Cope's rule","crown group","cryptic species","Deccan traps","derived trait","disruptive seelction","End-Permian extinction","eugenics","evolutionary arms race","exaptation","extinction","extinction rate","fossil record","geologic time scale","ghost lineages","Gondwana","gradualism","Great oxidation event","green beard","group selection","Haldane's rule","Hamilton's Rule","homology","homoplasy","inclusive fitness","island biogeography","island model","isolating mechanism","KT extinction","land bridge","Laurasia","left wall of minimal complexity","mating system","mechanical isolation","meme","mimicry","Modern Synthesis","MRCA","Müllerian mimicry","multifurcation","mutualism","natural selection","net diversification rate","non-independence","outgroup","paleontology","Pangaea","parallel evolution","parapatric speciation","paraphyly","parasitism","parsimony","parthenogenisis","peripatric speciation","phenetics","phylogeny","plesiomorphy","polyphyly","punctuated equilibrium","recapitulation","Red queen hypothesis","refugium","reproductive isolation","reticulate evolution","ring species","RNA world","saltation","spandrel","speciation","speciation rate","species selection","species sorting","stag hunt","stem group","sympatric speciation","symplesiomorphy","synapomorphy","taphonomic bias","taxon","trait","turnover rate","variance","vestigial","vicariance","vicariance biogeography","virulence","allele","allele frequency","Acromyrmex","Amborella","Amborella","ammonite","angiosperm","Anolis","Anolis","Anomalocaris","Archaea","bdelloid rotifers","bonobo","brachiopod","Buchnera","crinoid","Darwin's finches","diatoms","Dimetrodon","Dionaea muscipula","Ediacaran fauna","eubacteria","fig wasp","Gasterosteus aculeatus","Geospizinae","gingko","Hawaiian honeycreepers","HIV","Ichthyornis dispar","isopod","lycophytes","Maiasaura","Plasmodium","red panda","rift lake cichlids","silversword","spiny anteater","Strepsiptera","Thermus aquaticus","Tiktaalik","Tribolium","trilobite","tunicates","Welwischia","Wolbachia","16S","amber fossil","approximate Bayesian computation","Bayes rule","Bayesianism","binomial nomenclature","BLAST","body fossil","bootstrap","chloroplast DNA","CRISPR","fossil","frequentist","holotype","impression fossil","in silico","in situ","in vivo","inbred line","independent contrasts","likelihood","microsatellites","mitochondrial DNA","molecular clock","NCBI","neotype","nuclear DNA","paratype","PCR","posterior","prior","Robert FitzRoy","rock strata","Sanger sequencing","SNP","type specimen"],["general","general","general","general","general","general","general","general","general","general","general","general","general","general","general","general","general","general","general","general","general","general","general","general","general","general","general","general","general","general","general","general","general","general","general","general","general","general","general","general","general","general","general","general","general","general","general","general","general","general","general","general","general","general","general","microevolution","microevolution","microevolution","microevolution","microevolution","microevolution","microevolution","microevolution","microevolution","microevolution","microevolution","microevolution","microevolution","microevolution","microevolution","microevolution","microevolution","microevolution","microevolution","microevolution","microevolution","microevolution","microevolution","microevolution","microevolution","microevolution","microevolution","microevolution","microevolution","microevolution","microevolution","microevolution","microevolution","microevolution","microevolution","microevolution","microevolution","microevolution","microevolution","microevolution","microevolution","microevolution","microevolution","microevolution","microevolution","microevolution","microevolution","microevolution","microevolution","microevolution","microevolution","microevolution","microevolution","microevolution","microevolution","microevolution","microevolution","microevolution","microevolution","microevolution","microevolution","microevolution","microevolution","microevolution","microevolution","microevolution","microevolution","microevolution","microevolution","microevolution","microevolution","microevolution","microevolution","microevolution","microevolution","microevolution","microevolution","microevolution","microevolution","microevolution","microevolution","microevolution","microevolution","microevolution","microevolution","microevolution","microevolution","microevolution","microevolution","microevolution","microevolution","microevolution","microevolution","microevolution","microevolution","microevolution","microevolution","microevolution","microevolution","microevolution","microevolution","microevolution","microevolution","microevolution","microevolution","microevolution","microevolution","microevolution","microevolution","microevolution","microevolution","people","people","people","people","people","people","people","people","people","people","people","people","people","people","people","people","people","people","people","people","people","people","people","people","people","people","people","people","people","people","people","people","people","people","people","people","people","people","people","people","people","people","people","people","people","people","people","people","people","people","people","people","people","people","people","people","people","people","people","people","people","people","local interest","local interest","local interest","local interest","macroevolution","macroevolution","macroevolution","macroevolution","macroevolution","macroevolution","macroevolution","macroevolution","macroevolution","macroevolution","macroevolution","macroevolution","macroevolution","macroevolution","macroevolution","macroevolution","macroevolution","macroevolution","macroevolution","macroevolution","macroevolution","macroevolution","macroevolution","macroevolution","macroevolution","macroevolution","macroevolution","macroevolution","macroevolution","macroevolution","macroevolution","macroevolution","macroevolution","macroevolution","macroevolution","macroevolution","macroevolution","macroevolution","macroevolution","macroevolution","macroevolution","macroevolution","macroevolution","macroevolution","macroevolution","macroevolution","macroevolution","macroevolution","macroevolution","macroevolution","macroevolution","macroevolution","macroevolution","macroevolution","macroevolution","macroevolution","macroevolution","macroevolution","macroevolution","macroevolution","macroevolution","macroevolution","macroevolution","macroevolution","macroevolution","macroevolution","macroevolution","macroevolution","macroevolution","macroevolution","macroevolution","macroevolution","macroevolution","macroevolution","macroevolution","macroevolution","macroevolution","macroevolution","macroevolution","macroevolution","macroevolution","macroevolution","macroevolution","macroevolution","macroevolution","macroevolution","macroevolution","macroevolution","macroevolution","macroevolution","macroevolution","macroevolution","macroevolution","macroevolution","macroevolution","macroevolution","macroevolution","macroevolution","macroevolution","macroevolution","macroevolution","macroevolution","macroevolution","macroevolution","macroevolution","macroevolution","microevolution","microevolution","organism","organism","organism","organism","organism","organism","organism","organism","organism","organism","organism","organism","organism","organism","organism","organism","organism","organism","organism","organism","organism","organism","organism","organism","organism","organism","organism","organism","organism","organism","organism","organism","organism","organism","organism","organism","organism","organism","organism","organism","organism","organism","organism","tools","tools","tools","tools","tools","tools","tools","tools","tools","tools","tools","tools","tools","tools","tools","tools","tools","tools","tools","tools","tools","tools","tools","tools","tools","tools","tools","tools","tools","tools","tools","tools","tools","tools","tools","tools"]],"container":"<table class=\"display\">\n  <thead>\n    <tr>\n      <th> <\/th>\n      <th>Term<\/th>\n      <th>Type<\/th>\n    <\/tr>\n  <\/thead>\n<\/table>","options":{"pageLength":10,"columnDefs":[{"orderable":false,"targets":0}],"order":[],"autoWidth":false,"orderClasses":false}},"evals":[],"jsHooks":[]}</script>
</div>
</div>
</section>
<section id="things-to-change" class="level2" data-number="5">
<h2 data-number="5" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="things-to-change"><span class="header-section-number">5</span> Things to change</h2>
<p>Assuming I teach this again in 2024, some of the things I’d like to change:</p>
<ul>
<li>Continued revision of chosen papers: most worked ok, but some got in too much depth; also broader sampling of the literature</li>
<li>More use of overview slides early in the course</li>
<li>More frequent assessments: this could help students self-assess their knowledge over time</li>
<li>Encourage more evenness of classroom participation: everyone contributed, but the evenness could be improved</li>
<li>Add more contemporary human evolution, like the Framingham heart study</li>
<li>Other things students will suggest via their feedback forms</li>
</ul>
<hr>
<p>To subscribe, go to <a href="https://brianomeara.info/blog.xml" class="uri">https://brianomeara.info/blog.xml</a> in an RSS reader.</p>


</section>

<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-citation"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Citation</h2><div><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">BibTeX citation:</div><pre class="sourceCode code-with-copy quarto-appendix-bibtex"><code class="sourceCode bibtex">@online{o'meara2023,
  author = {O’Meara, Brian},
  title = {Grad Core Class in Evolutionary Biology, 2023 Edition},
  date = {2023-05-11},
  url = {https://brianomeara.info/posts/evolutioncore2023/},
  langid = {en}
}
</code></pre><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">For attribution, please cite this work as:</div><div id="ref-o'meara2023" class="csl-entry quarto-appendix-citeas">
O’Meara, Brian. 2023. <span>“Grad Core Class in Evolutionary Biology,
2023 Edition.”</span> May 11, 2023. <a href="https://brianomeara.info/posts/evolutioncore2023/">https://brianomeara.info/posts/evolutioncore2023/</a>.
</div></div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>teaching</category>
  <category>evolution</category>
  <category>core</category>
  <category>EEB511</category>
  <guid>https://brianomeara.info/posts/evolutioncore2023/</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 11 May 2023 04:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Joining Mastodon</title>
  <dc:creator>Brian O&#39;Meara</dc:creator>
  <link>https://brianomeara.info/posts/joiningmastodon/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>Social media keeps changing. I stopped using Facebook years ago (I still have an account, as my kids’ schools and some scientific orgs use it for communication, but I’m not active). I stopped using Twitter in November, 2022, though still keep an account to avoid impersonation (though people could find better accounts to impersonate). I’m now using this blog, but it’s unidirectional – you can read it or not, but I deliberately don’t have any way for people to comment.</p>
<p>I’m increasingly active on Mastodon, and various scientific societies and colleagues are now active there, too. Here’s an overview.</p>
<p>It’s probably easiest to think of Mastodon as</p>
<ol type="1">
<li>Similar to an email account: are you <code>example@gmail.com</code> or <code>example@harvard.edu</code>, but now it’s <code>@example@mastodon.social</code> or <code>@example@sauropods.win</code>. People on one provider (“instance” in Mastodon jargon) can generally see information from people on others, unless one of them has put a block on it (in the same way that your email provider may block emails from certain spammy domains).</li>
<li>But set up so that by default you can see what everyone on your instance posts.</li>
</ol>
<section id="it-is-not-a-11-twitter-replacement" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="it-is-not-a-11-twitter-replacement">It is not a 1:1 Twitter replacement</h3>
<ul>
<li>You can search for hashtags but not post content otherwise (people sometimes make sites to allow full search, but this is apparently against the norms and there’s pushback)</li>
<li>The algorithm is based on recency only. That <em>is</em> an algorithm, of course – it says people who are active at the same time you are should be prioritized. And it’s better than many other algorithms in social media (“prioritize things that make people angry”, “prioritize posts by the owner”, “prioritize people with the wealth to pay for it”, etc.). But I’d love to see something that prioritizes users I engage with the most even if they have different sleep schedules.</li>
<li>You can “like” or “boost”. Like tells the poster you like something – it does nothing for ranking that or later posts, for you or for others. Boost sends the post to all of your followers and onto your general instance feed.</li>
<li>There is no quote-tweeting. You can reply, or you can write a new post that has a link to the old, but the whole “wrap another post with your commentary” doesn’t exist (yet). This is seen as a way by those influencial in Mastodon as a way to prevent bullying, but taking a screen shot of a post is still possible.</li>
<li>Posts can be edited, easily.</li>
<li>There is a strong culture of including alternative text on images so that those who cannot see the images well know what they are. This is a good thing; do it.</li>
<li>Due to how the instances are organized, they can block one another (“defederate”), just as your email provider could block all emails from a certain domain. This can be a way of blocking from instances that don’t have good moderation.</li>
<li>Anyone can set up an instance; it’s easier than setting up an email provider. However, it’s a lot of responsibility: moderating is HARD.</li>
<li>You can change your instance easily. It’s like moving from hotmail to gmail: you can move your contacts (people you follow), but your posts won’t follow.</li>
<li>Moderation is up to each instance (similar to reddit subreddits). Some do a good job, others do not. And sometimes people may disagree on what moves are important to them. For example, there was a debate a few months ago about defederating from a journalism instance: a user posted a very bad article from a major US newspaper on the instance: should other instances block this whole instance (which has journalists from many media sources) since they allow this sort of post, or should it still be allowed to communicate? The person administrating your server decides (though you may still block individual people on your own).</li>
<li>It still lacks some features important for safety: see <a href="https://hachyderm.io/@mekkaokereke/110272951321280411">this thread</a>, for example. Twitter was not perfect, either, and media reports that it is getting even worse, but this does not mean that Mastodon is doing everything right.</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="which-instance-to-join" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="which-instance-to-join">Which instance to join?</h3>
<ul>
<li>One of the biggest, and the one run by the main developer, is <a href="https://mastodon.social/about">mastodon.social</a>. It has (as of the date of this post) about 212,000 users. It is a general instance. It’s the one I’m currently on: <a href="https://mastodon.social/@omearabrian">https://mastodon.social/<span class="citation" data-cites="omearabrian">@omearabrian</span></a> . I like it because I use social media to attempt to have reach. It’s also likely stable – it won’t go down if a check bounces or if an admin loses interest. However, see if its moderation works for you. For social media, moderation is a big deal, and it can cover things like hate speech but also things like tone-policing; ignoring vs confronting racism, sexism, homophobia; whether bots are allowed; and more.</li>
<li>A lot of people and journals in my academic sphere are on <a href="https://ecoevo.social/about">https://ecoevo.social/about</a>, which is moderated by <a href="https://www.normalesup.org/~asimon/">Dr.&nbsp;Alexis Simon</a>. It has 1,900 users, including groups like <a href="https://ecoevo.social/@SystBiol">https://ecoevo.social/<span class="citation" data-cites="SystBiol">@SystBiol</span></a>, <a href="https://ecoevo.social/@ASNAmNat">https://ecoevo.social/<span class="citation" data-cites="ASNAmNat">@ASNAmNat</span></a>, <a href="https://ecoevo.social/@sse_evolution">https://ecoevo.social/<span class="citation" data-cites="sse_evolution">@sse_evolution</span></a>, and <a href="https://ecoevo.social/@evol_mtg">https://ecoevo.social/<span class="citation" data-cites="evol_mtg">@evol_mtg</span></a>. It’s also a reasonable place to start.</li>
<li>There’s an instance for bots: <a href="https://botsin.space/about">https://botsin.space/about</a>. I haven’t set up anything there yet, but stay tuned.</li>
<li>There are a lot of other instances. You can find info at <a href="https://joinmastodon.org/servers">https://joinmastodon.org/servers</a>. Don’t overthink it: at this point, it’s like choosing between gmail and yahoo for email. There is a difference, but not as big a difference as between having email and not having email.</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="how-to-find-people" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="how-to-find-people">How to find people?</h3>
<ul>
<li>Searching for hashtags is good. You can get a tweetdeck-like interface by going to Preferences -&gt; Appearance -&gt; Enable advanced web interface and turning it on; then you can have columns dedicated to particular hashtags. See who is posting interesting stuff.</li>
<li>You can see who other people are following. I’m following <a href="https://mastodon.social/@omearabrian/following">these people</a> (note that following does not mean endorsement or agreement, just that I want to hear what they say).</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="how-to-use" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="how-to-use">How to use?</h3>
<ul>
<li>There are dedicated apps (some free, some paid). I mostly just use the web instance.</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="automate-all-the-things" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="automate-all-the-things">Automate all the things</h3>
<p>Though I’m on mastodon.social, many in my community are on ecoevo.social. So I wanted to follow them all. Here’s R code to do that, using <code>rtoot</code>:</p>
<p>Schoch David and Chan Chung-hong (2023) rtoot: Collecting and analyzing Mastodon data. R package version 0.3.0, <a href="https://github.com/schochastics/rtoot">https://github.com/schochastics/rtoot</a>.</p>
<p>Note that I assume this is all ok, and I have a pause to keep from overwhelming anything, but 1) you will be rate-limited at some point and will have to restart after waiting a bit (but it’ll only follow new people, so you won’t start from scratch), and 2) mass-following could be a scammy thing to do (i.e., someone could mass-follow everyone on a huge instance to try to game getting more followers). I like following ecoevo.social people because mastodon.social’s feed is huge and has lots of things not that interesting to me, while ecoeco.social (and a smaller instance, sauropods.win) does have a lot of interesting users, so I want to follow them. It also hopefully encourages new users: “someone want to hear what you say!”</p>
<pre><code>library(rtoot)

instance_name &lt;- 'ecoevo.social'

my_following &lt;- read.csv("~/Downloads/following_accounts.csv")

user_count &lt;- get_instance_general(instance_name)$stats$user_count
number_of_calls &lt;- min(ceiling(user_count/40),4000)
for (i in sequence(number_of_calls)) {
  people &lt;- get_instance_directory(instance_name,offset=40*(i-1), limit=40, local=TRUE, order="new")
  for (user in people$username) {
    full_user &lt;- paste0(user, '@', instance_name)
    print(full_user)
    if(full_user %in% my_following$Account.address) {
      print("Already following, not going to add")
    } else {
      system(paste0('toot follow ', user, '@', instance_name), timeout=30)
    }
    Sys.sleep(10)
  }
}</code></pre>
<hr>
<p>To subscribe, go to <a href="https://brianomeara.info/blog.xml" class="uri">https://brianomeara.info/blog.xml</a> in an RSS reader.</p>


</section>

<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-citation"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Citation</h2><div><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">BibTeX citation:</div><pre class="sourceCode code-with-copy quarto-appendix-bibtex"><code class="sourceCode bibtex">@online{o'meara2023,
  author = {O’Meara, Brian},
  title = {Joining {Mastodon}},
  date = {2023-04-30},
  url = {https://brianomeara.info/posts/joiningmastodon/},
  langid = {en}
}
</code></pre><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">For attribution, please cite this work as:</div><div id="ref-o'meara2023" class="csl-entry quarto-appendix-citeas">
O’Meara, Brian. 2023. <span>“Joining Mastodon.”</span> April 30, 2023.
<a href="https://brianomeara.info/posts/joiningmastodon/">https://brianomeara.info/posts/joiningmastodon/</a>.
</div></div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>social media</category>
  <guid>https://brianomeara.info/posts/joiningmastodon/</guid>
  <pubDate>Sun, 30 Apr 2023 04:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>An alternative to CRAN for phylogenetics</title>
  <dc:creator>Brian O&#39;Meara</dc:creator>
  <link>https://brianomeara.info/posts/phylotasticruniverse/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>For installing R packages, <a href="https://cran.r-project.org/">CRAN</a> is the main place to go. It’s a fantastic free service that checks R packages to make sure they meet standards and then compiles them for multiple architectures. It’s largely a <a href="https://cran.r-project.org/CRAN_team.htm">volunteer effort</a> and is important to keep packages working together. <a href="https://www.bioconductor.org/">Bioconductor</a> is a more specialized repository. Getting a package to pass the checks to go on CRAN has long been a point of pride, and it does lead to higher quality packages, though with odd constraints (the overall package size must be small, all examples must run very quickly, and more).</p>
<p>However, <em>keeping</em> a package on CRAN is an issue. Requirements keep changing: will this package work on the development version of R on Debian with a clang compiler, Fedora with a gcc compiler, Mac with both arm and x86 chips, Windows, etc. and continue to do so as operating systems, hardware, and compilers change? For example, our <a href="https://cran.r-project.org/web/checks/check_results_hisse.html"><em>hisse</em></a> package was removed briefly from CRAN in spring 2023 (it’s back online) because of an issue where, while the package passed all checks for Mac, Windows, Linux, all R-devel, R-patched, R-release, and R-oldrel, it would generate a warning if compiled using the <code>-Wlto-type-mismatch</code> flag to GCC. Our code hadn’t changed, and this wouldn’t have affected any users, but CRAN gave us two weeks to fix the warning. We didn’t do it on time, so it was archived, which <em>does</em> affect users (making it impossible for most users on Mac or Windows to use it, for example, as they don’t have compilers installed).</p>
<p>If you are part of an ecosystem, there are further risks. Many phylogenetics packages depend or import <a href="https://cran.r-project.org/web/packages/geiger/index.html"><code>geiger</code></a> – CRAN removed that package, and then two weeks later would have also archived every package that depends on it. Geiger’s authors got it restored in time, but it shows how brittle CRAN’s policies make our community. It’s like the <a href="https://xkcd.com/2347/">Randall Munroe XKCD cartoon</a>:</p>
<p><img src="https://imgs.xkcd.com/comics/dependency_2x.png" class="img-fluid" alt="XKCD cartoon showing a stack of boxes labeled 'All modern digital infrastructure' carefullly balancing on a small box labeled 'A project some random person in Nebraska has been thanklessly maintaining since 2003'"></p>
<p>but with the poor maintainer in Nebraska putting the whole ecosystem at risk if they take two weeks off and there is a new requirement in the interim.</p>
<p>The nature of academia makes this even more precarious. A student might work on a package for their dissertation and others could find it very useful. There is no guarantee that the student remains in the field: it’s not unusual for someone to go into teaching, or working at a nonprofit, or working for a company, and even the weak incentive of getting more citations is no longer sufficiently relevant for them to volunteer their time to meet changing CRAN standards. Ongoing maintenance would be ideal for the field, but it is a high bar.</p>
<p>Fortunately, rOpenSci has made an alternative: <a href="https://ropensci.org/r-universe/">r-universe</a>. This creates a place where R packages can be built automatically for different platforms, just as CRAN does, but in nearly real time. If a package is in an open source repository (the best known is GitHub), and the r-universe instance knows about it, it will try to compile it. Thus, even if something goes off CRAN, students taking a class can likely still install it from r-universe.</p>
<p>To help our community, I’ve created an instance for phylogenetics. The instance is at https://phylotastic.r-universe.dev/ . Information on how to use it is at http://phylotastic.org/phylotastic.r-universe.dev/. For the packages, I’ve used everything from the <a href="https://cran.r-project.org/web/views/Phylogenetics.html">CRAN task view for phylogenetics</a> (something I maintained for over a decade, now taken over by <a href="https://williamgearty.com/">Dr.&nbsp;William Gearty</a> who has assembled a team to keep it going), as well as other packages used in phylogenetics in R, including packages in development.</p>
<section id="using-the-universe" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="using-the-universe">Using the universe</h3>
<p>To use the most recent available version of each package:</p>
<pre><code>options(repos = c(
  phylotastic = 'https://phylotastic.r-universe.dev',
  CRAN = 'https://cloud.r-project.org')
 )</code></pre>
<p>This will check the phylotastic r-universe, and only go to CRAN for packages that are not there.</p>
<p>To use the CRAN package if available, then use phylotastic as a backup:</p>
<pre><code>options(repos = c(
  CRAN = 'https://cloud.r-project.org',
  phylotastic = 'https://phylotastic.r-universe.dev')
 )</code></pre>
</section>
<section id="why-phylotastic" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="why-phylotastic">Why “phylotastic”?</h3>
<p>Phylotastic started as an idea launched at the [US] National Evolutionary Synthesis Center, NESCent, in 2012. Over hackathons and other events, and later an NSF grant (written by Arlin Stoltzfus, Enrico Pontelli, and me) it resulted in various tools for phylogenetics (includng http://datelife.opentreeoflife.org/ ). I wanted to keep that connection, not least so that people could use phylotastic R packages even when there are CRAN hiccups.</p>
<hr>
<p>To subscribe, go to <a href="https://brianomeara.info/blog.xml" class="uri">https://brianomeara.info/blog.xml</a> in an RSS reader.</p>


</section>

<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-citation"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Citation</h2><div><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">BibTeX citation:</div><pre class="sourceCode code-with-copy quarto-appendix-bibtex"><code class="sourceCode bibtex">@online{o'meara2023,
  author = {O’Meara, Brian},
  title = {An Alternative to {CRAN} for Phylogenetics},
  date = {2023-04-23},
  url = {https://brianomeara.info/posts/phylotasticruniverse/},
  langid = {en}
}
</code></pre><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">For attribution, please cite this work as:</div><div id="ref-o'meara2023" class="csl-entry quarto-appendix-citeas">
O’Meara, Brian. 2023. <span>“An Alternative to CRAN for
Phylogenetics.”</span> April 23, 2023. <a href="https://brianomeara.info/posts/phylotasticruniverse/">https://brianomeara.info/posts/phylotasticruniverse/</a>.
</div></div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>R</category>
  <category>rbloggers</category>
  <category>reproducibility</category>
  <guid>https://brianomeara.info/posts/phylotasticruniverse/</guid>
  <pubDate>Sun, 23 Apr 2023 04:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Fossils do not help fix diversification parameter estimates</title>
  <dc:creator>Brian O&#39;Meara</dc:creator>
  <link>https://brianomeara.info/posts/fossilsdonothelp/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>Jeremy Beaulieu and I have a <a href="https://doi.org/10.1093/sysbio/syac049">paper</a> in <em>Systematic Biology</em> on the impact of fossils on estimating diversification rates. There has been a lot of interest in the fossilized birth-death process, FBD (<a href="https://doi-org.utk.idm.oclc.org/10.1016/j.jtbi.2010.09.010">Stadler 2010</a>), and with the rediscovery in the field that diversification methods might be telling tales signifying nothing, Jeremy and I thought about how the FBD might help. We know fossils help, a lot, with things like ancestral state reconstruction and dating trees: knowing about fossils might help with diversification processes (especially with parameters relating to extinction).</p>
<p>Jeremy implemented it in <a href="https://speciationextinction.info/"><em>hisse</em></a>. One thing we discussed in the implementation is how there are two kinds of fossils FBD uses:</p>
<p><img src="https://brianomeara.info/posts/fossilsdonothelp/fbd_fig1.png" class="img-fluid" alt="Figure 1 from Beaulieu and O'Meara (2022), showing the distribution of fossils on two trees. The left tree shows the sampled fossils; the right plot shows the distinction between parent fossils (ones that have a descendant sample, either a fossil or a tip) and childless fossils (terminal fossils)."></p>
<p>One is terminals that are fossils with no sampled descendants (‘<em>m</em>’ type). The other is parent fossils (‘<em>k</em>’ type): they have a sampled descendant on the tree (which could be a fossil or extant tip). We worried that the methods assume equal probability of sampling for all these fossils, but that empiricists might not be generating data that meet these assumptions. For example, one might put a single <em>T. rex</em> fossil specimen on the tree, but would one put on every individual? All but the most recent one would be parent fossils, and we suspected they could be missing.</p>
<p>We made predictions based on the math, but it’s also useful to test with simulations. Simulations can be tricky when testing models: all models are simplifications of the world that can fail if the world is complex in the wrong ways. One can always write “method X fails under real world conditions Y” if conditions are extreme enough, but that doesn’t necessarily mean that it will fail in everyday use. So in setting up our simulations for this study, we chose to make it biased towards FBD working and based on realistic parameters. One way we biased it was including mass extinctions: methods using only tip data should do terribly for that, and fossils might help.</p>
<p>The key result is in Figure 4:</p>
<p><img src="https://brianomeara.info/posts/fossilsdonothelp/fbd_fig4b.png" class="img-fluid" alt="Figure 4b from Beaulieu and O'Meara (2022), showing the estimated turnover rate with different true turnover rates and different way of running the analysis. It shows a grouping of box plots, with red lines showing the true values. Using extant data only performed far better than using extant with sampled fossil tips; using all the parent and terminal fossils performed about as well as no fossils at all."></p>
<p>Using just the extant tips (dark purple) performed better than using extant tips and fossil tips (white bars) and similarly to using all the fossils, which based on limited data (see our Figure 3) is rarely done empirically. This surprised us: we were expecting fossils to pretty clearly help except when there was a bias to only use tip fossils. It is frankly a little disappointing that even perfect fossil data (we assumed fossil positions were known exactly, for example) does not help noticeably with estimating diversification models (though they remain important for dating, for ancestral state reconstruction, and likely for tree inference, as well).</p>
<p>To see all the code we used, go to https://github.com/thej022214/Fossils_impact_BO .</p>
<p>To see how to use fossils in <em>hisse</em>, including in models with and without traits, look at Jeremy’s vignette: https://speciationextinction.info/articles/adding_fossils.html . Based on our analysis, fossils don’t help much with diversification, but you can prove us wrong for your data, and you can use these tools for things like looking at correlations where fossils might indeed help.</p>
<hr>
<p>To subscribe, go to <a href="https://brianomeara.info/blog.xml" class="uri">https://brianomeara.info/blog.xml</a> in an RSS reader.</p>



<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents" id="quarto-citation"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Citation</h2><div><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">BibTeX citation:</div><pre class="sourceCode code-with-copy quarto-appendix-bibtex"><code class="sourceCode bibtex">@online{o'meara2023,
  author = {O’Meara, Brian},
  title = {Fossils Do Not Help Fix Diversification Parameter Estimates},
  date = {2023-04-22},
  url = {https://brianomeara.info/posts/fossilsdonothelp/},
  langid = {en}
}
</code></pre><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">For attribution, please cite this work as:</div><div id="ref-o'meara2023" class="csl-entry quarto-appendix-citeas">
O’Meara, Brian. 2023. <span>“Fossils Do Not Help Fix Diversification
Parameter Estimates.”</span> April 22, 2023. <a href="https://brianomeara.info/posts/fossilsdonothelp/">https://brianomeara.info/posts/fossilsdonothelp/</a>.
</div></div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>fossil</category>
  <category>R</category>
  <category>hisse</category>
  <category>misse</category>
  <category>diversification</category>
  <category>simulation</category>
  <category>publication</category>
  <guid>https://brianomeara.info/posts/fossilsdonothelp/</guid>
  <pubDate>Sat, 22 Apr 2023 04:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
